<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><agreement size="Small" period="2008-2010" alignement="left">
	<article id="article-1">
		
		<title langue="en">
			PURPOSE OF THE COLLECTIVE AGREEMENT
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The purpose of this Agreement is to establish and maintain harmonious relationships between the University, its employees and the Institute, and to set out the employment conditions on which agreement has been reached through the collective bargaining process.
			</paragraph-numbered>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<article id="article-2">
		
		<title langue="en">
			DEFINITIONS
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				<strong>
					Agreement (Convention)
				</strong>
				This collective agreement.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				<strong>
					Continuous service (Service continu)
				</strong>
				A period of service without more than thirteen (13) consecutive weeks of uninterrupted employment relationship. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				<strong>
					Demotion (Rétrogradation)
				</strong>
				The permanent appointment of an employee from one regular position to another regular position at a lower salary grade. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				<strong>
					Employee (Employé)
				</strong>
				Any person covered by the Bargaining Unit and governed by the Agreement.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				<strong>
					Employee representative (Représentant des employés)
				</strong>
				<strong>
				</strong>
				An Institute Stewart who is a member of the Group, or a member of the Group executive committee or a representative who is an Institute employee. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				<strong>
					Employment on a special project (Emploi pour un projet spécial
				</strong>
				) An employment contract for a special project with a maximum determinate duration of three (3) years.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				<strong>
					Fiscal year (Année financière)
				</strong>
				The period corresponding to the University fiscal year, i.e. from May 1 of the current year to April 30 of the subsequent year.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				<strong>
					Full-time employee (Employé à temps complet)
				</strong>
				An employee who holds a full-time position.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				<strong>
					Full-time employment (Emploi à temps complet)
				</strong>
				Employment at 35 hours per week.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				<strong>
					Immediate supervisor (Supérieur immédiat)
				</strong>
				The line supervisor who holds a position at a rank higher than that of an employee and to whom an employee reports. This person is the first level of authority for an employee. When an employee has both a functional line supervisor and an administrative line supervisor, the immediate supervisor is the administrative line supervisor. The title of the latter's position is identified in the job description. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				<strong>
					Liaison officer (Agent de liaison)
				</strong>
				The Director, HR Client Advisory Service or the Assistant Director, Labour Relations, or their delegates, who alone are empowered to deal with any problems relating to labour relations, discussions or negotiations and agreements with the Institute.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				<strong>
					Part-time employee (Employé à temps partiel)
				</strong>
				An employee who holds a part-time position.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				<strong>
					Part-time employment (Emploi à temps partiel
				</strong>
				) Employment at more than 24 hours a week but less than 35 hours a week.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				<strong>
					Personnel file (Dossier personnel)
				</strong>
				An employee's official file is that retained at the Human Resources Service. It is agreed that administrative units may retain administrative documents and that any such documents kept elsewhere or in any other manner are not considered part of the official file. After making an appointment with the Human Resources Service, an employee has the right to consult his file that holds the University and to be accompanied by an Institute representative.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				<strong>
					Promotion (Promotion)
				</strong>
				A permanent appointment of an employee from one regular position to another regular position at a higher salary grade.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				<strong>
					Regular employee (Employé régulier)
				</strong>
				An employee who holds a regular position.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				<strong>
					Regular employment (Emploi régulier)
				</strong>
				A regular indeterminate position
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				<strong>
					Temporary assignment (Affectation temporaire)
				</strong>
				The assignment of a regular employee to a term employment or to replace an employee in a regular position while the former retains his substantive position.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				<strong>
					Term employee (Employé à terme (temporaire)
				</strong>
				An employee who holds a term position.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				<strong>
					Term employment (Emploi à terme (temporaire)
				</strong>
				A determinate work contract.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				<strong>
					Transfer (Mutation)
				</strong>
				The permanent appointment of an employee from one regular position to another regular position at the same salary grade . 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				<strong>
					The Bargaining unit (L'Unité de négociation
				</strong>
				) The unit described in the certification dated January 25, 2008, and for which the Institute is certified to represent (number 3320-06-R).
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				<strong>
					The Group (Groupe)
				</strong>
				The affiliate of the Institute comprised of University employees who are members for the Group of the Information Technology Professionals of the University of Ottawa.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				<strong>
					The Institute (L'Institut)
				</strong>
				The union, the Professional Institute of the Public Service of Canada.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				<strong>
					The Parties (Les parties)
				</strong>
				The University and the Institute.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				<strong>
					The University (L’Université)
				</strong>
				The employer, the University of Ottawa.
			</paragraph>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<article id="article-3">
		
		<title langue="en">
			OFFICIAL TEXTS
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Both the English and the French texts of this Agreement are official. In this Agreement, the use of the masculine gender includes the feminine without discrimination. In view of the fact that the conditions of employment for the employees in this bargaining unit are set out in this Agreement, it is understood that in the event of contradiction between a provision in this Agreement and any other custom, rule, policy or practice of the University, the provisions in this Agreement prevails.
			</paragraph-numbered>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<article id="article-4">
		
		<title langue="en">
			HARASSMENT AND DISCRIMINATION
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				There must be no discrimination or harassment against any employee based on any prohibited grounds listed in the Ontario Human Rights Code.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The following definitions apply for the purpose of this article: 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			<list type="Alpha">
				
				<item langue="en">
					Discrimination on prohibited grounds: Discrimination on prohibited grounds is a distinction that, whether intentional or not but based on grounds related to the personal characteristics of an individual or group, has the effect of erecting barriers or creating obligations or disadvantages that withhold or limit access to privileges; advantages; or political, social or economic rights available to other members of society. 
				</item>
				<list type="Roman">
					
					<item langue="en">
						Intentional or malicious discrimination is an avowed, conscious or deliberate behaviour designed to produce unjust or inequitable treatment. It may involve harassment.
					</item>
					
					<item langue="en">
						Unequal or differential treatment consists of treating individuals differently than others on prohibited grounds.
					</item>
					
					<item langue="en">
						Systemic discrimination is a form of discrimination that is integrated into an organization’s rules and practices and is therefore self-perpetuating. It is practised consciously or unconsciously and has the effect of intentionally or unintentionally excluding individuals or groups.
					</item>
				</list>
				
				<item langue="en">
					Harassment on prohibited grounds
				</item>
				<list type="Roman">
					
					<item langue="en">
						Vexatious comments or conduct, based on one or more prohibited grounds, that is known or ought reasonably to be known to be unwelcome; or
					</item>
					
					<item langue="en">
						Comments or behaviour that may be perceived as harmful or as having a negative effect on the work or study environment (poisoned environment).
					</item>
				</list>
				
				<item langue="en">
					Sexual harassment
				</item>
				<list type="Roman">
					
					<item langue="en">
						Unwanted sexual attention from a person who knows or ought reasonably to know that such attention is unwanted; or
					</item>
					
					<item langue="en">
						Implied or expressed promise of reward for complying with a sexually oriented request; or
					</item>
					
					<item langue="en">
						Unwanted sexual attention from a person who knows or ought reasonably to know that such attention is unwanted; or
					</item>
					
					<item langue="en">
						A sexual relationship that constitutes an abuse of power in a relationship of trust; or
					</item>
					
					<item langue="en">
						A sexually oriented comment or behaviour that may reasonably be perceived to create a negative psychological and emotional environment for work or study (poisoned environment).
					</item>
				</list>
				
				<item langue="en">
					Personal harassment
				</item>
				<list type="Roman">
					
					<item langue="en">
						A course of comments or actions directed toward a specific person or group of persons that is known, or ought reasonably to be known, to be unwelcome and which:
					</item>
					<list type="Numeric">
						
						<item langue="en">
							intimidates, humiliates, undermines or dominates the other person by belittling, embarrassing or demeaning them; or
						</item>
						
						<item langue="en">
							involves the use of abusive or threatening language, verbal or physical threats or any form of physical assault.
						</item>
					</list>
				</list>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				A single incident alone may constitute harassment under the Ontario Human Rights Code.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Each employee has the right to work in an environment free of harassment and discrimination. The parties, including employees, are responsible for fostering and maintaining an atmosphere free of harassment and discrimination at the University. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The parties, including employees, further undertake to collaborate in a spirit of respect throughout the implementation of reasonable accommodation measures.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The University will not discriminate against any employee, nor harm him or impose restrictions on him or use coercion against him because he is a member of the Institute.. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The provisions set out in these articles in no way affect an employee's right to exercise the remedies open to him under the Ontario Human Rights Code within the time frames set out therein. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The Institute and the University are jointly committed to the principles of employment equity and to integrating these principles within the workplace. Consistent with the requirements of the Federal Contractors Program, the University of Ottawa's Employment Equity Program applies to the following designated groups: women, visible minorities, persons with disabilities and Aboriginal communities.
			</paragraph-numbered>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<article id="article-5">
		
		<title langue="en">
			MANAGEMENT RIGHTS
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				All the functions, rights, powers and authority that the University has not specifically abridged, delegated or modified by this Agreement are recognized by the Institute as being retained by the University. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<article id="article-6">
		
		<title langue="en">
			RIGHTS AND OBLIGATIONS OF THE PARTIES
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Strike or lockout 
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				The University must not declare a lockout and the Institute must not call for any form of strike, work stoppage or slowdown for the term of this Agreement. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				In the event of a strike or lockout affecting another University union, an employee does not lose any wages provided he has complied with University or Protection Services directives and he is not be required to perform the duties of employees who are on strike or in lockout. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Policies
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				The University informs the Institute of any general policies or regulations affecting employees in the bargaining unit, insofar as possible, in advance or no later than the time it informs its employees. The Institute may formulate observations pertaining to them. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Other University personnel
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Except in the case of strike or lockout, University personnel not included in the bargaining unit are not to perform duties normally carried out by employees covered by the Agreement, other than:
			</paragraph>
			<list type="Dash">
				
				<item langue="en">
					in an emergency or to provide an indispensable service where there is a shortage of employees qualified to perform the task;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					for employee training;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					where an employee hired on a fixed-term contract to perform these duties has not yet completed the twelve (12) months of continuous service required to join the bargaining unit;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					where these duties are performed by consultants working on special projects;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					where these duties are subcontracted in accordance with Article 40;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					where these duties fall within the scope of a confidential position excluded from the bargaining unit on these grounds. 
				</item>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Specific agreement 
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				No specific agreement between an employee and the University in respect of working conditions differing from the conditions prescribed in this Agreement is valid without the Institute's written approval.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					University representative
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				The University acts through its HR Client Advisory Services when dealing with the Institute regarding any labour relations, discussions, collective bargaining and agreement issues. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Copies of Agreement
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				The University sends an electronic copy of the ratified Agreement to the Institute for review within sixty (60) days of its ratification by both parties.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				An electronic copy of the Agreement is published on the Human Resources website.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				A hard copy of the Agreement is sent to employees who request it from the Human Resources Service (maximum of 150 copies). 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				A hard copy of the current Agreement is given to new employees wishing a copy at the time they are hired.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				All costs associated with printing and copying the Agreement covering Institute members are borne by the University. The parties agree on the composition and presentation of the Agreement before it is printed. Ten (10) copies of the printed Agreement are provided to the Institute.
			</paragraph>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<article id="article-7">
		
		<title langue="en">
			UNION RECOGNITION
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Sole bargaining agent
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				The University of Ottawa (University) recognizes the Professional Institute of the Public Service of Canada (Institute) as the exclusive bargaining agent and representative of the employees covered by the bargaining unit described in the certificate delivered in Toronto on January 25, 2008, by the Ontario Labour Relations Board (3320-06-R), and further recognizes that the Institute possesses all the rights inherent in such certification. The certificate and the list of exclusions issued by the Ontario Labour Relations Board, including the appendices containing the title and number of the position occupied at that time, are published on the University and the Institute websites. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Excluded positions
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Where the University creates a position it feels should be excluded from the bargaining unit on one of the grounds prescribed in section 1(3)(b) of the Ontario Labour Relations Act, 1995 (OLRA), the University informs the Institute and provides the Institute with a detailed description of the position and its duties. The Institute has thirty (30) days from the date said notice is received in which to object. Such a dispute shall be brought before an arbitrator in accordance with the provisions of Article 14. The burden of proof at arbitration therefore rests with the University.
			</paragraph>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<article id="article-8">
		
		<title langue="en">
			TRADE UNION REGIME AND UNION DUES
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Union membership
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				As a condition of employment, all employees will join the Institute in order to maintain their employment. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Union dues
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				The University deducts from every employee's salary for each pay period ending on the 15th day of the month any regular or special fee established by the Institute. Before the date on which a new union fee or new rate comes into effect, the Institute sends written notice at least thirty (30) days before the implementation of the new union fee. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				These deductions are made in the pay period of the month following the start of employment. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				The University sends to the Institute any special fees deducted by the fifteenth (15th) day of the month following the month during which the fees were deducted. Such remittance is accompanied by a list identifying:
			</paragraph>
			<list type="Dash">
				
				<item langue="en">
					surname and given nam; 
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					employee number;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					annual base salary;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					amount deducted for the period;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					total amount deducted since January 1 of the current year;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					class of position; 
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					full-time equivalent (FTE);
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					home address; 
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					uOttawa email address;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					preferred language of correspondence;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					status (regular or term employee);
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					seniority date;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					faculty or service and department;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					INTRA address;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					effective date of the employee's departure, if applicable, and the reasons for the departure as they appear in the Record of Employment. 
				</item>
				
				<paragraph langue="en">
					The list is sent in the appropriate electronic format. 
				</paragraph>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				In the event that union dues are not collected because of an administrative error, the University undertakes, upon written notification by the Institute to that effect, to collect the amount not remitted within thirty (30) days of said notice. Monthly union fee deductions are doubled up until the full unpaid amount has been collected. The Institute notifies the employee.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The University does not collect any union fees in the following cases:
			</paragraph-numbered>
			<list type="Dash">
				
				<item langue="en">
					the employee is on unpaid leave;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					the employee is on maternity or parental leave;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					the employee is on extended sick leave; or
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					the employee is receiving benefits from the Workplace Safety and Insurance Board (WSIB).
				</item>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The Institute indemnifies and holds the University harmless from any claims, suits, attachments and any form of liability as a result of deductions authorized by the Institute and any information stated in 8.2.
			</paragraph-numbered>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<article id="article-9">
		
		<title langue="en">
			GROUP ACCESS TO UNIVERSITY SERVICES
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Mail, electronic mail and miscellaneous services 
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				After receiving prior approval from the Labour Relations sector, Human Resources Service, the Institute may send out notices or invitations by internal electronic mail. Such communications are addressed to bargaining unit employees personally.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				The Institute may use the electronic mail address issued by the University to its staff (@uottawa.ca) to communicate with its members.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				In all cases, the Institute adheres to University policy on the content of documents, in terms of style, respect and politeness between the parties.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Subject to recovery of operating costs, the Institute may use certain University services, namely internal mail and photocopying of documents. It is agreed that priority is given to work carried out to meet the University's obligations with regards to the University's student-related or administrative operations.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Meeting rooms
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				The Institute has access to the University's classrooms and conference rooms, subject to the same rules governing use, booking and costs as apply to internal University groups, in accordance with the rules of the Conventions and Reservations sector. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Group office
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				The Group is provided an office free of charge, and its location, equipment and services are negotiated between the parties. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					External representatives
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				The representatives of the Institute who are not included in the bargaining unit have access to the University for the purpose of consulting with the Group managers, and participating in Group meetings, negotiations and consultations with the University.
			</paragraph>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<article id="article-10">
		
		<title langue="en">
			LEAVE FOR UNION BUSINESS
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Paid leave credits
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				A total of nine hundred and ten (910) hours of paid leave credits per calendar year are available for use by employee representatives who are members of the bargaining unit to attend to union business. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Each quarter, the Group president, or the vice-president in the absence of the president, provides the University with a schedule of leave credits to be used in order for staffing the union office. The scheduled dates may be changed to accommodate a holiday or to replace a scheduled employee representative who is a member of the bargaining unit who will be absent. Changes are to be made in accordance with the provisions stipulated in 10.7.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				The University provides the Group president with a monthly statement of any leave credits used in excess of those set out in the schedule. 
			</paragraph>
			<paragraph langue="en">
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Collective bargaining
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				In addition to the leave referred to in 10.01, the University grants leave, without loss of pay or benefits, to two (2) employees designated by the Institute to participate in negotiations to renew the Agreement. Additional employees may be granted leave in accordance with 10.1 or 10.6. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Joint committees
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Employees required to sit on joint committees are granted leave in addition to the leave referred to in 10.1, without loss of pay or benefits. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
			</paragraph-numbered>
			<list type="Alpha">
				
				<item langue="en">
					An employee representative who is a member of the bargaining unit and who wishes to grant leave to an employee in order for the employee to meet with the employee representative during working hours obtains prior authorization from the Human Resources Service, Labour Relations sector. The Human Resources Service in turn informs the employee's immediate supervisor of the absence.
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					An employee requesting leave to meet with an employee representative who is a member of the bargaining unit about a labour-related matter obtains prior authorization from the immediate supervisor or from the Human Resources Service, Labour Relations sector, which in turn informs the employee's immediate supervisor of the absence. 
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					Time used by an employee representative who is member of the bargaining unit to meet with an employee under the provisions of 10.4 (a) and (b) is deducted from the leave credits referred to in 10.1. The Group president, or the vice-president in the absence of the president, is responsible for these leave requests. 
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					The University must make every attempt to accommodate these meetings. However, where department requirements preclude a meeting at the time requested, the parties must, as soon as possible, agree upon a time that is reasonable given the circumstances.
				</item>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				An employee representative who is a member of the bargaining unit who must accompany an employee to a meeting with the University provided for in this Agreement is given leave without loss of pay or benefits for the duration of the meeting and for a reasonable amount of time beforehand in order to prepare for the meeting. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Where the leave credits provided for in 10.1 have been exhausted or where the Institute so specifies in its request, the Institute may give an employee leave without pay in order for the employee to participate in a union activity. Whenever possible, the Institute makes its request at least five (5) days prior to the date of the activity. If the five (5) day time frame cannot be respected, the Institute advises the University why it is unable to respect the time frame. The University must not unreasonably withhold approval of such a request. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				The University continues to pay the wages, benefits, applicable premiums and contributions to benefit plans for an employee granted leave without pay and invoices the Institute once (1) each quarter for these leaves without pay. The Institute reimburses the University within thirty (30) days of the date of this invoice.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The Group president, or the vice-president in the absence of the president, is authorized to request leave for union business under Article 10, with the exception of leaves provided under 10.6. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Upon written request at least five (5) days in advance from the president or the vice-president, the University grants leave, without loss of pay or benefits, to the Group member or members referred to in the request. If the five (5) day time frame cannot be respected, the Institute advises the University why it is unable to respect the time frame. The University must not unreasonably withhold approval of such a request.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Leave granted under 10.1, 10.4 and 10.6 is in blocks of one (1) full day or one half (1/2) day.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Office at the Institute
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			<list type="Alpha">
				
				<item langue="en">
					This Article applies to regular employees only.
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					An employee asked to work full time at the Institute makes a request for release time without pay for union business at least thirty (30) days in advance indicating the nature of the work to be performed and the anticipated duration of the absence. 
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					The University guarantees an employee's position for a maximum term of one (1) year in the case of a non-elected position. At the end of the one year term, the employee may extend the leave without pay for a maximum of two (2) additional years without pay and without a guarantee of the position held prior to taking the leave.
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					The University guarantees the employee's position for a maximum term of three (3) years in the case of an elected position. At the end of the three year term, the employee may extend the leave without pay without a guarantee of the position held prior to taking the leave for as long as the employee continues to hold an elected office.
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					An employee who wishes to return to the position held prior to taking the leave or to another position at the end of the leave without pay under the provisions of 10.8(c) and (d) gives such notice at least thirty (30) days in advance of the date of return. 
				</item>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The parties acknowledge that service requirements take precedence over and supersede any leave for union business. However, the University will attempt to accommodate requests for leave for union business whenever possible. In situations where there is a conflict with work schedules, the parties can try to find a solution, including changing the dates of the leave for union business.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Within thirty (30) days of the Agreement being ratified, the Institute provides HR Client Advisory Services, Labour Relations sector, with a written list of the name and duties of representatives likely to be granted leave and to act on the Institute's behalf, in accordance with the provisions herein. This list includes the names of the Group's executive committee members, the Institute's union stewards, the members of the bargaining unit, the Institute's employment relations officer assigned to the Group and the members who represent the Institute on the different joint committees referred to in the Agreement. The Human Resources Service, Labour Relations sector, receives notification of any changes to this list.
			</paragraph-numbered>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<article id="article-11">
		
		<title langue="en">
			WORKING HOURS
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Given the breakdown of working hours under 11.2 and calculated as an annual average, the length of the regular work week is thirty-five (35) hours, for a total of 1,820 hours a year. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				In order for employees to take advantage of reduced summer hours, the hours referred to in 11.1 are broken down throughout the year as follows: 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			<list type="Alpha">
				
				<item langue="en">
					From September 1 to May 31, inclusive, the regular work week is thirty-six and a quarter (36.25) hours, with the work day being seven and a quarter (7.25) hours. The regular daily schedule is 8:45 a.m. to 5 p.m;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					From June 1 to August 31, inclusive, the regular work week is thirty-one and a quarter (31.25) hours, with the work day being six and a quarter (6.25) hours. The regular daily schedule is 8:45 a.m. to 4 p.m;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					If operational requirements allow and with the approval of the dean of the Faculty or service director as the case may be, an employee may choose not to participate in the summer work schedule and instead work an annual average of thirty-five (35) hours per week. 
				</item>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The regular work week for the majority of employees consists of five (5) working days, from Monday to Friday. The University sets employee work schedules based on operational requirements and may include a regular work schedule involving weekends or evenings. Such a schedule is outlined in the job description. "Weekend" is defined as Saturday and Sunday.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				An employee whose regular work schedule involves weekends has one day off during the week and can, upon request, have at least one weekend off every three (3) weeks. In all cases, the employee's work week involves no more than five (5) days.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				For operational reasons and with the employee's consent, an employee's regular work schedule may be changed periodically to include hours outside the regular daily schedule. In such cases, hours worked before 7:30 a.m. are paid at a rate of one and one-half (1 1/2) times the hourly rate. This provision does not apply if a start time prior to 7:30 a.m. is a result of a work schedule set in accordance with 11.4.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				The University sets work schedules based on operational requirements. As a result, some schedules may differ from the one described in 11.2. Any such schedules are outlined in the job description for the position.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				If necessitated by operational requirements, the work schedule outlined in the job description may be modified upon agreement with the employee concerned and after the employee has been given at least thirty (30) days notice. If the changes required are necessary for teaching purposes, the schedule takes effect after (15) days. The agreement respects the total annual number of work hours laid out in 11.1. This agreement is signed by the employee, a representative of the Institute, the dean or service director, as the case may be, and a representative from Human Resources. The agreement is kept in the employee's file. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Modified schedules in effect at the time the collective agreement was signed remain in effect and are deemed to have been modified in accordance with the procedure outlined in this Article. Modified schedules are not considered permanent and can be terminated by the University if operational requirements change. An arrangement for a modified schedule must not be terminated without prior consultation with the employee and the Institute. Reasons for ending the arrangement are communicated during the consultation. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Subject to 11.3, the regular work day is an average of seven (7) hours in length. During each work day, employees are entitled to two (2) paid breaks of fifteen (15) minutes each, one in the morning and one in the afternoon, and a one (1) hour unpaid meal break, which generally begins between 11:00 a.m. and 1 p.m. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Employees whose work day is shorter than seven (7) hours in length are entitled to one (1) break of fifteen (15) minutes for every three (3) hours worked and one thirty (30) minute unpaid meal break for every five (5) hours worked.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Breaks are not designed to shorten the work day and, unless necessitated by specific needs of a service, cannot be taken at the beginning or end of the work day or in order to extend meal breaks.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				In all cases, break schedules are to be set or authorized by the employee's immediate supervisor.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				For the purposes of calculating the number of hours worked in a week, the work week begins at 12:01 a.m. on Sunday and ends at midnight on Saturday. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Flexible schedule
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Notwithstanding 11.1 and 11.2, employees can, upon agreement with the dean or service director (or their delegate), as the case may be, work flexible hours. A copy of the schedule is provided to the Institute.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				A flexible schedule must take into account operational requirements and the obligation to provide the best possible service to students and the University community. A request for a flexible schedule may not be refused without just cause. A flexible schedule must not result, in and of itself, in additional overtime hours or additional costs.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Flexible schedules must include a meal break of at least thirty (30) minutes and two (2) breaks of fifteen (15) minutes each. Flexible schedules cannot allow for the work day to begin before 7:30 a.m. or to end before 3:30 p.m., except during summer hours when the work day cannot end before 3:00 p.m.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Breaks are not designed to shorten the work day and, unless necessitated by specific needs of a service, they cannot be taken at the beginning or end of the work day or to extend meal breaks.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Such schedules can be for a limited time period and can be terminated if operational requirements change and result in a conflict with such a schedule or if the employee chooses to terminate it. If the University terminates a flexible schedule, it consults with the employee and gives advanced notice of the termination to the employee. Such consultation includes the reasons for changing or ending the arrangement.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Compressed schedule
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Notwithstanding 11.1 and 11.2, employees can spread their hours over a bi-weekly period, creating one (1) extra day off by working nine (9) days during a period of 10 (ten) days. Compressed schedules are subject to the same conditions as those for flexible schedules, outlined in 11.7. The extra day off is determined at the time the compressed schedule is agreed upon.
			</paragraph>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<article id="article-12">
		
		<title langue="en">
			OVERTIME
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The terms and conditions of this article apply to every employee covered by the bargaining unit.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Unless addressed in the employee's regular schedule pursuant to 11.4 or 11.5, any work done in addition to or outside of the normal work day or week is deemed to be overtime, and the employee is compensated in time or salary, or a combination thereof, according to his preference, at time and a half (150%) of his hourly rate.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Notwithstanding 12.2, employees on a flexible or compressed work schedule is paid the overtime rate when asked to work beyond the work day or week provided in the flexible or compressed work agreement. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Only overtime hours previously included in the schedule or authorized by the immediate supervisor are paid under the terms and conditions of 12.2.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Overtime work is optional unless major circumstances require it to avoid serious interference with the working of the University or its activities, cases such as: 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			<list type="Alpha">
				
				<item langue="en">
					To deal with an emergency;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					To ensure that continuous processes or seasonal operations are not interrupted if something unforeseen occurs; or
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					To carry out urgent repair work to the University facilities. 
				</item>
				
				<paragraph langue="en">
					An employee will not be required to work more than fourteen (14) consecutive hours.
				</paragraph>
				
				<paragraph langue="en">
					Overtime work is allocated in turns and equitably among the employees who regularly do the work for which the overtime is being requested.
				</paragraph>
				
				<paragraph langue="en">
					To the extent that an insufficient number of employees agree to work overtime, and major circumstances so require, employees with the least seniority among those who regularly do the work does the overtime. 
				</paragraph>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				When, during cyclical peak periods, special projects or under exceptional circumstances, there is a risk of substantial overtime hours, the concerned employees, the dean or the service director, as appropriate, may agree on what they feel is a reasonable recognition of hours worked in salary or compensatory time. Such agreement will be endorsed by the Institute and the Human Resources Service. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Compensation for overtime in compensatory leave is pursuant to an agreement between the employee and his immediate supervisor and is to be taken in half- or full-days. However, the supervisor must not deny the compensatory leave without just cause. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Weekend, evening and night premiums do not apply in the case of overtime. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				A maximum of fifty (50) hours of overtime, including the time-and-a-half calculation, can be banked during each calendar year to be taken as time off. The choice between overtime pay and banked time is at the employee's discretion. All overtime beyond these fifty (50) hours must be paid. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Subject to advance notice of one (1) month, the employee may draw a portion or all of the banked overtime. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			<list type="Alpha">
				
				<item langue="en">
					On December 31 of each year, overtime banked between January 1 and September 30 of the current year that has not been drawn is paid in cash. 
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					On April 30 of each year, overtime banked between October 1 and December 31 of the previous year that has not been drawn is paid in cash.
				</item>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Employees with banked overtime who are transferred to another faculty or service are paid in cash when they leave the faculty or service where the overtime was worked. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Meal allowance and time
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				An employee is entitled to a meal break of at least thirty (30) minutes after five (5) hours of consecutive overtime. An employee who is required to work beyond his regular scheduled workday is entitled to a meal allowance of nine dollars ($9) after working two (2) consecutive hours of overtime, and after each four (4) consecutive hours of overtime thereafter, except when meals are provided. When required to work overtime on a day that is not part of that employee's regular schedule, an employee receives the meal allowance after every four (4) hour overtime period. Allowances are paid from petty cash.
			</paragraph>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<article id="article-13">
		
		<title langue="en">
			AVAILABILITY AND CALL BACK TO WORK
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				When the University requires that employees be available for recall to work outside of normal hours, they must be reachable, available, able and ready for work at all times during the designated period. The required availability is allocated so as to alternate among the employees who normally do the work for which the availability is required to respond to emergency calls in their sector. The deans and directors determine the required amount of availability.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				When a single employee normally does the work for which the availability is required, the University ensures that the employee can get, at his request, respite periods of one (1) week out of two (2), including weekends, when he is not required to be available.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				An employee on call is available at all times to report to work in a timely manner during his availability period. An employee on annual leave or on sick leave for more than one week cannot be on the availability list for recalls or receive the indemnity.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				An employee who regularly neglects his responsibility by failing to respond to the calls made to him may have his name struck from the list of employees available for recall. The first time, the name is struck for three (3) months, and every subsequent time for one (1) year.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The University provides the employee on standby a communications device, and pays him half (1/2) hour wage for each four (4) hours of standby requested.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Employees recalled to work fifteen (15) minutes or more after finishing their normal workday and who must physically come to the workplace without being able to solve the problem from home receives a minimum of either four (4) hours of straight time or time-and-a-half (1.5) for the hours worked, whichever is highest. When an employee is paid under this article, any accumulation of on-call time ceases for the period in question. If, during the time that the employee is performing the task that initiated the recall, an additional task requiring a recall occurs, this new work is deemed to be part of the initial recall.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				An employee on standby who manages to resolve a problem from home is paid for a minimum of one hour at time and a half (1½). If during that period another problem arises, this work is deemed to be a single problem and addressed in continuity. If the situation requires a recall to work, the employee reports to work and is paid pursuant to 13.3. The recall time is calculated from the initial call.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Travel time for recalls is not compensated.
			</paragraph-numbered>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<article id="article-14">
		
		<title langue="en">
			GRIEVANCES
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Grievance
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				A grievance is defined as any dispute relating to the interpretation, application, administration or alleged violation of this Agreement. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				An individual grievance is presented by or in the name of an employee. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Where an employee presenting a grievance at the first level does not wish to be accompanied by an employees' representative, he makes this known by signing the form agreed upon by the parties and provided for this purpose. A copy of this form is sent immediately to the Institute.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				A group grievance covers an identical dispute and seeks the same redress for employees of the same faculty or department. Where the employees involved do not have the same supervisor, the grievance is presented immediately at the second level. The grievance is accompanied by a list of the employees who are a party to the grievance and their signatures authorizing the presentation of the group grievance on their behalf. In this case, one of the employees in the group is designated by the Institute to accompany the Institute during discussions at the various levels of this procedure.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				A policy grievance is one which is presented by the Institute or by the University and raises a question concerning the general application or interpretation of the Agreement. In this case, the grievance is presented immediately at the second level, which is to say to the HR Client Advisory Services, Labour Relations sector, or to the Institute.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				No employee or Institute representative belonging to the bargaining unit will suffer reprisals for presenting a grievance.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				The parties acknowledge that grievances are to be resolved promptly and undertake to act diligently to do so.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				The Institute has carriage of all grievances at Level Two (2) of the grievance procedure and thereafter. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Dispute resolution
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			<list type="Alpha">
				
				<item langue="en">
					Informal discussion:
				</item>
				
				<paragraph langue="en">
					Before initiating a grievance, an employee, alone or accompanied by a representative from the Institute, may attempt to resolve any dispute during an informal encounter with his immediate superior. From the perspective of prompt dispute resolution, the parties acknowledge that, although not mandatory, informal discussions between employees and their supervisors may often prove useful.
				</paragraph>
				
				<item langue="en">
					First level
				</item>
				<list type="Roman">
					
					<item langue="en">
						Should the parties fail to reach an understanding at the informal discussion stage or if no informal discussion takes place, the employee, or the Institute through its representative, may present a grievance in writing to the University's authorized representative, i.e., the dean of the faculty or the director of the department involved, and send a copy to the HR Client Advisory Services, Labour Relations sector.
					</item>
					
					<item langue="en">
						The grievance briefly sets out the dispute and the redress demanded and is presented no later than whichever date occurs last: the fifteenth (15th) working day following the incident giving rise to the grievance or the fifteenth (15th) working day after the employee first learned of the events giving rise to the grievance.
					</item>
					
					<item langue="en">
						Recourse to the informal discussion provided for in 14.2 a) stops the clock on the aforementioned fifteen (15) working days time limit; the countdown begins again only after a written decision is issued by the immediate supervisor following this informal discussion, or no later than five (5) days after this discussion.
					</item>
					
					<item langue="en">
						Within ten (10) working days following the presentation of the grievance, the University's representative, alone or accompanied by a representative from HR Client Advisory Services, Labour Relations sector, meets with the employee and his representative if so desired, and try to resolve the grievance. 
					</item>
					
					<item langue="en">
						The University's authorized representative issues a written decision that is to be sent to the other party and his representative within fifteen (15) working days of receiving the grievance.
					</item>
				</list>
				
				<item langue="en">
					Second level:
				</item>
				<list type="Roman">
					
					<item langue="en">
						Should the parties fail to resolve the grievance at the first level, the employee's representative may submit the grievance to the Assistant Director, Labour Relations, HR Client Advisory Services within the fifteen (15) working days following the reply by the University's authorized representative, or in the absence of such reply, following the expiration of the time limit for replying.
					</item>
					
					<item langue="en">
						The Assistant Director, Labour Relations, HR Client Advisory Services or his authorized representative meets with the employee's representative in the company of the employee at the second level within ten (10) working days of receiving the second-level grievance and attempts to resolve the grievance. The Assistant Director, Labour Relations, HR Client Advisory Services, or his authorized representative issues a written decision that is to be sent to the Institute with a copy to the employee within fifteen (15) working days of the meeting provided for in the preceding paragraph.
					</item>
				</list>
				
				<item langue="en">
					Referral to arbitration: Should the parties fail to resolve the grievance at the second level, the Institute informs the Labour Relations sector in writing of its intent to refer the grievance to arbitration within sixty (60) days of the reply from the Assistant Director, Labour Relations, HR Client Advisory Services, or in the absence of a reply, on expiration of the time limit for responding. Where the grievance has been presented by the University, its authorized representative has the same time limit for informing the Institute of its intent to refer the grievance to arbitration.
				</item>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Abridged Procedure
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Any grievance challenging a layoff, dismissal or suspension without pay is presented directly at the second level provided in 14.2 within thirty (30) days of the action being challenged.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Extension of Time Limits
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			<list type="Alpha">
				
				<item langue="en">
					The time limits and levels provided in this article are mandatory unless mutually extended or substituted in writing by the University and the Institute, or unless it is expressly agreed to proceed directly to a specific level.
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					Where the grievance is presented by the University, the same time limits provided in Article 14 for the Institute and the employees applies to the University, and the time limits available to the University also applies to the Institute. If at any time the University's representatives fail to respect the time limits stipulated in this Agreement, the Institute and the person who presented the grievance may proceed to the next level or refer it to arbitration if need be.
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					Should the employee or the Institute or the University fail to respect the time limits incumbent upon them as set out in this Agreement, or should a reply not be received within the stipulated time limits, the grievance is deemed abandoned. In the event of disagreement as to whether the Article 14 time limits were respected, an arbitrator appointed in accordance with Article 15 is charged with settling this new dispute in consideration of the circumstances surrounding the presumed failure to respect these time limits.
				</item>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Notwithstanding the aforementioned procedure, the parties may meet with each other at any time in the aim of finding a satisfactory solution to the grievance.
			</paragraph-numbered>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<article id="article-15">
		
		<title langue="en">
			ARBITRATION
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Sole arbitrator
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Unless otherwise indicated by either party within thirty (30) days of the notice of intent served by the Institute in accordance with 14.2 d), the grievance is heard by a sole arbitrator.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Within fifteen (15) days following the time limit of thirty (30) days provided in the preceding clause, the parties appoint an arbitrator. Should the parties be unable to agree on an arbitrator within the aforementioned time limits, either or both of the parties apply to the Ontario Minister of Labour to have one appointed pursuant to section 48(4) of the Labour Relations Act, 1995, specifying that the arbitrator so appointed be able to hear the grievance in the language chosen by the employee involved or, in the case of a policy grievance, by the instigator of the grievance, whether the Institute or the University. The request to the Minister also specifies the names of the arbitrators on whom the parties were unable to agree.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Arbitration board
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				The party who serves notice of not wishing to be heard by a sole arbitrator identifies at the same time the name of the person who will represent him at the arbitration board. The other party then have thirty (30) days from the notice it receives to identify its representative before the board and to inform the opposing party of this. The parties' appointed representatives have fifteen (15) days to choose a Chair, failing which an application identical to the application referred to in 15.1 is sent by one or both parties to the Minister of Labour.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Powers and duties of the arbitrator and the board
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				The sole arbitrator or the arbitration board, as the case may be, is duty-bound and has the power to render decisions on all aspects of the dispute being grieved, including on the question of whether arbitration is appropriate, and has all the powers of an arbitrator or an arbitration board under the Ontario Labour Relations Act as periodically amended.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Subject to the provisions of the Ontario Labour Relations Act, the jurisdiction of the arbitrator and the board is limited to the application and interpretation of the wording of the Collective Agreement, and excludes adding, deleting, making compensation for or amending it.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Disciplinary powers
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				In arbitration matters concerning disciplinary action, the arbitrator or the board may, as the case may be, uphold, change or rescind the penalty and, where applicable, order payment of the wages the employee would have earned were it not for the penalty.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Burden of proof
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				In the arbitration of disciplinary matters, the burden of proof lies with the University.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Arbitration time limits, expenses and fees
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Insofar as possible, the arbitrator or the board, as the case may be, holds the first investigative session within thirty (30) days of the appointment of the sole arbitrator or the board chair and issues a reasoned written decision within the same time limit after the hearing's conclusion. This decision is enforceable and binding upon the parties.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				The arbitrator's or the board chair's expenses and fees are paid equally by the parties. Where applicable, each party bears the expenses and fees of its respective representative at the board hearing.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Wages of witnesses and representatives
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Employees required to testify at a grievance arbitration hearing are released from work without loss of wages for the time required to deliver their testimony. The employee concerned by a grievance is released without loss of wages to attend the grievance arbitration hearing. Where a group grievance is involved, only one employee concerned and designated by the Institute is released from work without loss of wages for the duration of the arbitration hearing. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Mediation
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				At any time during the grievance procedure provided under Article 14, or at any time in the aforementioned arbitration procedure, the parties may agree in writing to attempt to resolve the grievance by resorting to mediation. In this case, they agree on the choice of mediator and on the time limits they both will have in order to try to resolve their dispute.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				The time limits set out in articles 14 and 15 are suspended effective the date on which the parties agree in writing to resort to mediation. Upon written notice from either party that the mediation process has been terminated, the clock starts again from the point at which the time limits in articles 14 and 15 were suspended.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				The mediator's expenses and fees are paid equally by the parties.
			</paragraph>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<article id="article-16">
		
		<title langue="en">
			DISCIPLINARY MEASURES
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				A disciplinary letter, suspension or dismissal is a disciplinary measure. The University must not impose any disciplinary measures without sufficient just cause.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				In the application of a disciplinary measure, if the alleged acts or behaviours are serious enough, the University may disregard progressive discipline and the misconduct may be subject to serious disciplinary measures, including dismissal, upon the first alleged act.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				When discipline involving a disciplinary letter, suspension or dismissal is to be applied, the dean of the faculty or the service director consults the Human Resources Service. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Disciplinary meeting 
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				For any meeting of a disciplinary nature or that could result in a disciplinary measure, the employee, unless he expressly waives this option in writing, is accompanied by an Institute representative of his choice and available for this meeting.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				If the University wishes to impose a disciplinary measure, it calls the employee to a meeting through a written notice at least one (1) working day in advance. The written notice informs the employee of the day, time and location of the meeting and of his right to be accompanied by a representative of the Institute. A certified copy of the written notice is sent to the Institute. In the event that the employee is not available, the meeting is postponed by up to one (1) working day.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				When the University suspends or dismisses an employee, it notifies him in writing. This notice includes the reasons for the sanction, the duration of the suspension, if applicable, and the effective date of the suspension or dismissal.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				If the employee files a grievance against or requests an arbitration of the suspension or dismissal, the University may not use any other reasons for the suspension or dismissal than those included in the notice in the previous paragraph.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The University deletes any disciplinary measure from the employee's personnel file and destroys any document or statement related to the disciplinary measure two (2) years after the sanction is imposed unless a subsequent disciplinary infraction of the same nature was added to the personnel file. The University informs the employee in writing once the documents and statements have been removed from his file and destroyed. The removal and destruction of the documents and statements is postponed to the date set for the removal and destruction of the documents and statements related to the latter sanction for a similar offence. The unit where the employee was working when the disciplinary measure was imposed is notified by the Human Resources Service that it is required to destroy any such documents related to the concerned employee that might be contained in the administrative files held in the unit.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				A copy of the notice is sent to the employee, and a copy of the confirmation of the removal of the documents and statements is sent to the Human Resources Service.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Any disciplinary measures that have been decided in the employee's favour are removed from the employee's file immediately.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The University may suspend an employee with full salary and all benefits during an administrative investigation. It is understood that such suspension does not constitute discipline and cannot be the subject of a grievance. If no disciplinary measure results from this investigation, the University immediately removes from the personnel file and the administrative files held in the units, and destroys, any documents related to this suspension with pay and to the investigation. If a disciplinary measure results from this investigation, the above-mentioned documents are removed from the above-mentioned files and destroyed in accordance with the instructions under 16.7.
			</paragraph-numbered>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<article id="article-17">
		
		<title langue="en">
			SENIORITY
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				For the purpose of this Agreement, seniority is defined as follows:
			</paragraph-numbered>
			<list type="Alpha">
				
				<item langue="en">
					Seniority is a function of a date. The seniority of an employee in a position that is covered by the bargaining unit at the time the first collective agreement is ratified corresponds to his last date of continuous service at the University.
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					The seniority of an employee hired after the ratification of the first collective agreement or who joins the bargaining unit after that ratification corresponds to his first day on the job in a function covered by the bargaining unit.
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					The seniority of a regular employee is recognized and may be exercised after his probation period has been completed. It is retroactive to the date identified under 17.1 a) or b), as the case may be.
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					The seniority of a term employee is recognized and may be exercised after he joins the bargaining unit. It is retroactive to the date identified under 17.1 a) or b), as the case may be.
				</item>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The date of seniority may be amended if the employee is absent and the Agreement provides that he does not accumulate any seniority during this absence.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				The seniority of employees at the signing of the Agreement is indicated in Appendix A to this document.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Once a year, on September 30, the seniority list (Appendix A) is updated and posted by the University on the Human Resources Service website. A copy of the updated list is sent to the group president.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Employees have thirty (30) days after the list was posted to request a review of the seniority date indicated and to file a grievance if they are not satisfied with the review or the denial of such of a review. The list is in order of seniority, and includes the employee names and their respective seniority dates.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Employees retain and accumulate seniority in the following cases:
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			<list type="Alpha">
				
				<item langue="en">
					a layoff period when the employee is placed on the call back list;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					an absence due to disability not exceeding 24 months;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					an authorized absence in the case of leave authorized under 10.08 up to a maximum of two (2) years in the case of a non-elective function, and up to a maximum of three (3) years in the case of an elective function;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					an accident or occupational disease of less than twenty-four (24) months;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					an appointment of an employee who is not covered by the Agreement pursuant to 25.1 a) and b); or
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					non-paid leave of less than thirty (30) days authorized by the University under 30.12.
				</item>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Employees retain seniority but do not accumulate seniority in the following cases:
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			<list type="Alpha">
				
				<item langue="en">
					non-paid leave of more than thirty (30) days authorized by the University under 30.12;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					an absence due to long-term disability lasting more than 119 days that has been accepted by the insurer and for which the employee receives benefits.
				</item>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Employees lose their seniority in the following cases
				</strong>
				:
			</paragraph-numbered>
			<list type="Alpha">
				
				<item langue="en">
					resignation or voluntarily leaving their position;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					retirement;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					termination, unless rescinded by the grievance and arbitration procedure;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					layoff, where the right of recall has been exhausted;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					refusal of a term assignment or a reasonable offer of employment pursuant to Article 19, when a position has been eliminated;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					severance payment is being received pursuant to 19.11 or 19.12; 
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					assignment for more than twelve (12) months to a job that is not covered under this Agreement pursuant to 25.1 b); or
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					absence for long-term disability that extends beyond twenty-four (24) months.
				</item>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				When more than one employee has the same seniority, the University holds a lottery in the presence of the employees concerned to determine their order of seniority, whenever necessary.
			</paragraph-numbered>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<article id="article-18">
		
		<title langue="en">
			JOB POSTINGS AND APPOINTMENTS
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The University posts online for a period of ten (10) days all vacant or newly created regular positions to be filled.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Postings are first to be made available exclusively to employees of the bargaining unit. If, at the end of the posting period and after the selection process has been completed a suitable candidate was not chosen, the University can accept applications from persons outside the bargaining unit.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Postings are in both official language and contain:
			</paragraph-numbered>
			<list type="Dash">
				
				<item langue="en">
					the position title;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					a summary job description;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					a detailed job description in one or both official languages;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					the essential qualifications;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					the faculty or service and department;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					the work location, for information purposes;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					the standard number of hours in the work week and, if applicable, any irregular hours;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					the job classification and salary range;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					the posting number;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					the immediate supervisor's title; and
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					the start and end dates for the posting.
				</item>
				
				<paragraph langue="en">
					The University also indicates on the posting whether it is proceeding with a concurrent pre-qualification competition for identical positions that may be created or become vacant in the near future.
				</paragraph>
				
				<paragraph langue="en">
					The Institute is advised of the posting and receives a copy of it1. 
				</paragraph>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Employees applying for a position submit their application electronically to the University by the deadline indicated on the posting. The University sends an acknowledgement to the email address from which the application was received.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Employees who have not completed their probationary period may not apply for other positions.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				When positions that have been posted are being filled, primary consideration is given to the competence of the employees. In all cases, the employee must meet the requirements of the position. These requirements must be established based on the duties of the position being filled. The University evaluates candidates through an interview or an interview together with selection test(s). During the interview, candidates are evaluated using a scoring grid, with a total of one hundred (100) points. Candidates with a score of seventy-five percent (75%) or more are retained, and the employee with the most seniority is offered the position.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				The following factors are taken into consideration for each candidate for a given position: skills and ability required to function effectively in the position, credentials and aptitude. These criteria are considered and applied equally and fairly.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				After being authorized to do so by the successful candidate, the Human Resources Service is responsible for checking references before recommending the candidate for the position. The University also checks the candidate's performance appraisals from the last three (3) years and reviews any non-authorized absences over the past three (3) years.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Following the appointment of the selected employee, and within thirty (30) days if possible, the University determines the date when the selected employee will occupy the position. The employee is paid according to the rate of his new position from the first (1st) day of work in the position. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Every month, the University posts all appointments made under this Article on the Human Resources Service website. An employee who applied for a posting and wishes to file a grievance related to a competition must do so within the time frame laid out in Article 14, Grievances. The grievance is presented directly at the second level and, if the grievance goes to arbitration, the burden of proof lies with the University.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				An employee appointed to a position receives the following salary terms and conditions:
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				<strong>
					Promotion: 
				</strong>
				A permanent appointment of an employee from one regular position to another regular position with a higher salary grade. The employee receives a 5% salary increase for every salary grade over the salary grade of his position. An employee's pay must not be less than the minimum and must not exceed the maximum of the salary grade for the new position.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				<strong>
					Transfer: 
				</strong>
				The appointment of an employee from one regular position to another regular position at the same salary grade. There is no salary adjustment.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				<strong>
					Demotion: 
				</strong>
				The appointment of an employee from one regular position to another regular position at a lower salary grade. The employee's salary is reduced by 5% for every salary grade below the salary grade of his current position. An employee's salary must not be less than the minimum and must not exceed the maximum of the salary grade for the new position. 
			</paragraph>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<article id="article-19">
		
		<title langue="en">
			ELIMINATION OF A REGULAR POSITION AND LAYOFF
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The following provisions on staffing priority terms and conditions apply strictly to incumbents of regular positions.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				When the University is required to eliminate a position, it first informs the Institute at least thirty (30) days prior to eliminating it. During this period, the Advisory Committee on Labour Relations meets to discuss alternatives.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				If no alternative is possible or is no longer available, the regular employee with the least seniority in the service or faculty who has the same position title and level as the one being eliminated is laid off and notified thereof.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The employee is placed on a staffing priority list at the University for a period of nine (9) months after the notice under 19.3. During this period, the employee has the first right to any reasonable job offer. The competency of the employee for the position may be assessed by the dean or the service director, as appropriate, or their delegate, through an interview and/or selection tests.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				During the staffing priority period, the employee is assigned to a temporary function at his regular salary, either in the faculty or service or elsewhere in the University, unless he is assigned to functions at a higher level, in which case his salary is adjusted upwards by 5% for each pay grade higher than that for the position he holds. An employee's pay is not to be less than the minimum and not exceed the maximum of the pay grade for the new position. The University determines the temporary assignment according to the needs of the service, the faculty or the University.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				A temporary assignment respects the employee's qualifications and expertise and, unless the employee agrees, only includes functions covered by the bargaining unit.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				A "reasonable job offer" is a regular position that is part of the bargaining unit, normally at an equivalent level, although lower-level job offers are not excluded. The employee must be trainable and flexible. The employee must be able to perform the essential duties of the position, as long as he qualifies. A training period may be determined by the parties, without loss of salary and at the University's expense. If the appointment results in a demotion, the employee's salary is not reduced, but his wage progression is that of the new grade. If the employee's salary is higher than the maximum of the new pay grade, his salary is frozen (red circled) until the grade rises and can be integrated.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				A job offer is deemed reasonable providing that the appointment is at a rate of pay and an attainable salary maximum not less than the employee's salary at the date of the offer.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Positions offered under staffing priority are exclusively positions covered by the bargaining unit.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				An employee who is offered a reasonable position has five (5) days from the date of the offer to accept or refuse it.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				When an employee has not been able to find a new position during his nine (9) month staffing priority period and has not refused a reasonable job offer as defined in 19.6, the bumping procedure is used as a last resort. In this case, the parties prepare a list of regular employees with less seniority than the employee who was laid off and who have an equivalent position for which he has the required competencies. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				The employee who was laid off takes the place of the employee with the least seniority on the above list whose position level is the closest to that of the position that was eliminated.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				The employee who is hereby replaced then becomes eligible for the process pursuant to 19.1 and the following articles.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				An employee who refuses a reasonable job offer, a temporary assignment or his bumping right is deemed to have voluntarily abandoned his employment at the University and receives:
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<list type="Bullet">
				
				<item langue="en">
					one week of salary for every year of full-time continuous service at the University, excluding leaves without pay for more than one month, up to a maximum of twenty-six (26) weeks;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					one-twelfth (1/12) of one week of severance for each month of continuous full-time service in excess of full years at the University; and
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					The University continues to provide the employee's insured benefits for a maximum period of two (2) months in the same proportion as usual.
				</item>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				An employee who has not found a new position during his nine (9) month staffing priority period and who has not refused a reasonable job offer receives a severance payment. The employee has the choice to either accept the severance payment or be placed on the call-back list under article 20 for a period not to exceed twelve (12) months with laid-off status. An employee receives a severance payment in the following amounts:
			</paragraph-numbered>
			<list type="Bullet">
				
				<item langue="en">
					a lump sum equivalent to six (6) months of regular base salary;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					one week of salary for every year of full-time continuous service at the University, excluding leaves without pay for more than one month, up to a maximum of twenty-six (26) weeks;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					one-twelfth (1/12) of one week of severance for each month of continuous full-time service in excess of full years at the University. 
				</item>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				The University continues to provide the employee's insured benefits for a maximum period of two (2) months in the same proportion as usual.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				If at the end of this period on the recall list, the employee who has not secured a regular position or has removed his name from the recall list, he receives the severance payment pursuant to 19.11.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Should the employee who has been laid off be re-hired by the University within six (6) months of the date of termination of employment, the balance of the lump sum is returned to the University as a condition of obtaining employment. Repayment terms and conditions are established between the employee and the University.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Should an employee be affected one or more times by the elimination of positions later during his period of employment at the University, the employee receives a severance payment for these eliminations only for the years or the partial years that were not covered in the past in addition to a lump sum equivalent to six(6) months of regular base salary.
			</paragraph-numbered>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<article id="article-20">
		
		<title langue="en">
			RECALL LISTS
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Recall lists of regular employees laid off
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			<list type="Alpha">
				
				<item langue="en">
					A regular employee who has been laid off and has not been able to displace or be placed during the staffing priority period is added to a recall list for up to twelve (12) continuous months.
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					A regular employee on the recall list maintains his skills profile with the Human Resources Service, identifying his training and qualifications, up to date.
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					Notwithstanding Article 18, "Job Postings and Appointments," a regular employee on the recall list has priority for any regular vacant position offered for which he meets the essential requirements. The rules under 18.4 apply. The regular vacant position must meet the definition of reasonable job offer under 19.6 and 19.7.
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					A regular employee who refuses such a position offered to him under the previous article is deemed to have resigned and receives the allowance under 19.10.
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					A regular employee on the recall list may resign at any time during the maximum twelve (12) month period and receive the severance payment under 19.11. 
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					While the regular employee is on the call-back list, only articles 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 10, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 22, 25, 28, 34 of the Agreement apply to him for the period under 20.1 a).
				</item>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Recall lists for term employees 
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			<list type="Alpha">
				
				<item langue="en">
					A term employee with three (3) or more years of continuous service whose contract has terminated may ask to be added to the recall list of term employees for up to twelve (12) continuous months. This employee must sign up with the Human Resources Service.
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					Only articles 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 10, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 22, 25, 28, 34 of the Agreement apply to a term employee on the term employee call-back list for the period under the previous article and, in addition to applying for any regular advertised position, may be given priority for any new term employment for which he meets the essential requirements. The rules under 18.4 apply.
				</item>
			</list>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<article id="article-21">
		
		<title langue="en">
			REGULARIZATION OF NEW DUTIES
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Where new duties are added in a faculty or department and are performed by term employees, the faculty or department decides, prior to the expiry of a period of three (3) consecutive years from the addition of these new duties, whether they are permanent and must be regularized by the creation of a new regular position, or whether they are to be terminated. Term employees performing these duties are notified at the launching of the regularization process.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Where a regular position is created on completion of the regularization process, the position is posted and staffed in accordance with Article 18, Job Postings and Appointments. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				A term employee who has three (3) years or more of continuous service performing duties regularized under this article and does not obtain the regularized position is entered, upon his request, on the call back list referred to in 20.2. Otherwise, he receives an advance notice of termination and severance pay, where applicable, in accordance with the Ontario Employment Standards Act.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				After an agreement has been reached with the Institute and for the term specified in that agreement, duties not converted to regular positions by the end of the aforementioned regularization process may be extended. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Barring an extension agreement with the Institute, a term position created as part of a special project ends no later than three (3) years after its creation.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The parties may at any time and by mutual consent remove duties referred to in 21.1 from the aforementioned regularization process. The parties may also agree to postpone to a later date the implementation of the regularization process for those same duties. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The provisions of this article do not apply to duties performed for more than three (3) years by the same term employee hired prior to January 25, 2007.
			</paragraph-numbered>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<article id="article-22">
		
		<title langue="en">
			TEMPORARY ASSIGNMENTS
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Temporary assignments offer regular employees training and development opportunities in new functions covered by the bargaining unit without losing their regular position and the benefits related to their status of regular employee.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				All temporary assignments longer than six (6) months in duration are posted and staffed in accordance with 18.1. If a temporary assignment of six (6) months or less is extended, the assignment is then posted for the time left, in accordance with the provisions of this article.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				A regular position left temporarily vacant as a result of a temporary assignment is posted and staffed in accordance with the provisions of this article. However, the University is not required to follow this procedure to staff any vacancy subsequent to this posting. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Regular employees who accept a temporary assignment return to their original position at the end of the assignment. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				In all cases, employees must receive their supervisor's approval to be considered eligible for a temporary assignment. Employees cannot be refused without a valid reason. If this reason might come up again with respect to the possibility of a subsequent assignment, the immediate supervisor takes the necessary steps to deal with the issue to allow for a subsequent assignment.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Two (2) weeks of notice is given in the following situations:
			</paragraph-numbered>
			<list type="Bullet">
				
				<item langue="en">
					the employee wishes to return to his substantive position; 
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					the University terminates the temporary assignment before the anticipated end date.
				</item>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				As soon as a temporary assignment starts, the employee selected for the assignment receives a salary pursuant to 18.7. The difference in salary received for a temporary assignment is not pensionable and does not confer entitlement to other employee benefits.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The University staffs term positions with employees on the callback list. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				If no employee on the callback list has the skills and knowledge necessary for the position, the University posts the position as though it were a temporary assignment. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				If the University is unable to fill a position in accordance with the above procedure, it proceeds with hiring a new term employee.
			</paragraph>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<article id="article-23">
		
		<title langue="en">
			PROBATIONARY PERIOD
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				All new regular employees are subject to a six (6) month probation period beginning when they become a member of the bargaining unit. The period excludes any layoff period or other absence of more than ten (10) consecutive days. Annual leave and time taken off in lieu of time worked are not considered absences for the purposes of this Article.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				In order to allow an employee to overcome obstacles to successfully completing the probation period, the University conduct a performance appraisal three (3) months after the beginning of the probation period. The University uses this opportunity to convey areas for improvement to the employ and create a plan for the employee to improve in these areas.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				This probation period can be extended by three (3) months upon written notice given no later than ten (10) working days before the end of the probation period.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				This extension notice is forwarded to the Institute and includes the reasons for the extension. If the probationary period is extended, the immediate supervisor develops a remedial training plan for the employee.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				If an employee stops working for the University, loses his seniority pursuant to the provisions of Article 17 and is then rehired in a position covered by the bargaining unit, the employee is subject to the probation period set out in 23.1.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				An employee who has not completed the probation period is eligible for benefits provided for in the collective agreement. During this period, the employee can be dismissed at any time. The employee and the union cannot grieve the dismissal. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				An employee who has been dismissed during the probation period receives a termination notice as required under the Ontario Employment Standards Act or the equivalent in severance pay.
			</paragraph-numbered>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<article id="article-24">
		
		<title langue="en">
			PERFORMANCE APPRAISALS
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				A formal performance appraisal refers to any written evaluation by an immediate superior of how well the employee has performed the assigned tasks and met objectives set for the period being evaluated. The appraisal provides an opportunity for setting objectives for the next evaluation period. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				All employee performance appraisals are in writing and signed by the evaluator, with a copy provided to the employee. The written performance appraisal made available to the employee at the earliest possible opportunity after being signed by all designates.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				A formal employee performance appraisal is conducted once per year for employees who have completed their probationary period, according to the procedures established by the Institute and the University. The employee performance appraisal is in the employee's preferred language of correspondence.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The base year for annual performance appraisals is January to December. The University conducts performance appraisals within sixty (60) days of the end of the base year.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				An employee on a leave of absence for more than six (6) months during the base year is not evaluated for that year.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Appraisals for employees promoted or transferred to a new position less than three (3) months prior to the month of December is based on their previous position and is completed by their previous immediate supervisor at the time they leave the previous position.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Unless otherwise mutually agreed, supervisors provide at least five (5) working days notice to employees prior to any formal meeting for the annual employee performance appraisal and encourage employees to provide a written summary of their work performance over the preceding period that includes, but is not limited to, achievements, areas for improvement, areas for job-related development activities and proposed performance goals for the next period. The latter is for purposes of discussion prior to the goals being established for the next year.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The performance appraisal process includes a meeting between the employee and the immediate supervisor. The purpose of this meeting is to discuss the performance appraisal. The meeting is held before the final appraisal is written.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				An employee performance appraisal that alleges an employee's performance is unsatisfactory outlines: 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			<list type="Alpha">
				
				<item langue="en">
					the reason(s) the employee's performance appraisal is unsatisfactory; and
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					specific recommendations for improvements necessary to achieve satisfactory performance in the area(s) the supervisor has alleged are unsatisfactory. 
				</item>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Once the supervisor has completed the written performance appraisal, the employee is given an opportunity to sign the performance appraisal and attach written comments, if so desired, prior to the appraisal being forwarded to the dean or director of the appropriate faculty or service. If employees dispute the accuracy or completeness of a performance appraisal, they can request a meeting with the dean or director of the appropriate faculty or service to discuss their performance appraisal prior to the dean or the director of the appropriate faculty or service confirming the appraisal and it being placed in their personnel file. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The employee has the right to attach a response or written comments to the performance appraisal. Any such response or written comment is attached to the employee performance appraisal in the employee's personnel file after the dean or director of the appropriate faculty or service has had the opportunity to read it.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				By signing a performance appraisal, the employee simply acknowledges being aware of the appraisal and the information contained in it. The employee's signature cannot be interpreted as agreement or disagreement with the contents of the appraisal.
			</paragraph-numbered>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<article id="article-25">
		
		<title langue="en">
			WORKING OUTSIDE THE BARGAINING UNIT
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
			</paragraph-numbered>
			<list type="Alpha">
				
				<item langue="en">
					Employees who accept a temporary assignment and are replacing a person on maternity leave, sick leave or leave pursuant to an employment contract in a position not covered by the collective agreement returns to their original position at the end of the assignment with all the rights and benefits they would have had if they had not taken a temporary assignment in a position outside the bargaining unit.
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					In the case of a temporary assignment for reasons other than those listed in 25.01(a), the employee must return to a position covered by the bargaining unit no later than twelve (12) months from the date the temporary assignment commenced. Any temporary assignment similar to the first temporary assignment that is accepted within twelve (12) months of the termination date of the first assignment is considered a continuation of the first assignment.
				</item>
			</list>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<article id="article-26">
		
		<title langue="en">
			PARENTAL AND MATERNITY LEAVE
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Maternity leave
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				All female employees who have thirteen (13) weeks of continuous service are entitled to maternity leave. During such leave, the employee retains the right to her position or to an equivalent position. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Maternity leave usually lasts seventeen (17) consecutive weeks and can be taken during the period from the seventeenth (17th) week preceding the expected date of delivery until at least the sixth (6th) week following the birth or stillbirth. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				An employee who miscarries more than seventeen (17) weeks before the expected delivery date is not entitled to maternity leave. If the miscarriage occurs in the seventeen (17) weeks preceding the expected delivery date, the leave ends no later than seventeen (17) weeks after the beginning of the leave or six (6) weeks after the miscarriage. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				A pregnant employee must present a medical certificate attesting to her pregnancy and submit a written notice at least two (2) weeks before the leave, except when the doctor states that this deadline cannot be observed. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				When an employee gives birth later than expected, postnatal leave lasts at least six (6) weeks. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				An employee may shorten her maternity leave by advising the University at least four (4) weeks ahead of the proposed end date, but in this case postnatal leave last at least six (6) weeks.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Remuneration during maternity leave
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				A female employee who holds a regular position at the University, has completed a minimum of twelve (12) months of continuous service and is entitled to maternity leave receives benefits as follows:
			</paragraph>
			<list type="Alpha">
				
				<item langue="en">
					the University continues to pay her ninety-five percent (95%) of her regular basic salary for an initial period of fourteen (14) calendar days; 
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					for the following fifteen (15) weeks of leave, the employee receives Employment Insurance benefits or benefits from the Québec Parental Insurance Plan (QPIP) and the University makes up the difference up to a maximum of ninety-five percent (95%) of her regular salary.
				</item>
				
				<paragraph langue="en">
					Notwithstanding the preceding, for a seasonal employee, the University does not pay the additional amounts during the usual period of seasonal absence.
				</paragraph>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Parental leave 
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				All employees who have completed thirteen (13) weeks of continuous service are entitled to adoption or childcare leave. During this leave, the employee retains the right to his position or to an equivalent position. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				A regular employee on parental leave whose position is abolished or who is bumped is, upon his return, is entitled to the provisions under Article 19, Elimination of a Regular Position and Layoff, in which case the timelines provided start on the date the employee returns to work. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				A term (temporary) employee on parental leave returns to the position he had at the time of taking leave, for the remainder of his contract. If this contract is not renewed, the term employee is entitled to the provisions under 20.2 a) and 20.2 if he meets the criteria stated therein in terms of continuous service.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				This leave is normally for a period of thirty-five (35) weeks for employees who have just taken the maternity leave referred to in 26.1, and for a period of thirty-seven (37) weeks for all other employees. It must begin no later than fifty-two (52) weeks following the adoption of the child or after the employee first obtains care of the child. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Parental leave for women who are also on maternity leave begins, at the latest, during the eighteenth (18th) week after the child's birth, unless the child is not yet under the employee's care. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Employees planning to use parental leave must submit written notice at least two (2) weeks before the proposed leave. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				An employee may shorten his parental leave by advising the University at least four (4) weeks in advance. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Remuneration during parental leave
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Employees who hold a regular position at the University, have completed a minimum of twelve (12) months of service and are entitled to the above parental leave receive the following benefits for the first six (6) weeks of leave following the adoption of a child or after the employee first obtains care of a child. 
			</paragraph>
			<list type="Alpha">
				
				<item langue="en">
					For employees who did not take maternity leave immediately before the parental leave: 
				</item>
				<list type="Roman">
					
					<item langue="en">
						the University continues to pay ninety-five percent (95%) of the regular basic salary for an initial period of fourteen (14) calendar days; 
					</item>
					
					<item langue="en">
						for the next four (4) weeks, the employee receives Employment Insurance benefits or benefits from the QPIP, and the University makes up the difference up to a maximum of ninety-five percent (95%) of the regular salary.
					</item>
				</list>
				
				<item langue="en">
					For employees who took maternity leave immediately prior to the parental leave, they receive, for the six (6) weeks, the difference between the amounts paid by Employment Insurance and ninety-five percent (95%) of the salary, since the two-week waiting period will have been completed at the beginning of the maternity leave.
				</item>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Notwithstanding the preceding, in the case of a seasonal employee, the University does not pay the additional amounts during the usual period of seasonal absence.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
			</paragraph-numbered>
			<list type="Alpha">
				
				<item langue="en">
					Additional benefits paid under 26.2 and 26.4 are not considered income for the purposes of calculating Employment Insurance premiums, but they are subject to the other deductions imposed by the Employment Insurance Act. 
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					The employee and the University continue paying their full contributions to the employee benefits program, even though the employee is collecting only ninety-five percent (95%) of his regular salary. 
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					If there is a salary increase during the employee's maternity leave, the ninety-five percent (95%) remuneration she receives is to be adjusted according to the new salary. 
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					Any amount to be reimbursed by virtue of the taxation limits set out in the Employment Insurance Act (1.5) times the maximum yearly allowance) is at the employee's expense. 
				</item>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Additional benefits under 26.2 and 26.4 are not payable in the following cases: 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			<list type="Alpha">
				
				<item langue="en">
					an employee who received a termination of employment notice before advising the University of the pregnancy, the adoption or the upcoming birth; 
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					an employee was terminated for cause before advising the University of the maternity or parental leave, where the termination was not overturned through the grievance process;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					an employee who submitted a resignation before advising the University of the pregnancy, the adoption or the upcoming birth; 
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					an employee who was suspended for disciplinary reasons before advising the University of the pregnancy, the adoption or the upcoming birth, where the additional benefits are not payable during the suspension period; 
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					an employee who took part in a strike or a work stoppage, except when the maternity or parental leave began before the work stoppage or strike; 
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					an employee who does not meet the requirements for Employment Insurance benefits as determined under the Employment Insurance Act.
				</item>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Employees entitled to maternity and/or parental leave retain and accumulate their seniority and can continue to participate in employee benefits by paying their share, in which case the University continues to pay its part.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Extra leaves
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			<list type="Alpha">
				
				<item langue="en">
					Following maternity leave, an employee may request a one- (1) year leave of absence without pay but with job security. 
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					Following parental leave (without maternity leave before parental leave), the employee may request a one (1) year leave of absence without pay but with job security. 
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					A one- (1) year leave of absence without pay but with job security may be approved at the discretion of the responsible faculty or service, who keeps the position available for the employee's eventual return to work. 
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					Following maternity and/or parental leave, an employee may request leave without pay of up to two (2) years instead of the leave under 26.8 a) and b), in which case the University would no longer be bound to keep the position open for the employee's return. Such leave is automatically approved by the responsible faculty or service. 
				</item>
				
				<paragraph langue="en">
					If an employee wishes to return to work after a two-year (2) leave of absence, he may request his name be added to the recall list, pursuant to 20.1 a) as if he had been laid off. He benefits from the provisions set out under 20.1 f) only. 
				</paragraph>
				
				<item langue="en">
					The choice of 26.8 a), b) or d) must be made in writing at least two (2) weeks before the end of the maternity and/or parental leave. 
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					An employee cannot be compelled to take annual vacation time during maternity and/or parental leave but can use it to extend his leave.
				</item>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Paternity leave
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				An employee can claim paternity leave and receive one hundred percent (100%) of his salary, without this leave being considered part of the benefits and leave covered by provincial laws, for a maximum of three (3) working days. It is therefore distinct from the parental leave described above.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Such leave is claimed by an employee who is not the birth mother, within five (5) days of the birth of a child.
			</paragraph>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<article id="article-27">
		
		<title langue="en">
			SICK LEAVE
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				<strong>
					Note: Definitions of disability appear under 38.1, Group Insurance, and are hereby referenced.
				</strong>
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Sick leave benefits are payable for a maximum period of one hundred and nineteen (119) calendar days or for a period ending on the employment termination date identified before the start of the disability, whichever period is shorter. A gradual return to work or a return to work part time or to a part-time position is included in the calculation of the one hundred and nineteen (119) calendar days of sick leave granted to the employee.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				A regular employee who has not completed his probationary period accumulates a half-day (0.5) of sick leave per month, which can be used during his probationary period.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				A regular employee with a total disability can receive sick leave benefits under the following conditions:
			</paragraph-numbered>
			<list type="Alpha">
				
				<item langue="en">
					at the beginning of the disability period, the employee informs his supervisor of the anticipated length of absence;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					the employee fills out the online application for sick leave within ten (10) working days from the start of the sick leave; 
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					the employee submits a medical note within three (3) days after returning to work, indicating the date of the appointment, the dates of absence, the doctor's name, signature and registration number, and any applicable functional limitations:
				</item>
				<list type="Bullet">
					
					<item langue="en">
						when the sick leave exceeds three (3) consecutive calendar days; or
					</item>
					
					<item langue="en">
						when the employee's sick leave record casts serious doubt on the validity of the request for sick leave, even when the sick leave is less than three (3) consecutive calendar days.
					</item>
				</list>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				When the disability period exceeds (10) days, the employee provides a medical certificate to the University, duly completed by his treating physician, no later than twenty (20) days after the start of the absence. This certificate is then to be renewed every month. Otherwise, the sick leave is without pay, and the faculty or service discontinues the salary from the date where a medical certificate was to be submitted and the days off work used up to that date are treated as annual leave. If the employee's annual leave has been exhausted, the absent days are treated as leave without pay and a Record of Employment is issued for potential Employment Insurance benefits.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				At any time during a sick leave, in order to determine the employee's eligibility for sick leave benefits or his ability to return to work, the University, through its Employee Health, Wellness and Leave Sector, may request that the employee undergo a medical assessment by one (1) or more physicians designated by the University, at the latter's expense. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				When the medical certificate or examination(s) do not support a sick leave due to disability or recognized under the long-term disability program, but the attending physician maintains that the employee cannot return to work, the employee is on leave without pay. A medical certificate is required every month to maintain the unpaid-leave status for a maximum of one hundred and nineteen (119) calendar days, then every six (6) months thereafter. The conditions set out in the article on seniority apply to the accumulation and retention of seniority during this period. The employment is terminated two (2) years after the start of the absence. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Under normal work-related circumstances, the University's sick leave plan is not intended to allow an employee to benefit from a period of therapeutic rest simply for reasons of fatigue, stress or for other similar reasons resulting from personality conflicts with his supervisor, legitimate disciplinary measures or any other similar reason as determined by the Employee Health, Wellness and Leave Sector.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				In order to protect confidentiality, the employee arranges for medical notes and certificates to be forwarded by the employee or the doctor directly to the health care professional in the Employee Health, Wellness and Leave Sector.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Under no conditions, is the employee required to disclose the nature of his sickness or the name of his treating physician to any representative of the University other than the health care professional in the Employee Health, Wellness and Leave Sector.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				In order to renew the maximum period of one hundred and nineteen (119) calendar days of sick leave under 27.1, the employee must: 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			<list type="Alpha">
				
				<item langue="en">
					return to work for one (1) full working day before a new sick leave period in the case of a completely unrelated and different disability, where the accident or sickness occurred after the day of return to work; or
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					return to work for thirty (30) consecutive calendar days before a new sick leave period if the disability results from the same cause. During this period of thirty (30) consecutive days, the employee cannot take annual leave.
				</item>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				An employee who misses work after receiving a notice of termination of employment is not eligible for sick leave benefits unless he provides a medical certificate for any sick leave after this notice. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The benefit period of one hundred and nineteen (119) calendar days or the balance of unused days in this period cannot be cashed in or accumulated.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Sick leave benefits are reduced by the amount of compensation paid under an occupational health and safety program, or the amount of similar benefits received by the employee under a governmental insurance plan by reason of sickness or accident.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				When an employee is injured or sick during leave without pay, he is not eligible for sick leave benefits.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				An employee who is still on sick leave after the benefit period of one hundred and nineteen (119) calendar days may be eligible for long-term disability benefits under the long-term disability insurance plan under Article 38 of the Agreement.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The above sick leave benefits are not granted under certain circumstances, including but not limited to:
			</paragraph-numbered>
			<list type="Alpha">
				
				<item langue="en">
					an injury or sickness voluntarily self-inflicted with the sole purpose of benefiting from the provisions of this article; 
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					pregnancy (however, complications arising from the pregnancy are covered by this article upon presentation of a medical certificate); 
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					diseases or injuries sustained while committing an act recognized as a criminal offence by a duly constituted court or while serving a prison sentence;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					when the employee is on vacation; or
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					during a strike, except if the valid disability started before the beginning of the strike and a medical certificate was provided prior to the strike.
				</item>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				When the disability stems from drug addiction, alcoholism or any other addiction recognized as a disability, sick leave benefits are to be granted only during the leave required for the treatment of these conditions by a physician or another specialist approved by the University. Treatment for such a disability, such as a treatment program or a recovery plan, must be approved by the Employee Health, Wellness and Leave Sector.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Wherever possible and reasonable, the University accommodates employees with functional limitations to facilitate their return to work after an accident or illness. If possible, and depending on the accommodations to be made, the parties can also decide to place an employee in a vacant position that is in keeping with the functional limitations.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				When an employee who has not been given sick leave benefits requires reasonable accommodation according to his treating physician, the University can obtain an assessment from a specialist to determine the functional limitations and the accommodations required. The University pays the cost of such an assessment. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The employee notifies the Employee Health, Wellness and Leave Sector, of the health condition, disability or impairment preventing him from meeting the job requirements.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The employee provides the Employee Health, Wellness and Leave Sector, in confidence, with the information and documents from health professionals to properly explain the nature and extent of the accommodation requested. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The employee and Institute support and collaborate with the University in its efforts to identify and provide the necessary accommodations, in particular by helping to identify solutions that the University can reasonably consider to meet the employee's needs. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Sick leave for term employee
				</strong>
				s
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Term employees accumulate one half (0.5) day of sick leave per month for the duration of the contract.
			</paragraph>
			<list type="Alpha">
				
				<item langue="en">
					In the case of a long-term illness, the employee is entitled to use accumulated sick leave to cover the waiting period before receiving Employment Insurance benefits. 
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					Sick leave can be accumulated when a contract is renewed but cannot be cashed in. The unused sick leave from previous contracts in a position of continuous service is credited up to a maximum of fifteen (15) working days. 
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					The terms, conditions and limitations for sick leave for a regular employee apply to a term employee using the above leave.
				</item>
			</list>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<article id="article-28">
		
		<title langue="en">
			ANNUAL LEAVE
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Continuous service for the accumulation of annual leave
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			<list type="Alpha">
				
				<item langue="en">
					Subject to 28.1 c), the date of continuous service for the accumulation of annual leave in the case of a regular employee covered by the bargaining unit at the time the agreement is ratified is the one indicated in the Human Resources Service file.
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					The date of continuous service for the accumulation of annual leave in the case of an employee whose first regular position starts after the date the agreement is ratified corresponds to the date of the start of his continuous service with the University.
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					A term employee employed by the University on January 24, 2007, or hired after that date, whose functions were covered by the bargaining unit and who started a regular position other than the one held on a term basis before the date the agreement was ratified is deemed to have the more recent of January 24, 2007, or the date he was hired as the date of continuous service for the accumulation of annual leave.
				</item>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Annual leave may be taken as it is accumulated during the course of the year beginning on January 1 of every year. Annual leave is accumulated on a monthly basis but is established at each pay period. When days of annual leave are added on the basis of the date of continuous service for the accumulation of annual leave, the monthly accumulation is amended to include these additions from the time of the application date.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The University determines the period when an employee may take his annual leave. This determination must take into account the requirements of the position. Every faculty or service determines the periods when annual leave is limited, the maximum number of people who may take annual leave at the same time, as well as the maximum number of days that can be taken together. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				An employee is guaranteed entitlement to take two (2) consecutive weeks of annual leave, if he wishes, between the first Monday after June 15 and the Friday preceding Labour Day each year.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				An employee provides notice of his choice of annual leave for the coming summer no later than May 1 of that same year. He gives three (3) choices, specifying the order of preference. If he requests more than two (2) consecutive weeks of annual leave, the employee indicates which weeks he would prefer in case the weeks, in their entirety, cannot be granted. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				No later than May 15, the supervisor prepares the annual leave schedule for the summer, taking into consideration the preferences expressed, and inform the concerned employees of the schedule. If a given week of annual leave cannot be granted to the employees who requested it, and if the concerned employees and the supervisor cannot readily agree on an acceptable compromise, the priority for approval is based on seniority. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				For annual leave requests outside of the summer period, or for requests made after May 1 for this period, the "first come, first served" principle applies.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				A supervisor may not refuse a request for annual leave without just and reasonable cause.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Before taking annual leave, an employee must obtain authorization from his supervisor and complete his request through the University's electronic leave management system.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				When an employee is unable to take an annual leave already approved by his supervisor due to an illness that occurred before the start of the scheduled annual leave, the employee may postpone his annual leave to a later date with the agreement of his supervisor.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				An employee who becomes ill during a period of annual leave begins his sick leave only at the end of the on-going period of annual leave, if necessary.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				An employee who is hospitalized and admitted as a result of an illness or accident that occurred during a period of annual leave may postpone his annual leave to a later date. In that event, the employee must provide the Human Resources Service, Occupational Health, Disability and Leave sector, with proof of his hospitalization, which determines the employee's eligibility.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				An employee who holds a permanent regular position and who is not on probation may borrow and use up to ten (10) days of unearned annual leave.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				As long as a regular employee whose probation period is over has taken at least two (2) weeks of annual leave in the year, he may accumulate and automatically carry forward to the following year, up to ten (10) days of unused annual leave in addition to the annual accumulation. Subject to agreement on when this leave is to be used, and the approval of the dean or director, the employee may accumulate up to a maximum of thirty (30) days of annual leave.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Annual leave for seasonal and part-time regular employees is calculated and paid on a prorated basis according to the number of hours worked. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Employees on sick leave approved by the University or on leave due to a workplace accident accumulate annual leave credits during the first one hundred and nineteen (119) calendar days of their absence.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<table>
				<tableheading>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								Date de service continu aux fins d'accumulation de congés annuels
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								Accumulation de congés annuels
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
				</tableheading>
				<tablebody>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							Jusqu’à 1 an
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							Taux d’accumulation de 1,25 j/m = 15 j/a
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							Entre 1 an et 4 ans
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							Taux d’accumulation de 1,33 j/m = 16 j/a
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							Entre 5 et 10 ans
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							Taux d’accumulation de 1,66 j/m = 20 j/a
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							11 ans
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							Taux d’accumulation de 1,75 j/m = 21 j/a
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							12 ans
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							Taux d’accumulation de 1,75 j/m = 21 j/a
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							13 ans
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							Taux d’accumulation de 1,83 j/m = 22 j/a
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							14 ans
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							Taux d’accumulation de 1,83 j/m = 22 j/a
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							15 ans
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							Taux d’accumulation de 1,91 j/m = 23 j/a
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							16 ans
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							Taux d’accumulation de 1,91 j/m = 23 j/a
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							17 ans
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							Taux d’accumulation de 2,00 j/m = 24 j/a
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							18 ans
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							Taux d’accumulation de 2,08 j/m = 25 j/a
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							25 ans
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							Taux d’accumulation de 2,50 j/m =30 j/a
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
				</tablebody>
			</table>
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				During a leave without pay of more than ten (10) consecutive days in a given year, an employee does not accumulate annual leave.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			<table>
				<tableheading>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								Date of continuous service for the accumulation of annual leave
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								Accumulation of Annual Leave
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
				</tableheading>
				<tablebody>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							Up to 1 year
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							Accumulation rate is 1,25 d/m = 15 d/a
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							Between 1 and 4 years
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							Accumulation rate is 1,33 d/m = 16 d/a
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							Between 5 and 10 years
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							Accumulation rate is 1,66 d/m = 20 d/a
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							11 years
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							Accumulation rate is 1,75 d/m = 21 d/a
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							12 years
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							Accumulation rate is 1,75 d/m = 21 d/a
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							13 years
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							Accumulation rate is 1,83 d/m = 22 d/a
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							14 years
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							Accumulation rate is 1,83 d/m = 22 d/a
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							15 years
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							Accumulation rate is 1,91 d/m = 23 d/a
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							16 years
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							Accumulation rate is 1,91 d/m = 23 d/a
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							17 years
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							Accumulation rate is 2,00 d/m = 24 d/a
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							18 years
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							Accumulation rate is 2,08 d/m = 25 d/a
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							25 years
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							Accumulation rate is 2,50 d/m =30 d/a
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
				</tablebody>
			</table>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Notwithstanding the preceding, an employee in a class 10 (with supervision) or higher position with less than five (5) years of service for accumulation of annual leave purposes, but who has already accumulated twenty (20) days of annual leave per year, continues to be entitled to this leave.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Term employees accumulate 1.25 days of annual leave per month. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<article id="article-29">
		
		<title langue="en">
			STATUTORY AND CHRISTMAS HOLIDAYS
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The following statutory holidays are paid holiday days:
			</paragraph-numbered>
			<list type="Dash">
				
				<item langue="en">
					New Year's Day
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					Family Day
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					Good Friday
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					Easter Monday
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					Victoria Day
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					Canada Day
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					Civic Holiday
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					Labour Day 
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					Thanksgiving
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					Christmas Day
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					Boxing Day
				</item>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				The calendar is established ahead of time, based on the University calendar.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				If one of the statutory holidays coincides with an employee's weekly day of rest other than Saturday or Sunday, the employee is granted a day of holiday leave at a later date agreed on by the employee and his immediate supervisor. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Christmas holidays
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Employees are granted paid leave according to the normal work schedule for the period beginning on December 22 at 5:00 p.m. (or at the hour determined in the work schedule) and ending on January 3 at 8:45 a.m. (or at the employee's normal time to start work). If January 3 falls on a Saturday or Sunday, employees return to work at 8:45 a.m. on the first working day that follows.
			</paragraph>
			<list type="Alpha">
				
				<item langue="en">
					If December 23 or December 24 falls on a Saturday or Sunday, floating leave days are granted in the following calendar year to employees employed by the University on December 31 of that year, subject to the following terms and conditions:
				</item>
				<list type="Dash">
					
					<item langue="en">
						December 23: one day of floating leave
					</item>
					
					<item langue="en">
						December 24: half a day of floating leave.
					</item>
				</list>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				An employee who, at the employer's request, works one of the holidays listed under 29.1 is paid in time, salary or both, as he prefers, at time and a half (150 %) for his normal hourly rate, in addition to his base salary for the day. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				An employee who, at the employer's request made before the start of the Christmas holiday period under 29.2, works one day of the Christmas holiday other than those under 29.1 or December 23 or 24, is compensated in time or salary, at time and a half (150%) of his normal hourly rate, in addition to his base salary for the day. The method of payment is established before the holiday by the dean or the director of the faculty or service, or his delegate, along with the employee.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				An employee who, at the employer's request made after the start of the Christmas holiday under 29.2, works one day of the Christmas holiday other than those under 29.1 or December 23 and 24, is compensated in time, salary or both, as he prefers, at time and a half (150 %) of his normal hourly rate, in addition to his base salary for the day.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				In both of the above cases, this overtime work is optional.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				An employee who, at the employer's request, works on December 23 and the morning of December 24, receives in addition to his base pay equivalent floating leave in the following calendar year. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				When the University calendar shows the University open on December 23 and/or 24, employees are credited floating leave of one (1) day for December 23 at half (1\2) a day for December 24, as applicable, to be used in the following calendar year.
			</paragraph-numbered>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<article id="article-30">
		
		<title langue="en">
			VARIOUS PAID AND UNPAID LEAVES
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				In view of the circumstances underlying the following holiday leaves, the employee requires the written consent of the dean or service directors, or their delegates.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Special leave with pay cannot be granted for periods during which the University is closed.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Bereavement leave with pay
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			<list type="Alpha">
				
				<item langue="en">
					An employee is granted paid leave of five (5) working days for the death of an immediate family member. The term "immediate family" is limited to the father, mother, step-parent, foster parent, brother, sister, spouse, child, spouse's child, ward, father-in-law or mother-in-law.
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					An employee is granted paid leave of three (3) working days for the death of a grandchild of the employee or his spouse. When the funeral following the death takes place more than three hundred and twenty (320) kilometres from Ottawa (200 miles), the employee gets one (1) day of additional paid leave. 
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					An employee is granted one (1) working day of paid leave for the death of his sister-in-law, brother-in-law, son-in-law, daughter-in-law, grandparent, uncle or aunt, or that of his spouse. 
				</item>
				
				<paragraph langue="en">
					When the funeral following the death takes place more than three hundred and twenty (320) kilometres from Ottawa (200 miles), the employee receives one (1) day of additional paid leave. 
				</paragraph>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Marriage leave
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Once during his employment at the University, a regular employee is granted five (5) working days of paid leave for his own wedding. The employee must submit this request at least four (4) weeks in advance.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Moving leave
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				At most once per calendar year, an employee is granted one (1) working day of paid leave for moving his own permanent place of residence.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Leave for medical appointments and treatments
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			<list type="Alpha">
				
				<item langue="en">
					Employees endeavour at all times to schedule their medical appointments outside of work hours or at the beginning or end of the work day to minimize the impact of their absence on their work sector. 
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					Employees give their supervisor reasonable advance warning when they have to take leave for a medical appointment or treatment.
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					A maximum period of two (2) hours is granted for preventive or diagnostic appointments with a doctor, dentist or optometrist. If an absence of more than two (2) hours is required, this period is accounted for and treated as sick leave unless the time is made up for in hours of work.
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					All appointments for medical treatment purposes are accounted for and treated as sick leave and validated by the Employee Health, Wellness and Leave Sector, Human Resources Service. Employees accumulate hours approved for appointments and enter them into the University's electronic leave management system as half-days or full days of sick leave.
				</item>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Leave for family obligations or for circumstances deemed exceptional 
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				A regular employee is entitled to maximum of twenty-one (21) hours of paid leave per calendar year under the following circumstances:
			</paragraph>
			<list type="Alpha">
				
				<item langue="en">
					For a medical or dental appointment for a family member who is incapable of attending the appointment without accompaniment, or for appointments with appropriate school authorities or at an adoption agency when alternate arrangements are not possible. An employee is expected to make every reasonable effort to schedule medical or dental appointments for family members so as to minimize or preclude the employee's absence from work;
				</item>
				<list type="Roman">
					
					<item langue="en">
						For the purpose of 30.7 a), family includes a spouse, children of the spouse, foster children, parents, step-parents and foster parents as well as any other relative permanently residing in the employee's household or with whom the employee permanently resides;
					</item>
					
					<item langue="en">
						An employee requesting a leave under this provision must obtain prior authorization from the immediate supervisor. The supervisor's approval must not be unreasonably withheld.
					</item>
				</list>
				
				<item langue="en">
					To provide for the immediate and temporary care of a sick member of the employee's family or an elderly member of the employee's family and to provide an employee with time to make alternate care arrangements where the illness is of a longer duration;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					When exceptional circumstances prevent the employee from reporting to work, circumstances such as hospitalization of a family member or fire, flood or break-in at the employee's residence. 
				</item>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				The employee advises the immediate supervisor as soon as possible of any circumstances listed in 30.7 b) and c). 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Time used is counted in hours but recorded by the employee in the electronic leave management system in blocks of half or full days.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Special leave without pay
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				In addition to the leave provided under 30.7, a regular or term employee can also be granted a maximum of 10 days special leave without pay as set out in the Employment Standards Act for any of the following reasons:
			</paragraph>
			<list type="Alpha">
				
				<item langue="en">
					personal injury, illness or medical emergency;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					the death, sickness, injury or medical emergency of a close relative or dependant; or
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					an urgent matter concerning a close relative or dependant.
				</item>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				A partial day of leave taken under this Article counts as one full day of leave. Reasonable proof of the circumstances for the leave must be provided to the immediate supervisor.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Family medical leave
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				As outlined in the Ontario Employment Standards Act, employees are entitled to family leave for medical reasons of up to eight (8) calendar weeks to provide care or support to a close family member if a qualified health practitioner issues a certificate stating that the individual has a serious medical condition with a significant risk of death occurring within a period of twenty-six (26) weeks or such shorter period as may be prescribed. The employee can claim federal Employment Insurance, provided that he meets the conditions.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Court leave
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Paid leave is granted to employees for the period when they must:
			</paragraph>
			<list type="Alpha">
				
				<item langue="en">
					be available for jury selection;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					serve on a jury; or
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					attend, by subpoena or summons, as a witness in any proceeding in which the employee is not a party. 
				</item>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				To be granted court leave, the employee must inform the dean or service director in writing as soon as possible and substantiate the court appearance with appropriate documents.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Pay received during court leave is decreased by any amount paid by the court for jury duty.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Court leave does not apply to members who are serving a prison sentence.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				An employee called before a civil or criminal court or administrative tribunal in a case where he is involved is eligible for leave without pay or can use days of annual leave in order to attend. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Attendance at compulsory religious service
				</strong>
				s
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				An employee is granted paid leave when the employee is required to attend a mandatory religious service taking place during work hours. The University sets the amount of time deemed adequate to attend the service. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Leave without pay
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			<list type="Alpha">
				
				<item langue="en">
					The dean or the service director, as appropriate, may authorize leave without pay with protection of the person's position for a regular employee who has five (5) years of continuous service for a up to one (1) year. The leave period may be extended after consultation with the Human Resources Service. In this case, any period in excess of twelve (12) months falls under 30.12f) in regards to the applicable benefits.
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					During an authorized leave without pay with protection of the person's position, the employee's position must be kept available, even when a replacement is hired.
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					Approval of a leave without pay without protection of the person's position is the responsibility of Human Resources Service management and must not be denied without a valid reason. Such leave is not to be approved for a period exceeding one (1) year. Under very exceptional circumstances, a request for leave of up to two years may be granted. 
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					The authorization of a leave without pay with protection of the person's position is at the discretion of the dean or service director and takes into account the following criteria:
				</item>
				<list type="Roman">
					
					<item langue="en">
						the reason for the leave;
					</item>
					
					<item langue="en">
						the duration of the leave;
					</item>
					
					<item langue="en">
						the employee's seniority;
					</item>
					
					<item langue="en">
						the projected length of service after the return to work;
					</item>
					
					<item langue="en">
						the possibilities of obtaining a competent replacement on a temporary basis; and
					</item>
					
					<item langue="en">
						performance.
					</item>
					
					<paragraph langue="en">
						Human Resources Service is available to all deans and service directors for advice.
					</paragraph>
				</list>
				
				<item langue="en">
					A regular employee who is granted a leave without pay with protection of the person's position remains entitled to insured benefits as follows: 
				</item>
				<list type="Roman">
					
					<item langue="en">
						For the first three (3) months of leave, the employee is covered for all of the insured benefits to which his salary normally gives entitlement, according to the distribution of costs just prior to the leave.
					</item>
					
					<item langue="en">
						The employee can continue participating in the insured benefits program of the University after the third (3rd) month of leave without pay, provided that the Human Resources Service is notified in writing at least thirty (30) days before the start of the leave and that the employee undertakes to pay the costs in full (employer and employee contributions).
					</item>
					
					<item langue="en">
						During the leave, the regular employee can continue contributing to the University pension plan provided that he pays both the employer and employee contributions. 
					</item>
				</list>
				
				<item langue="en">
					A regular employee who is granted a leave without pay without protection of the person's position can, but is not required to, continue contributing to insured benefits as follows. 
				</item>
				<list type="Roman">
					
					<item langue="en">
						For the first three (3) months of leave, the employee can be covered for all of the insured benefits to which his salary normally gives entitlement, according to the usual distribution of costs.
					</item>
					
					<item langue="en">
						The employee can continue participating in the insured benefits program of the University after the third (3rd) month of leave without pay, provided that the Human Resources Service is notified in writing at least thirty (30) days before the start of the leave and that the employee undertakes to pay the costs in full (employer and employee contributions).
					</item>
					
					<item langue="en">
						During the leave, the regular employee can continue contributing to the University pension plan provided that he pays both the employer and employee contributions.
					</item>
					
					<item langue="en">
						Access to the program for exemption from tuition fees for the employee and his dependents is not available during this type of leave. 
					</item>
					
					<item langue="en">
						During the leave and for up to twelve (12) months thereafter, the employee may apply for any position for which he meets the essential requirements. The rules under 18.4 apply. An employee who is appointed to a position pursuant to Article 18 must be in that position by the date indicated on the notification of appointment. If the employee turns down the position, he is deemed to have abandoned his employment. 
					</item>
				</list>
				
				<item langue="en">
					A regular employee who was granted leave without pay with protection of his position and who wants to return to his position before the end of his leave or the scheduled return date must notify the dean or service director in writing at least one (1) calendar month before the new scheduled return date and must obtain the dean or service director's authorization.
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					Progress-through-the-ranks (PTR) increases are not withheld for periods of leave of absence without pay of three months or less. In the event of a leave of absence without pay for a period exceeding three months, PTR increases are withheld on a prorated basis of the leave period. A full PTR increase is granted to a regular employee on leave of absence without pay when the activities during his leave are recognized as being experience or studies relevant to his position at the University. In such instances, the decision is taken jointly by the dean or service director and the Human Resources Service management. 
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					A regular employee who was granted leave without pay with protection of his position and who returns to his position at the end of his leave receives the same basic salary that he was receiving just before his leave, adjusted for cost-of-living salary increases that would have been granted during his absence, as long as these adjustments do not put him above the maximum salary for his salary class.
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					Regular employees already on leave without pay are not eligible for the various leaves covered by the Agreement.
				</item>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Leave without pay to hold public office
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				A leave without pay for the purpose of taking part in military or paramilitary activities for the Government of Canada is approved upon request in accordance with the terms and conditions of government agreements and programs in force.
			</paragraph>
			<list type="Alpha">
				
				<item langue="en">
					A regular employee who is an official candidate for election to the Parliament of Canada, to a provincial legislature or assembly, or to the office of mayor of Ottawa or Gatineau or any similar office as determined by the University, may request a leave without pay for a maximum period of sixty (60) consecutive calendar days to campaign for office. A regular employee may request a leave of absence without pay without protection of his position for a maximum period equal to the duration of his first term if he is elected.
				</item>
			</list>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<article id="article-31">
		
		<title langue="en">
			SELF - FUNDED LEAVE
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Regular employees may take advantage of the self-funded leave plan in accordance with the terms and conditions set out in the University's Policy 46a.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Although authorization for self-funded leave remains at the discretion of the dean or the director of a service, such leave is not refused without just and reasonable cause. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<article id="article-32">
		
		<title langue="en">
			TRAINING AND DEVELOPMENT
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The parties acknowledge the need for training and development for regular employees covered by the bargaining unit.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				A labour-management training and development committee is struck within ninety (90) days after the signing of the Agreement.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				This committee includes four (4) members, including two (2) appointed by the University and two (2) selected from among the regular employees designated by the Institute. Any decision by this committee must be unanimous. The committee sets its own rules of operation and determines the procedures it deems appropriate for its internal governance. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The committee meets, as required or according to a set schedule, on the date and at the place agreed upon by the parties.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The mandate of the training and development committee is to: 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			<list type="Dash">
				
				<item langue="en">
					Promote greater employee participation in training and development activities;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					keep the rules simple and accessible to all;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					prepare and organize collective training and development activities with regards to the needs expressed by the bargaining unit, and appropriate for the work or career plans of employees; and
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					encourage employees to take responsibility for managing their training and development activities.
				</item>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				On May 1 of each year, the committee is allocated a minimum annual budget of fifty thousand dollars ($50,000). The committee allocates its budget according to the collective training and development activities, and makes any required amendments identified during the year.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The decisions of the training and development committee are binding within the limits of its mandate and the budget provided to it.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				An employee who is denied a request for training by his faculty or service can bring this request to the attention of the training and development committee, which can then attempt to resolve the issue by paying for the training out of its budget or attempting to find an alternative way to meet the requirement.
			</paragraph-numbered>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<article id="article-33">
		
		<title langue="en">
			TRAVEL EXPENSES
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Employees travelling for business, training, development or to attend conferences with prior written authorization from the dean or the director of a service or a delegate are reimbursed for their expenses according to the terms of Policy 21, Travel Expenses and Field Trips, in effect at the time the expenses were incurred.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Section 33.1 does not preclude a dean or service director from providing written permission for an employee to attend, at the employee's request, a conference, without reimbursement of their travel expenses. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<article id="article-34">
		
		<title langue="en">
			PUBLICATIONS AND COPYRIGHT
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				When an employee acts as a sole author, a co-author or an editor of an original publication, the employee's authorship or editorship is normally shown on the title page of the publication, and this, with the discretion of the University.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The University agrees that original stand-alone articles and professional papers prepared by an employee within the scope of the employee's regular duties are retained in the appropriate departmental files for the normal life of such files, as outlined in University policies and regulations.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				An employee wishing to publish a stand-alone original article or professional or technical paper written by the employee in professional media must request approval from the University. Such approval must not be withheld without just cause. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<article id="article-35">
		
		<title langue="en">
			TECHNOLOGICAL CHANGES
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				When the University is planning to make technological changes that will eliminate one or more positions or significantly change the way employees carry out their tasks or the knowledge normally required for the position, it notifies the Institute at least six (6) months before implementing the changes. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				At the point of implementation, and if necessary, the provisions under Article 19 : Elimination of a regular position and lay-off will apply.
			</paragraph-numbered>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<article id="article-36">
		
		<title langue="en">
			RETIREMENT ALLOWANCES
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Regular employees who are not currently and who have not been on long-term disability for a minimum period of three (3) months and who are not on leave without pay at the time of their retirement receive a retirement allowance in accordance with the terms and conditions set out in this article. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Definitions:
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			<list type="Alpha">
				
				<item langue="en">
					<strong>
						Standard salary for position
					</strong>
				</item>
				
				<paragraph langue="en">
					Salary corresponding to the standard of the pay grade for the position held by the retiring employee, in accordance with the salary scale in effect as of May 1, 2003. 
				</paragraph>
				
				<item langue="en">
					<strong>
						Multiplier factor
					</strong>
				</item>
				<list type="Dash">
					
					<item langue="en">
						equal to 0.004 for employees who are less than 60 years of age or who have not reached "factor 90".
					</item>
					
					<item langue="en">
						equal to 0.006 for employees who are at least 60 years of age or who have reached "factor 90" between the ages of 55 and 60.
					</item>
				</list>
				
				<item langue="en">
					<strong>
						Factor 90
					</strong>
				</item>
				
				<paragraph langue="en">
					When the sum of the employee's age (expressed in years, months and days) plus his years of participation in the pension plan (expressed in years and half-months [0,5]) is at least 90. 
				</paragraph>
				
				<item langue="en">
					<strong>
						Number of years of service at the University
					</strong>
				</item>
				
				<paragraph langue="en">
					Total number of years of active service at the University of Ottawa (expressed in years, months and days). This excludes years with other employers credited for pension purposes, years of leave without pay and years of service prior to continuous service at the University. 
				</paragraph>
				
				<item langue="en">
					<strong>
						Number of years of service remaining before normal retirement age
					</strong>
				</item>
				
				<paragraph langue="en">
					Number of years of service an employee still needs to work before reaching the normal retirement date, i.e. age 65 (expressed in years and months). This figure must never exceed five (5) (i.e. it corresponds to five (5) for all employees between the ages of 55 and 60). It progressively decreases between age 60 and 65 to reach zero (0) at age 65.
				</paragraph>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Calculation formula
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Eligible employees who take their retirement between the ages of 55 and 65 are entitled to a retirement allowance calculated using the following formula: 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				[standard for position] x [multiplier factor] x [number of years of service at the University] x [number of years of service remaining before normal retirement age]] 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				In accordance with the Income Tax Act, certain amounts may not be subject to taxation. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Employees must give three (3) months notice that they are retiring in order to receive the retirement allowance. Such notice is irrevocable. Employees are encouraged to give as much notice as possible in order to help the faculty or service with its budget and succession planning. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Retirement allowances are payable in the month following the employee's retirement.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<table>
				<tableheading>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								Classe
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								PTS
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								%
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								Minimum ($)
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								Standard ($
							</strong>
							)
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								Maximum ($)
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								PDR (2 %)
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
				</tableheading>
				<tablebody>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							6
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							210 - 244
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							84
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							30 605
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							36 605
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							40 078
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							729
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							7
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							245 - 286
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							83
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							33 073
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							39 847
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							43 832
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							797
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							8
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							287 - 335
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							81
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							35 552
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							43 891
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							48 280
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							878
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							9
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							336 -399
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							39 211
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							49 013
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							53 914
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							980
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							10
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							400 - 459
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							43 815
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							54 768
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							60 245
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1095
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							11
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							460 - 540
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							49 253
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							61 566
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							67 723
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1231
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							12
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							541 - 634
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							55 444
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							69 305
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							76 235
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1386
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							13
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							635 - 745
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							62 407
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							78 009
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							85 810
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1560
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
				</tablebody>
			</table>
			<paragraph langue="en">
				<strong>
					SALARY STRUCTURE 2003-2004, 35 HOURS /WEEK
				</strong>
			</paragraph>
			<table>
				<tableheading>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							Grade
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								PTS
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								%
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								Minimum ($)
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								Standard ($
							</strong>
							)
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								Maximum ($)
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								PTR (2 %)
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
				</tableheading>
				<tablebody>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							6
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							210 - 244
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							84
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							30 605
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							36 605
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							40 078
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							729
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							7
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							245 - 286
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							83
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							33 073
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							39 847
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							43 832
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							797
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							8
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							287 - 335
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							81
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							35 552
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							43 891
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							48 280
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							878
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							9
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							336 -399
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							39 211
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							49 013
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							53 914
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							980
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							10
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							400 - 459
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							43 815
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							54 768
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							60 245
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1095
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							11
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							460 - 540
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							49 253
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							61 566
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							67 723
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1231
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							12
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							541 - 634
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							55 444
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							69 305
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							76 235
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1386
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							13
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							635 - 745
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							62 407
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							78 009
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							85 810
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1560
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
				</tablebody>
			</table>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<article id="article-37">
		
		<title langue="en">
			PENSION FUND
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Barring any agreement to the contrary between the parties, the University maintains in force the University of Ottawa Retirement Pension Plan and the benefits included therein for the duration of the Agreement.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The University undertakes the necessary steps to amend the University Board of Governors Regulations on the Pension Plan Committee to include a position for a member of the bargaining unit, to be designated by the Institute. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<article id="article-38">
		
		<title langue="en">
			GROUP INSURANCE
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Definitions
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				<strong>
					Total disability:
				</strong>
				An employee is considered to be totally disabled when he suffers from a total and uninterrupted disability attributable to an injury, sickness, complications resulting from pregnancy or a mental condition. He is unable to perform the duties of his usual position for the duration of the maximum number of days of sick leave. Subsequently, the conditions established by the insurance provider in the article on extended long-term disability apply. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				<strong>
					Partial disability:
				</strong>
				An employee is considered to be totally disabled when he suffers from a total and uninterrupted disability attributable to an injury, sickness, complications resulting from pregnancy or a mental condition. He is unable to perform the duties of his usual position for the duration of the maximum number of days of sick leave. However, with the University's approval, he may perform a portion of the usual duties of his position or another position with similar duties, and the salary received for the duties performed is at least 30 (thirty) percent less than his regular salary. An employee cannot be deemed partially disabled before having met the definition of totally disabled.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Eligibility for group insurance
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			<list type="Alpha">
				
				<item langue="en">
					Unless otherwise provided for by the Agreement or insurance plans in effect, all regular employees covered by the Agreement are eligible for group insurance from their starting date in a regular position. 
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					Term employees are eligible for certain group insurance coverage when they have accumulated two (2) years of continuous service, as provided in the clauses 38.6 to 38.14 inclusively.
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					When a regular employee reaches 65 years of age and is still working and holding a regular position, the group insurance as provided for in 38.15 ends. All other group insurance benefits are maintained, without age restriction, in accordance with the conditions that apply to all other employees.
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					Barring any provision to the contrary in the insurance contracts in effect, when an active employee dies, his spouse and dependants continue to have access to the collective insurance benefits for one (1) year.
				</item>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Group insurance
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Barring any agreement to the contrary between the parties to the Agreement, the terms and conditions governing the following collective insurance contracts remain the same as the ones in effect at the time of the issuance of the certificate held by the Institute: 
			</paragraph>
			<list type="Dash">
				
				<item langue="en">
					Basic employee life insurance 
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					Optional life insurance 
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					Extended health insurance plan 
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					Basic dental insurance 
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					Optional dental insurance 
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					Optional hospital room coverage 
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					Optional accidental death and dismemberment insurance 
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					Long term disability program
				</item>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The University's participation in the payment of collective insurance premiums is as indicated in clauses 38.6 and follows. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The University must provide the Institute with a copy of the insurance contracts in force, as well as the related additional clauses, as changes are made.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Basic employee life insurance
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Term employees who have worked two (2) years of continuous service and regular employees must participate in a basic life insurance plan for which the University pays one hundred (100) percent of the monthly premiums for the first $25,000 of coverage. The University agrees to continue the current practice with regards to the payment of insurance policy premiums. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Optional life insurance
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				If they so choose, term employees who have two (2) years of continuous employment and regular employees can participate in an optional life insurance plan based on the insurance provider's conditions and must pay the required premium for the policy. The University agrees to continue the current practice with regards to the payment of insurance policy premiums.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Extended health insurance plan
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Term employees who have two (2) years of continuous service and regular employees must participate in an extended health insurance plan, the monthly premiums for which are paid in full by the University. The University agrees to continue the current practice with regards to the payment of insurance policy premiums. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Basic dental insurance
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Term employees who have two (2) years of continuous service and regular employees must participate in a basic dental insurance plan, the monthly premiums for which are paid in full by the University. The University agrees to continue the current practice with regards to the payment of insurance policy premiums 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Reimbursement of dental expenses are based on the Ontario Dental Association fee guide for general practitioners for the year prior to the current year and on the least expensive treatment that yields professionally adequate results.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Optional dental insurance
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				If they so choose, term employees who have two (2) years of continuous service and regular employees can participate in an optional dental insurance plan in accordance with the provider's conditions and must pay the required premium for the policy. The University agrees to continue the current practice with regards to the payment of insurance policy premiums.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Reimbursement of dental expenses is based on the Ontario Dental Association fee guide for general practitioners for the year prior to the current year and on the least expensive treatment that yields professionally adequate results.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Optional hospital room coverage
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				If they so choose, term employees who have two (2) years of continuous service and regular employees can participate in an optional hospital room coverage in accordance with the provider's conditions and must pay the required premium for the policy. The University agrees to continue the current practice with regards to the payment of insurance policy premiums. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Optional accidental death and dismemberment insurance
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				If they so choose, term employees who have two (2) years of continuous service and regular employees can participate in an optional accidental death and dismemberment insurance plan in accordance with the provider's conditions and must pay the required premium for the policy. The University agrees to continue the current practice with regards to the payment of insurance policy premiums. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Long term disability program
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Regular employees participate in a long-term disability program for which the University pays one hundred (100) percent of the monthly premiums based on two thirds (2/3) of the employees' regular base salary. The University agrees to continue the current practice with regards to the payment of insurance policy premiums. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				When an employee is on sick leave for a sufficient length of time to foresee that he may need to avail himself of long-term disability insurance, the Human Resources Service takes the necessary steps to notify the employee of the actions that he needs to take to apply for benefits from the insurance provider. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				When an insurance provider determines an employee's eligibility for long-term disability benefits, this decision cannot be subject to a grievance under the Agreement.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				An employee is considered to be disabled when he is eligible for long-term disability benefits. The period of the employee's disability is considered to be continuous, notwithstanding the return to his full-time duties, provided that his return to work does not exceed one hundred and eighty (180) consecutive calendar days.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				An employee on disability does not accumulate annual leave. Any period during which an employee is on disability is considered, for pension plan purposes, to be a period of full-time employment at the University. When an employee is on disability during a given fiscal year, the employee's base salary may increase the following May 1st, for a cost-of-living adjustment only. Prior to April 30, 2010, the amount granted for seniority for the fiscal year is based on the overall portion of normal workload performed by the employee when he worked at the University during the year in question. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				As of May 1, 2010, if the employee has completed six (6) consecutive months of the fiscal year with his normal workload, he moves up to the next level of his pay grade. An employee is not eligible for any leave while he is on long-term disability.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				An employee has no workload obligations while he is on total disability and does not receive work-related compensation. Access to benefits included in the group insurance plan in which the employee was participating is maintained as if he were not on disability, but the employee does not make any contributions.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				When the employee's total disability ends and he resumes all or a portion of his workload, the remuneration granted by the University is based on the base salary determined pursuant to 38.19. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Subject to the approval of the dean or the service director, an employee can undertake a portion of his workload, with his doctor's approval, giving due regard to the employee's medical condition. The dean's or service director's approval must not be refused without valid reason. Disability benefits and pay are determined on the basis of the disability and the amount of time worked. Benefits granted to the employee are maintained as if the employee were not on disability. Contributions are determined on the basis of the usual formula and rate, but according to the work pay. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				An employee is entitled to sick leave pursuant to the provisions of the Agreement, provided that the condition requiring sick leave is different from the condition that caused the long-term disability. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				When an employee is on sick leave, disability benefits and pay are determined according to a formula established by the parties from time to time. 
			</paragraph>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<article id="article-39">
		
		<title langue="en">
			HEALTH, SAFETY, HYGIENE, WELLNESS, ACCIDENT AND OCCUPATIONAL DISEASES
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					General declaration
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				The University, the Institute and the employees recognize their respective obligations imposed by the 
				<emphasis>
					Ontario Occupational Health and Safety Act
				</emphasis>
				and associated legislation for ensuring the employees have workplaces in which their health and safety are protected. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				The University, the Institute and the employees work together to maintain the highest possible occupational health and safety conditions in order to prevent accidents and occupational diseases in accordance with the 
				<emphasis>
					Occupational Health and Safety Act and with the terms of the Workplace Safety and Insurance Act, 1997
				</emphasis>
				(WSIA).
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Health and safety committee
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Employees required to attend meetings of the University of Ottawa Health and Safety Committee lose neither wages nor benefits.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Employees on the Health and Safety Committee are entitled to be absent from work for reasonable periods of time without loss of wages or benefits to attend training sessions. Such absences are recommended by the Health and Safety Committee according to its responsibilities.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Return to work after an occupational accident or disease
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				The University, the Institute and the employees acknowledge their respective obligations under the Workplace Safety and Insurance Act, 1997 to cooperate towards an employee's speedy, safe return to work following an accident or an occupational disease.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Compensation during leave for accident or occupational disease
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				An employee off work because of an accident or an occupational disease continues to receive his regular basic salary for the duration of his absence or for up to a maximum of one hundred and nineteen (119) days. During this period, the University receives directly the amounts payable by the WSIB. Where the absence extends beyond the one hundred and nineteenth (119th) day, the employee receives the benefits to which he is entitled under the legislation directly from the WSIB.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Student supervision
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				An employee who, in performing his duties, is required to supervise an unpaid student is not deemed to be a supervisor in the meaning of the Occupational Health and Safety Act.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Work space
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				The University ensures employees have work spaces that comply with applicable provincial legislation and regulations.
			</paragraph>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<article id="article-40">
		
		<title langue="en">
			SUBCONTRACTING
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				A contract awarded to an outside contractor by the University cannot have the effect of reducing the normal working hours of employees or of preventing recalls of employees laid off from the sector in question because of the outside contract.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				If the University intends to contract out an important function or the majority of a function normally carried out by employees covered by the bargaining unit, the University first discusses its intent with the Institute. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				For the purposes of 40.2, the discussion takes place before the Labour Relations Committee. Either party can terminate discussions sixty (60) days after the Institute has been advised of the University's intention to subcontract and the justification for subcontracting, or sooner if an agreement is reached between the parties. An outside contractor cannot be awarded a contractor prior to discussions provided for in this Article have been undertaken.
			</paragraph-numbered>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<article id="article-41">
		
		<title langue="en">
			ELECTRONIC SURVEILLANCE
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Surveillance cameras installed by the University in and outside its buildings are to protect people and property. However, where the University reasonably believes that reprehensible acts have been or are being committed, resulting in the University rightfully installing surveillance cameras for investigative purposes, the University will comply with the applicable legislation.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The employees and the University undertake to abide by the existing policies and code of conduct governing the use of the University's computing resources. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Where electronic equipment is to be used for measuring performance or for assessing training needs, employees are notified in advance of their installation, and they are to be used for a maximum of one (1) month. In cases where there are permanent measures, the job descriptions reflect this. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<article id="article-42">
		
		<title langue="en">
			WORK TOOLS
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The University provides the tools required for employees to perform their work, and replaces them as required, unless there is a written agreement between the employee and the University. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<article id="article-43">
		
		<title langue="en">
			LABOUR RELATIONS ADVISORY COMMITTEE 
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Within sixty (60) days of contract ratification, the University and the Institute agree to create and maintain a Labour Relations Advisory Committee (LRAC) composed of no more than three (3) University representatives and no more than three (3) Institute representatives. Each party agrees to inform the other of its committee representatives. A party can invite experts as necessary, but informs the other party at least five (5) days before the date of the meeting at which the experts will be present. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The purpose of the LRAC is to review and discuss issues, problems or disputes, other than grievances, pertaining to working conditions or relations between the University on the one hand, and the employees and the Institute on the other. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The LRAC meets during normal working hours four (4) times a year or as required, at the written request of either party. The LRAC may adopt any procedure it deems appropriate to its internal governance and keeps minutes of each meeting, copies of which are sent to each representative. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The LRAC may make recommendations to the parties but has no decision-making authority. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The Institute representatives who are members of the bargaining unit have leave from their work to participate in LRAC meetings without loss of pay and benefits. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<article id="article-44">
		
		<title langue="en">
			PAYROLL
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Calendar of pay dates
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				The University follows the payroll and direct deposit calendar currently in effect.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Recovering overpayments and underpayments
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			<list type="Alpha">
				
				<item langue="en">
					In the case of a payroll error resulting in an overpayment to an employee, the University provides notice of the error to the employee as soon as possible. Unless an agreement has been made between the employee and the University within thirty (30) days of the overpayment, the University begins deducting an amount of not more than 15% of the employee's gross pay beginning on the next pay until the overpayment has been repaid in full. Notwithstanding the above procedure, the University can recover only overpayments made in the twelve (12) months preceding the notice of the error to the employee. 
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					In the case of a payroll error resulting in an amount due to an employee but not paid, the University promptly pays the amount due no later than the following pay date, if possible, and advises the employee the error has been corrected. 
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					In the case of termination of employment, the University can deduct any overpayments from the employee's final pay.
				</item>
			</list>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<article id="article-45">
		
		<title langue="en">
			PREMIUMS FOR SHIFTS AND ADDITIONAL RESPONSABILITIES
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Evening, night and weekend premiums
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			<list type="Alpha">
				
				<item langue="en">
					Employees whose work schedule requires working evenings, nights or weekends are paid the following premiums: 
				</item>
				<list type="Dash">
					
					<item langue="en">
						<strong>
							Evening premium:
						</strong>
						$0.85 per hour for time worked between 3 p.m. and 11 p.m.;
					</item>
					
					<item langue="en">
						<strong>
							Weekend premium:
						</strong>
						$1.00 per hour;
					</item>
					
					<item langue="en">
						<strong>
							Night premium: 
						</strong>
						$1.25 per hour worked for time worked between 11 p.m. and 7 a.m. 
					</item>
				</list>
				
				<item langue="en">
					The evening and night premium are added onto any weekend premium for hours worked. 
				</item>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The annual base pay for employees whose position requires regular evening, weekend or night schedules is adjusted proportionately to take into account the hours worked during these periods, i.e. the number of hours worked in a week are multiplied by 52/1,820.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Premiums for additional responsibilities
				</strong>
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				When the University temporarily, for a period of at least fifteen (15) days, assigns an employee additional responsibilities beyond his normal duties that are not included in his job description, the employee receives a second source of salary, regardless of the reason for this assignment. This additional remuneration lasts the entire duration of the assignment and is paid retroactively beginning on the first day the employee takes on the responsibilities. 
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Such remuneration is determined in the same way as for temporary assignments posted under 22.6 if the responsibilities are carried out during normal work hours. 
			</paragraph>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<article id="article-46">
		
		<title langue="en">
			Salary
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The University pays each employee by direct deposit into an account at a financial institution chosen by the employee.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Any calculations made under this article are rounded to the closest dollar.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				An employee's remuneration must not be changed unless such a change is in compliance with the provisions of the Agreement or has been agreed upon between the parties.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				Increases for employees whose work schedule is other than thirty-five (35) hours per week are calculated in relation to the number of hours worked over the one thousand eight hundred and twenty (1,820) regular hours of work that represent one (1) full-time equivalent (FTE).
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				An employee's annual salary is increased by two (2) adjustments :
			</paragraph-numbered>
			<list type="Dash">
				
				<item langue="en">
					An economic increase;
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					A progress-through-the-ranks increase (if employee has not reached the maximum salary for their salary scale).
				</item>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				An employee who has not yet completed their probationary period by the date for salary adjustments does not receive the progress-through-the-ranks (PTR) increase. Once an employee successfully completes his probationary period, he is granted a salary adjustment for PTR.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				When an employee's salary surpasses the maximum of the salary grade, the salary is referred to as "red circled." This employee receives only half of the economic increase. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				With respect to salary adjustments for University employees who are members of the bargaining unit, including retired employees, the adjustments made on May 1, 2007; May 1, 2008; May 1, 2009; and May 1, 2010, are as follows, in chronological order: 3%, 3%, 2.4% and 2.2%.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				On May 1, 2007, a 3% adjustment of salary scales for all pay grades; this is the first step for the calculation of salary increases but does not affect individual salaries; the second step is a maximum 3% salary adjustment for individuals, up to the new maximum for the pay grade and the indexed PTR adjustment. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				For employees whose salaries are higher than the maximum for their new salary scale: a maximum salary adjustment of 1.5%.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				On May 1, 2008, a 3% adjustment of salary scales for all pay grades; this is the first step for the calculation of salary increases bus does not affect individual salaries; the second step is a maximum 3% salary adjustment for individuals, up to the new maximum for the pay grade and the indexed PTR adjustment. 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				For employees whose salaries are higher than the maximum for their new salary scale: a maximum salary adjustment of 1.5%.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				On May 1, 2009, a 2.4% adjustment of salary scales; this is the first step for the calculation of salary increases but does not affect individual salaries; the second step is a maximum 2.4% salary adjustment for individuals, up to the new maximum for the pay grade and the indexed PTR adjustment.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				For employees whose salaries are higher than the maximum for their new salary scale: maximum salary adjustment of 1.2%.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				On May 1, 2010, a 2.2% adjustment of salary scales for all pay grades; this is the first step for the calculation of salary increases but does not affect individual salaries; the second step is a maximum 2.2% salary adjustment for individual salaries, up to the new maximum for the pay grade and the indexed PTR adjustment.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				For employees whose salaries are higher than the maximum for their new salary scale: a maximum salary adjustment of 1.1%.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				<strong>
					Progress through the ranks (PTR)
				</strong>
				: 
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Employees not at the maximum for their scale are given a progress-through-the-ranks adjustment in their pay grade provided they have worked the entire fiscal year prior to May 1. For employees who have not worked the entire fiscal year prior to May 1 or who were on leave without pay during this period, the PTR is calculated on a prorated basis according to the number of months worked during the 12-month period prior to May 1. 
			</paragraph>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<article id="article-47">
		
		<title langue="en">
			TERM OF AGREEMENT
		</title>
		<sub-article>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				This Collective Agreement comes into effect upon ratification by the parties and remains in force until April 30, 2011.
			</paragraph-numbered>
			
			<paragraph-numbered langue="en">
				The provisions of the Agreement, all appendixes and letters of agreement continue to apply until the signing of the next collective agreement or until one of the parties exercises its right to strike or lockout.
			</paragraph-numbered>
		</sub-article>
	</article>
	<signature>
		
		<paragraph langue="en">
			IN WITNESS WHEREOF, the Parties have set their hands in the City of Ottawa, on the 22nd day of February, 2011.
		</paragraph>
		
		<paragraph langue="en">
			L'Institut professionnel de la fonction publique du Canada (IPFPC). The Professional Institute of the Public Service of Canada (PIPSC)
		</paragraph>
		
		<person langue="en">
			Gary Corbett Président et président-directeur général President and CEO
		</person>
		
		<person langue="en">
			André Lortie Négociateur Negociator
		</person>
		
		<person langue="en">
			Pierre Lalonde Président (PTIUO) President (IPTUO)
		</person>
		
		<person langue="en">
			Marc Fortier Vice-président (PTIUO) Vice-president (IPTUO)
		</person>
		
		<person langue="en">
			André Dault Secrétaire (PTIUO) Secretary (IPTUO)
		</person>
		
		<person langue="en">
			Charles Wendt Membre (PTIUO) Member (IPTUO)
		</person>
		
	</signature>
	<appendix>
		
		<title langue="en">
			SENIORITY LIST
		</title>
		<sub-appendix>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
			</paragraph>
		</sub-appendix>
		<leaveblank>
		</leaveblank>
		<leaveblank>
		</leaveblank>
		<leaveblank>
		</leaveblank>
		<leaveblank>
		</leaveblank>
		<leaveblank>
		</leaveblank>
	</appendix>
	<appendix>
		
		<title langue="en">
			SALARY SCALES
		</title>
		<sub-appendix>
			
			<table>
				<tableheading>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								Classe
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								PTS
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								%
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								Minimum ($)
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								Standard ($
							</strong>
							)
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								Maximum ($)
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								PDR (2 %)
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
				</tableheading>
				<tablebody>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							6
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							210 - 244
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							84
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							34 316
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							40 852
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							44 937
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							817
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							7
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							245 - 286
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							83
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							36 991
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							44 567
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							49 024
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							891
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							8
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							287 - 335
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							81
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							39 663
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							48 967
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							53 864
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							979
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							9
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							336 -399
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							43 746
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							54 682
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							60 150
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1094
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							10
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							400 - 459
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							48 882
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							61 103
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							67 213
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1222
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							11
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							460 - 540
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							54 950
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							68 687
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							75 556
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1374
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							12
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							541 - 634
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							61 856
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							77 320
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							85 052
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1546
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							13
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							635 - 745
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							69 625
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							87 031
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							95 734
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1741
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
				</tablebody>
			</table>
			<paragraph langue="en">
				<strong>
					SALARY SCALE 2007-2008 35 HOURS/WEEK
				</strong>
			</paragraph>
			<table>
				<tableheading>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								Grade
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								PTS
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								%
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								Minimum ($)
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								Standard ($
							</strong>
							)
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								Maximum ($)
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								PTR (2 %)
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
				</tableheading>
				<tablebody>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							6
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							210 - 244
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							84
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							34 316
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							40 852
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							44 937
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							817
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							7
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							245 - 286
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							83
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							36 991
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							44 567
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							49 024
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							891
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							8
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							287 - 335
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							81
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							39 663
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							48 967
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							53 864
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							979
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							9
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							336 -399
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							43 746
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							54 682
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							60 150
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1094
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							10
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							400 - 459
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							48 882
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							61 103
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							67 213
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1222
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							11
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							460 - 540
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							54 950
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							68 687
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							75 556
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1374
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							12
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							541 - 634
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							61 856
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							77 320
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							85 052
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1546
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							13
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							635 - 745
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							69 625
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							87 031
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							95 734
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1741
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
				</tablebody>
			</table>
			
			<table>
				<tableheading>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								Classe
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								PTS
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								%
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								Minimum ($)
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								Standard ($
							</strong>
							)
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								Maximum ($)
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								PDR (2 %)
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
				</tableheading>
				<tablebody>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							6
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							210 - 244
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							84
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							35 346
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							42 078
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							46 286
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							842
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							7
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							245 - 286
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							83
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							38 100
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							45 904
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							50 494
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							918
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							8
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							287 - 335
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							81
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							40 853
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							50436
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							55 480
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1009
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							9
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							336 -399
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							45 058
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							56 322
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							61 954
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1126
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							10
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							400 - 459
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							50 349
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							62 936
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							69 230
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1259
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							11
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							460 - 540
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							56 598
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							70 748
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							77 823
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1415
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							12
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							541 - 634
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							63 712
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							79 640
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							87 604
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1593
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							13
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							635 - 745
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							71 714
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							89 642
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							98 606
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1793
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
				</tablebody>
			</table>
			<paragraph langue="en">
				<strong>
					SALARY SCALE 2008-2009 35 HOURS/WEEK
				</strong>
			</paragraph>
			<table>
				<tableheading>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								Grade
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								PTS
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								%
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								Minimum ($)
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								Standard ($
							</strong>
							)
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								Maximum ($)
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								PTR (2 %)
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
				</tableheading>
				<tablebody>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							6
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							210 - 244
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							84
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							35 346
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							42 078
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							46 286
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							842
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							7
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							245 - 286
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							83
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							38 100
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							45 904
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							50 494
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							918
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							8
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							287 - 335
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							81
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							40 853
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							50436
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							55 480
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1009
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							9
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							336 -399
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							45 058
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							56 322
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							61 954
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1126
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							10
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							400 - 459
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							50 349
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							62 936
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							69 230
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1259
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							11
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							460 - 540
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							56 598
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							70 748
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							77 823
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1415
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							12
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							541 - 634
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							63 712
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							79 640
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							87 604
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1593
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							13
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							635 - 745
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							71 714
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							89 642
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							98 606
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1793
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
				</tablebody>
			</table>
			
			<table>
				<tableheading>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								Classe
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								PTS
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								%
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								Minimum ($)
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								Standard ($
							</strong>
							)
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								Maximum ($)
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								PDR (2 %)
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
				</tableheading>
				<tablebody>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							6
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							210 - 244
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							84
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							36 194
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							43 088
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							47 397
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							862
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							7
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							245 - 286
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							83
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							39 015
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							47 006
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							51 707
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							940
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							8
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							287 - 335
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							81
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							41 833
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							51 646
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							56 811
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1033
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							9
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							336 -399
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							46 139
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							57 674
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							63 441
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1153
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							10
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							400 - 459
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							51 557
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							64 446
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							70 891
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1289
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							11
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							460 - 540
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							57 957
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							72 446
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							79 691
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1449
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							12
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							541 - 634
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							65 241
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							81 551
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							89 706
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1631
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							13
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							635 - 745
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							73 434
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							91 793
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							100 972
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1836
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
				</tablebody>
			</table>
			<paragraph langue="en">
				<strong>
					SALARY SCALE 2009-2010 35 HOURS/WEEK
				</strong>
			</paragraph>
			<table>
				<tableheading>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								Grade
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								PTS
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								%
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								Minimum ($)
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								Standard ($
							</strong>
							)
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								Maximum ($)
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								PTR (2 %)
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
				</tableheading>
				<tablebody>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							6
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							210 - 244
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							84
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							36 194
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							43 088
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							47 397
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							862
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							7
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							245 - 286
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							83
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							39 015
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							47 006
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							51 707
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							940
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							8
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							287 - 335
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							81
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							41 833
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							51 646
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							56 811
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1033
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							9
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							336 -399
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							46 139
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							57 674
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							63 441
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1153
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							10
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							400 - 459
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							51 557
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							64 446
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							70 891
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1289
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							11
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							460 - 540
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							57 957
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							72 446
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							79 691
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1449
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							12
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							541 - 634
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							65 241
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							81 551
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							89 706
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1631
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							13
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							635 - 745
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							73 434
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							91 793
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							100 972
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1836
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
				</tablebody>
			</table>
			
			<table>
				<tableheading>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								Classe
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								PTS
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								%
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								Minimum ($)
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								Standard ($
							</strong>
							)
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								Maximum ($)
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								PDR (2 %)
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
				</tableheading>
				<tablebody>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							6
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							210 - 244
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							84
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							36 990
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							44 036
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							48 440
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							881
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							7
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							245 - 286
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							83
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							39 873
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							48 040
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							52 844
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							961
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							8
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							287 - 335
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							81
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							42 753
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							52 782
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							58 060
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1056
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							9
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							336 -399
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							47 154
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							58 943
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							64 837
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1179
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							10
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							400 - 459
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							52 691
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							65 864
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							72 450
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1317
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							11
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							460 - 540
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							59 232
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							74 040
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							81 444
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1481
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							12
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							541 - 634
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							66 676
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							83 345
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							91 680
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1667
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							13
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							635 - 745
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							75 050
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							93 812
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							103 193
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1876
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
				</tablebody>
			</table>
			<paragraph langue="en">
				<strong>
					SALARY SCALE 2010-2011 35 HOURS/WEEK
				</strong>
			</paragraph>
			<table>
				<tableheading>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							Grade
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								PTS
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								%
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								Minimum ($)
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								Standard ($
							</strong>
							)
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								Maximum ($)
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							<strong>
								PTR (2 %)
							</strong>
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
				</tableheading>
				<tablebody>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							6
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							210 - 244
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							84
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							36 990
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							44 036
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							48 440
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							881
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							7
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							245 - 286
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							83
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							39 873
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							48 040
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							52 844
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							961
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							8
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							287 - 335
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							81
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							42 753
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							52 782
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							58 060
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1056
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							9
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							336 -399
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							47 154
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							58 943
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							64 837
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1179
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							10
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							400 - 459
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							52 691
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							65 864
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							72 450
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1317
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							11
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							460 - 540
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							59 232
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							74 040
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							81 444
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1481
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							12
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							541 - 634
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							66 676
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							83 345
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							91 680
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1667
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
					<tablerow>
						<tablecell>
							13
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							635 - 745
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							80
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							75 050
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							93 812
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							103 193
						</tablecell>
						<tablecell>
							1876
						</tablecell>
					</tablerow>
				</tablebody>
			</table>
		</sub-appendix>
	</appendix>
	<letter>
		
		<title-prefix langue="en">
			LETTER OF AGREEMENT between THE UNIVERSITY OF OTTAWA (the University) and THE PROFESSIONAL INSTITUTE OF THE PUBLIC SERVICE OF CANADA (the Institute)
		</title-prefix>
		
		<title langue="en">
			Access to the University regulations
		</title>
		<sub-letter>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				For the duration of the Agreement, employees remain covered by any benefits under University regulations that are not addressed in the Agreement and that are applicable to them. At most thirty (30) days before any amendment to these regulations, the University will consult the Institute, which will then have the opportunity to provide its comments. In the case of a contradiction conflict between a regulation and a provision of the Agreement, the Agreement is applicable and takes precedence.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				In witness whereof the parties have signed on March 3, 2010.
			</paragraph>
		</sub-letter>
		<signature>
			
			<person langue="en">
				Date
			</person>
			
			<person langue="en">
				Date
			</person>
		</signature>
	</letter>
	<letter>
		
		<title-prefix langue="en">
			LETTER OF AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE UNIVERSITY OF OTTAWA (THE UNIVERSITY) AND THE PROFESSIONAL INSTITUTE OF THE PUBLIC SERVICE OF CANADA (THE INSTITUTE)
		</title-prefix>
		
		<title langue="en">
			Institute representation on various University committees
		</title>
		<sub-letter>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Whereas the Institute has representation on various University committees;
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Whereas a representative can be appointed by the Institute to serve on these committees, the parties agree on the union representation as follows:
			</paragraph>
			<list type="Bullet">
				
				<item langue="en">
					"Employment equity advisory committee for support staff: 1 representative; 
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					"Sexual harassment committee or other committee that might follow: 1 representative.
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					"University occupational health and safety committee: 1 representative depending on the recommendation of the university committee in the context of the review of the committee structure currently under way and to be approved by the Ministry of Labour.
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					"The representatives asked to participate on these committees do not incur any loss in pay because of their participation.
				</item>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Signed on March 3, 2010
			</paragraph>
		</sub-letter>
		<signature>
			
			<person langue="en">
				André Lortie Pour l’Institut For the Institute
			</person>
		</signature>
	</letter>
	<letter>
		
		<title-prefix langue="en">
			LETTER OF AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE UNIVERSITY OF OTTAWA (THE UNIVERSITY) AND THE PROFESSIONAL INSTITUTE OF THE PUBLIC SERVICE OF CANADA
		</title-prefix>
		
		<title langue="en">
			Restoration of hours of work of certain employees
		</title>
		<sub-letter>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Whereas the University and the Institute are to negotiate and ratify an initial agreement establishing the number of hours of work per week as thirty-five (35) hours per week;
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Whereas certain employees in the Faculty of Medicine opted to participate in a project that increased the number of hours of work in a week, which is yet to be terminated, thus returning to the regular number of hours of work per week;
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				And whereas certain other employees also have hours of work that are higher than thirty-five (35) hours per week.
			</paragraph>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				The parties have agreed on the following:
			</paragraph>
			<list type="Numeric">
				
				<item langue="en">
					To restore the hours of work of employees who, upon ratification of the Agreement, have a work week of thirty-seven-and-a-half (37.5) hours established on a temporary basis, such as at the Faculty of Medicine, the hours of work are reduced by one-and-one-quarter (1.25) hours three months after the date of ratification of the Agreement by the two parties, for a period of six (6) months. An additional reduction of one-and-one-quarter (1.25) hours takes effect following this period. During this restoration period, the hours worked by these employees are paid at straight time. 
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					For other employees with hours higher than thirty-five (35) and whose initial contract of employment indicates an average of thirty-five (35) hours per week, the measures detailed in point 1 also apply.
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					For other employees with hours of work higher than thirty-five (35) and whose initial contract of employment indicates an average number of hours of work higher than thirty-five (35) hours and who still have more than thirty-five (35) hours per week, these employees must choose between retaining their higher number of hours and dropping down to thirty-five (35) hours as detailed in point 1, within sixty (60) days of ratification of the Agreement. This decision is irrevocable. If they maintain the higher number of hours, the normal hours for the position, i.e. thirty-five (35) hours per week, are applied when the position becomes vacant and before it is posted again. Within sixty (60) days following ratification, the parties must meet to draw up a list of the affected members.
				</item>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Signed on March 3, 2010
			</paragraph>
		</sub-letter>
		<signature>
			
			<person langue="en">
				André Lortie Pour l'Institut For the Institute
			</person>
		</signature>
	</letter>
	<letter>
		
		<title-prefix langue="en">
			LETTER OF AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE UNIVERISTY OF OTTAWA (THE UNIVERSITY) AND THE PROFESSIONAL INSTITUTE OF THE PUBLIC SERVICE OF CANADA
		</title-prefix>
		
		<title langue="en">
			Letter of agreement in respect of the regularization of duties performed by term employeeshired prior to january 25, 2007
		</title>
		<sub-letter>
			<list type="Numeric">
				
				<item langue="en">
					Within ninety (90) days after each party has ratified the Agreement, the University must prepare and send to the Institute a list of the term employees who were hired prior to January 25, 2007 and have performed the same duties ever since. 
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					The University thereupon launches a process to regularize the duties performed by the employees appearing on the aforementioned list.
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					Notwithstanding articles 18 "Jobs Posting and Appointments" and 21 "Regularization of New Duties", where the University decides to convert to a regular position any duties that have been performed for more than three (3) years by the same term employee hired prior to January 25, 2007, it staffs such positions in accordance with the rules in effect prior to the ratification of this Agreement.
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					A term employee who performs duties regularized under this letter of agreement and fails to obtain the position once it is regularized, are included, upon their request, on the call back list referred to in 20.2 a).
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					After agreement with the Institute and for the term specified in that agreement, duties not converted to regular positions on completion of the aforementioned regularization process may be extended.
				</item>
				
				<item langue="en">
					6. The parties may at any time and by mutual consent remove duties performed by an employee appearing on the list referred to in paragraph 1 of the aforementioned regularization process. The parties may also agree to postpone to a later date the implementation of the regularization process for those same duties.
				</item>
			</list>
			
			<paragraph langue="en">
				Signed at Ottawa, March 3, 2010
			</paragraph>
		</sub-letter>
		<signature>
			
			<person langue="en">
				André Lortie Pour l'Institut For the Institute
			</person>
		</signature>
	</letter>
</agreement>