<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?Fm Condition Comment Red SINGLE_UNDERLINE show?><?Fm Condition FM8_SYSTEM_HIDEELEMENT AsIs NO_OVERRIDE hide?><?Fm Condition FM8_TRACK_CHANGES_ADDED Forest%20Green SINGLE_UNDERLINE show?><?Fm Condition FM8_TRACK_CHANGES_DELETED Red STRIKETHROUGH show?><?Fm BoolCondExpr "" State 0?><?Fm AttrCondExpr langueFr (langue="fr-ca") Inactive?><?Fm TrackChange Off PreviewState PREVIEW_OFF_TRACK_CHANGE?><agreement Size="Small" Period="2010-2013">
    <article>
        
        <title langue="en">Definitions</title>
        <section>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">ACADEMIC SESSION: The Fall session (September to December), the Winter session
                (January to April), and the Spring-Summer session (May to August).</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">ACADEMIC YEAR: For the purposes of this agreement, the period from September 1 to
                August 31.</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">AGREEMENT: This Collective Agreement between the APTPUO and the Employer (University
                of Ottawa).</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">APTPUO: The Association of Part-Time Professors of the University of Ottawa, and any
                person(s) duly authorized to act on its behalf.</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">BARGAINING UNIT: The unit as defined in 2.1 of this Agreement.</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">BOARD: The Board of Governors of the University of Ottawa as provided for in the
                University of Ottawa Act, 1965.</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">CHAIRPERSON: The Chairperson of a Department or her/his designate or where there is
                no department a person designated by the dean.</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">DEAN: Dean or her/his designate.</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">DEPARTMENT AND ACADEMIC UNIT: 1. A department as duly constituted by the Senate and
                the Board; 2. any school or faculty which does not have departments; 3. the Official Languages and
                Bilingualism Institute; 4. any additional departments or similar units as may be duly constituted by the
                University.</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">EMPLOYEE: Part-time academic staff appointed to perform bargaining unit
                work.</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">EMPLOYER: The Board of Governors of the University of Ottawa as defined by the
                University of Ottawa Act, 1965, and any person(s) duly authorized to act on its behalf.</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">FULL-TIME: Full-time or pro rata full-time, being not less than 50% of a full
                workload.</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">MEMBER: A member of the bargaining unit.</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">PARTIES: The Association and the Employer, as defined in this Article. </paragraph>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">PART-TIME ACADEMIC STAFF REPRESENTATIVE: A member of the part-time academic staff who
                is elected to be a representative for the part-time academic staff at any level of the University
                governance.</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">PART-TIME ACADEMIC STAFF: a) REGULAR PART-TIME ACADEMIC STAFF: Individuals who are
                not registered as full-time graduate students at the University of Ottawa and who perform bargaining
                unit work. b) STUDENT PART-TIME ACADEMIC STAFF: Individuals who are registered as full-time graduate
                students at the University of Ottawa and who perform bargaining unit work.</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">SECTION HEAD: A person designated by the Dean, having responsibility for a section in
                a faculty without departments.</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">VISITING PROFESSOR: A recognized scholar or artist whose presence enhances the
                breadth or quality of the university's scholarly or teaching activities and who either holds a full-time
                continuing appointment or has established a career outside of the University of Ottawa or is retired
                from a professorial or comparable position.</paragraph>
        </section>
    </article>
    <article>
        
        <title langue="en">GENERAL PROVISIONS</title>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">BARGAINING UNIT</title>
            <section>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The bargaining unit includes all part-time academic staff employed by
                    the Employer in the City of Ottawa, Stormont-Dundas, Renfrew North, Prescott and Lanark
                    Counties.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Part-time academic staff is understood to mean all persons having full
                    or joint full responsibility for one or more courses and who are:</paragraph-numbered>
                <list Type="Alpha">
                    
                    <item langue="en">sessional lecturers;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">part-time language teachers;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">part-time applied music teachers;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">clinical instructors in Nursing and in other units of the Faculty of Health
                        Sciences;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">clinical instructors in Physiotherapy (subject to a separate letter of
                        understanding between the parties);</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">persons in essentially comparable positions as those listed above;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">full-time graduate students registered at the University of Ottawa.</item>
                </list>
                
                <title langue="en" prefixMark="y" prefixLineOnly="y">EXCLUSIONS</title>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">The parties agree that the following are excluded from the Bargaining Unit. </paragraph>
                <list Type="Alpha">
                    
                    <item langue="en">employees who exercise managerial functions or are employed in a confidential
                        capacity in matters relating to labour relations between the Employer and the APTPUO;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">all persons who otherwise hold the academic rank of lecturer, assistant, associate
                        or full professor or full-time language teacher at the University of Ottawa, including visiting
                        professors and those who have been seconded to the University;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">all those engaged in the practice of medicine or psychology in the course of
                        clinical teaching of medicine or psychology;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">all part-time academic staff engaged in the teaching of courses in the Faculty of
                        Law, Common Law Section and Civil Law Section;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en" prefixMark="y">all those involved in the teaching of non-credit courses, except </item>
                    <list Type="Roman">
                        
                        <item langue="en">courses in the Official Languages and Bilingualism Institute and QBA/PDP at
                            the Faculty of Education which are required for the completion of a degree program;</item>
                        
                        <item langue="en">on an exceptional basis and for historical reasons, all those employees having
                            a contract for non-credit courses between the period of May 1, 2010 and April 30, 2011, in
                            the QBA/PDP and OLBI will be deemed to be included in the bargaining unit for the purposes
                            of the collective agreement.</item>
                        
                        <item langue="en">in order to maintain his/her status as a bargaining unit member, the member
                            will have to apply and receive a contract once per twenty-four (24) months.</item>
                    </list>
                    
                    <item langue="en">any person employed by the Employer as a support staff member who exercises
                        managerial functions or acts in a confidential capacity in matters relating to labour relations
                        with part-time academic staff;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">persons employed by the Employer whose regular job description includes teaching
                        duties related to his or her other duties.</item>
                </list>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">The parties further agree that the following positions are excluded because the
                    incumbents exercise managerial functions or are employed in a confidential capacity in matters
                    relating to labour relations with part-time academic staff:</paragraph>
                <list Type="Alpha">
                    
                    <item langue="en">the President </item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">the Vice-Presidents </item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">the Associate Vice-Presidents </item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">the Vice-President, Governance</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">the Deans </item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">the Administrative Officers of Academic Units or Faculties</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">the Director of the Counselling and Personal Development Service </item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">the University Librarian </item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">members of the Board of Governors or Joint Committee </item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">the Research Officers of Institutional Research</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">the Directors of Administrative and Academic Units. </item>
                </list>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">The list shall be reviewed on October 30, February 28 and June 30 of every year,
                    and the list shall be forwarded to the Association.</paragraph>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">PURPOSE OF THIS AGREEMENT</title>
            <section>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The general purpose of this Agreement is to establish an orderly
                    collective bargaining relationship between the Employer and the members of APTPUO or between the
                    Employer and the APTPUO, to ensure the peaceful settlement of disputes, and to set forth an
                    agreement covering rates of pay and other working conditions which shall be exclusive and shall
                    supersede all other agreements between the Employer and the employees represented by the
                    Association.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The parties recognize that it is in their mutual interest to promote and
                    to enhance the working relations between the Employer and the APTPUO and its members on the
                    principles of mutual respect and cooperation and to foster a climate of freedom and responsibility
                    appropriate for the promotion of excellence in the University.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The APTPUO agrees to collaborate with the Employer in promoting and
                    supporting the bilingual nature of the University.</paragraph-numbered>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">ABSENCE OF DISCRIMINATION AND/OR HARASSMENT</title>
            <section>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Subject to the particular provisions set out in section 2.3.2 and 2.4,
                    the parties agree that no member of the bargaining unit shall be subjected to discrimination,
                    interference, hindrance, restriction or harassment with regard to salary, employee benefits,
                    appointment of any type within the University, leave, dismissal or layoff, disciplinary measures,
                    any other term or condition of employment or student status (except as provided for in this
                    Agreement) based on her/his age, race, beliefs, colour, citizenship or permanent resident status,
                    national or ethnic origin, language, political or religious beliefs or affiliations, sex, sexual
                    orientation, marital status, family ties, a handicap, a criminal record or a record of offences,
                    her/his membership in the APTPUO and participation in its legal activities or membership in the
                    bargaining unit, or her/his withdrawal from the APTPUO.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">Moreover, all members of the bargaining unit may resort to any other
                    anti-discriminatory provision of any applicable provincial law.</paragraph>
            </section>
            <section>
                
                <title langue="en">LANGUAGE REQUIREMENTS </title>
                <section>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Where a member is required to have or to attain a specified level of
                        competence in French and/or English, such requirement shall be deemed
                        non-discriminatory.</paragraph-numbered>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">An applicant for an appointment shall be expected to have active
                        knowledge of either English or French according to the language in which the work will be
                        carried out. The language(s) of instruction must be specified in the
                        posting.</paragraph-numbered>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The Employer may, in addition, require an applicant to have an
                        active or passive knowledge of the other official language if there is a need. It is understood
                        that this requirement shall be specified in the posting.</paragraph-numbered>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en"> For the purpose of this Agreement, active knowledge of the language
                        means a level of competence which is adequate for the purposes of teaching, and passive
                        knowledge means the ability to grasp the essential content of oral or written communication
                        addressed to the employee in the course of his/her employment at the University of
                        Ottawa.</paragraph-numbered>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">If a course was last given by a member of the bargaining unit and if
                        the Employer intends to upgrade the language requirements in the posting while maintaining the
                        same course code, the Employer shall so advise the APTPUO as soon as possible after the decision
                        to upgrade the requirements.</paragraph-numbered>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The Employer agrees to advise the Union and any unsuccessful
                        applicant who is a member of the APTPUO, if his/her knowledge of either official language has
                        been the determining factor.</paragraph-numbered>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Members are eligible for the language courses offered to members of
                        staff of the University under the conditions of the Letter of Understanding in Appendix I –
                        2).</paragraph-numbered>
                </section>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">FURTHER PROVISIONS</title>
            <section>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Where a member's handicap interferes with the fulfilment of her/his
                    workload duties, any related measures taken by the Employer which affect the member's working
                    conditions and terms of employment shall be deemed non-discriminatory, it being understood that the
                    Employer shall not take any such measures unless:</paragraph-numbered>
                <list Type="Alpha">
                    
                    <item langue="en">they are required in light of the member's inability to meet satisfactorily the
                        objective requirements of her/his employment; and</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">the Employer has, previous to taking any such measures, taken all reasonable steps
                        which could enable the handicapped member to continue performing her/his workload duties.</item>
                </list>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Where a criminal record or a record of offenses is demonstrably
                    detrimental to a member's suitability for her/his position, any appropriate measures taken by the
                    Employer - which affect the member's working conditions and terms of employment - shall be deemed
                    non-discriminatory.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The application of any University insurance contract or policy regarding
                    eligibility to benefits for persons aged 65 or more shall be deemed
                    non-discriminatory.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">For the purposes of this article, reference to "handicap" shall mean a
                    reference to "physical or mental handicap, illness or incapacity, including addictive illness or
                    alcoholism".</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The Employer shall ensure that no University of Ottawa student who is
                    (or has been) a member of the bargaining unit shall be penalized in her/his student status for the
                    exercise of any of her/his rights under this Agreement or by reason of her/his membership or
                    non-membership or lawful activity in the APTPUO except that nothing in this section shall be
                    construed so as to diminish or eliminate any obligation resulting from her/his student
                    status.</paragraph-numbered>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">ACADEMIC FREEDOM</title>
            <section>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The parties agree neither to infringe nor abridge the academic freedom
                    of the members. Academic freedom is the right of reasonable exercise of civil liberties and
                    responsibilities in an academic setting. As such it protects each member's freedom to disseminate
                    her/his opinion both inside and outside the classroom, to practice her/his profession as teacher and
                    scholar, to carry out such scholarly and teaching activities as she/he believes will contribute to
                    and disseminate knowledge, to express and disseminate the results of her/his scholarly activities in
                    a reasonable manner, and to select, acquire, disseminate and use documents in the exercise of
                    her/his professional responsibilities, without interference from the Employer, its agents, or any
                    outside bodies. All the above-mentioned activities are to be conducted with due and proper regard
                    for the academic freedom of others and without contravening the provisions of this agreement.
                    Academic freedom does not require neutrality on the part of the member, but rather makes commitment
                    possible. However, academic freedom does not confer legal immunity, nor does it diminish the
                    obligations of members to meet their duties and responsibilities.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The parties agree that no censorship based on moral, religious, or
                    political values shall be exercised or allowed against any material which a member desires to be
                    placed in the library collections of the University of Ottawa.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Notwithstanding the provisions of paragraphs 2.4.1 and 2.4.2 the
                    Employer reserves the right to specify what textbooks are to be used in order to conform to
                    published course descriptions, to match parallel sections of a course, to meet prerequisites
                    required for other courses or to meet academic objectives of the academic unit.</paragraph-numbered>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">ETHICAL BEHAVIOUR</title>
            <section>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">In their actions affecting students, colleagues, or other scholars, as
                    well as any employees of the Employer, members of the bargaining unit and representatives of the
                    Employer shall observe commonly accepted norms of fairness and ethical
                    behaviour.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The Labour-Management Committee is charged with developing further
                    clarification of 2.6.1 to become part of this agreement if and when such texts are ratified by the
                    parties.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <title langue="en">SEXUAL HARASSMENT</title>
                <section>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The Employer and the APTPUO agree to take all necessary steps to
                        avoid all forms of sexual harassment with respect to any individual in any matter concerning the
                        application of the provisions of this Agreement or with respect to any applicant seeking to
                        become an employee insofar as the provisions of the Agreement relate to the application
                        process.</paragraph-numbered>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">For the purpose of this Agreement, the parties agree that sexual
                        harassment shall be defined as: a) unwanted sexual attention from a person who knows or ought
                        reasonably to know that such attention is unwanted, or b) implied or expressed promise of reward
                        for complying with a sexually oriented request, or c) implied or expressed threat of reprisal or
                        actual reprisal for refusal to comply with a sexually oriented request, or d) sexually oriented
                        remarks and behaviour which may be reasonably perceived to create a negative psychological and
                        emotional environment for work and study.</paragraph-numbered>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The parties agree that any allegations of sexual harassment shall be
                        dealt with in a confidential manner and in accordance with University
                        policy.</paragraph-numbered>
                </section>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">POSTING OF REGULAR FULL-TIME POSITIONS</title>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">Each department shall advise its part-time academic staff of its intention to fill a
                vacant regular full-time position by posting a copy of a notice to that effect on the bulletin board
                normally used for APTPUO matters in the department and on the department’s website. An electronic copy
                of the notice shall be sent to the APTPUO offices. Any APTPUO member qualified for the advertised
                position can apply and that member's application will be given the same consideration as all other
                applications.</paragraph>
        </section>
    </article>
    <article>
        
        <title langue="en">LABOUR-MANAGEMENT RELATIONS</title>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">APTPUO REPRESENTATION AND ACTIVITIES</title>
            <section>
                
                <title langue="en">RECOGNITION</title>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">The Employer recognizes the APTPUO as the sole bargaining agent for the members
                    of the bargaining unit as defined in this Agreement. The bargaining unit as defined in this
                    Agreement shall be amended only by mutual agreement of the parties. The Employer agrees that no
                    employee or group of employees shall undertake to represent the APTPUO to the Employer without
                    proper authorization of the APTPUO. In order for this to be carried out, the APTPUO shall provide
                    the Employer in writing with the names and position titles of its Officers and names of its elected
                    Board members. The Employer shall be obligated to recognize the status of these persons listed from
                    the date of such notice. Likewise at the beginning of each academic year, the Employer shall supply
                    the APTPUO with a list of its designated authorities with whom the APTPUO may be required to
                    transact business as well as a list of Employer representatives at the various administrative and
                    academic levels. The Employer shall inform the APTPUO of all subsequent changes to the
                    list.</paragraph>
                
                <title langue="en">ASSOCIATION ACTIVITIES </title>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">The Employer recognizes the right of every member to participate in any lawful
                    activities of the APTPUO, and it shall not interfere with this right, it being understood that
                    regular scheduled duties shall not be affected by such activities.</paragraph>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">APTPUO REPRESENTATION AND ACTIVITIES</title>
            <section>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">All inherent and common law management functions and prerogatives which
                    the Employer has not expressly modified or restricted by a specific provision of this Agreement are
                    retained and vested exclusively in the Employer.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Without limiting the generality of the above, these rights include, but
                    are not limited to, the right:</paragraph-numbered>
                <list Type="Numeric">
                    
                    <item langue="en">to hire, classify, direct, retire, transfer, lay off or recall and to discharge,
                        reprimand, suspend or otherwise discipline employees for just cause;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">to determine the requirements of a job and the standards of the work to be
                        performed;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">to expand, reduce, alter, combine, transfer or cease any job, department,
                        operation or service;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">to determine the size and composition of the work force;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">to make or change rules, policies and practices, provided that such rules,
                        policies and practices shall not be inconsistent with the terms of this Agreement;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">to maintain order and efficiency and otherwise generally manage the University,
                        direct the work force and establish terms and conditions of employment not in conflict with the
                        provisions of this Agreement.</item>
                </list>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">In exercising its rights and in conducting its employment relations, the
                    Employer shall act reasonably, non-discriminatorily and in good faith.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <title langue="en">INFORMATION RELATING TO MANAGEMENT RIGHTS </title>
                <section>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The Employer agrees to provide the APTPUO, upon written request,
                        with timely information on existing rules, policies and practices affecting the employment of
                        bargaining unit members or the working conditions between the Employer and the
                        members.</paragraph-numbered>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The Employer further agrees to provide the APTPUO through the
                        Labour-Management Committee with timely information on any proposed substantial changes in such
                        rules, policies and practices, as well as the motives for such changes or responses to questions
                        raised by the APTPUO.</paragraph-numbered>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">After the Employer has advised the APTPUO according to article
                        3.2.4.2, the APTPUO shall have thirty (30) days to comment on such changes before they are
                        implemented, except where such implementation must proceed more rapidly, in which case reasons
                        will be given. Such comments may include alternative proposals to improve the situation. The
                        thirty-day period may be extended if the Labour-Management Committee so
                        agrees.</paragraph-numbered>
                </section>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">CORRESPONDENCE</title>
            <section>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">All correspondence between the parties arising out of or incidental to
                    this Agreement, except where otherwise expressly provided, shall pass between the President (or
                    designate) APTPUO and the management of Academic Labour Relations or designate. </paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Where the Agreement specifies notice in writing or requires the exchange
                    of correspondence, the internal post system of the University shall normally be deemed an acceptable
                    means of communication. Such notices or correspondence may be sent by fax and electronic mail
                    transmission provided the original is also sent through the University's internal postage system
                    without undue delay.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">For the purposes of the present collective agreement, and in the absence
                    of proof to the contrary, receipt of any notice or other correspondence shall be deemed to have
                    occurred five (5) working days after the date of expedition.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Where a member is on leave in accordance with the current collective
                    agreement, the Employer shall forward any notice or other documentation related to the member’s
                    status as part-time professor to her/his last known address.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en"/>
                <list Type="Alpha">
                    
                    <item langue="en">A copy of all correspondence from the Employer or its representative(s) to any
                        bargaining unit member, relating to appointments or the terms and conditions of appointment
                        shall be forwarded to the APTPUO except for letters of appointment that comply with all key
                        conditions of the posting. </item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">An APTPUO representative may consult during regular hours any documents held by a
                        department concerning an APTPUO member, after giving reasonable notice and upon presentation of
                        written consent of the member, or upon presenting an order from an arbitrator or a court having
                        jurisdiction.</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">Upon making an appointment twenty-four (24) hours in advance with the Human
                        Resources Service, any employee can consult her/his file at the department in the presence of an
                        Human Resources Service representative during regular office hours. The employee can also be
                        accompanied by a union representative if so desired and as long as she/he advises the Human
                        Resources Service accordingly when making the appointment.</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">The employee or the union can obtain a copy of any document in the employee's
                        personal file by paying the fee set out in the Ontario Freedom of Information and Protection of
                        Privacy Act.</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">The University cannot disclose an employee's personal information, except when
                        complying with the provisions of 3.3.5 b) and Appendix H.</item>
                </list>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">LABOUR-MANAGEMENT COMMITTEE</title>
            <section>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The APTPUO and the Employer acknowledge the mutual benefits to be
                    derived from joint consultation and agree to a Labour-Management Committee consisting of four
                    representatives from each party. The APTPUO representatives shall be the President and three other
                    named persons among the members of the Board of Directors. The Committee shall function in an
                    advisory capacity only, making recommendations to the APTPUO and/or the Employer with respect to its
                    discussions and conclusions concerning the working relations between the Employer and the APTPUO or
                    its members. The Committee shall not have the power to add to or to modify the terms of this
                    Agreement.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Recommendations from the Labour-Management Committee are made to the
                    Employer and to the APTPUO. If implemented the methodology shall be either:</paragraph-numbered>
                <list Type="Alpha">
                    
                    <item langue="en">by an Employer approved policy or</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">by corollary agreement between the parties.</item>
                </list>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Notwithstanding paragraph 3.4.2, neither the Employer nor the APTPUO
                    shall act in a manner contrary to the recommendations of the Committee without having first informed
                    the Committee in writing that it intends to do so.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">A representative of each party shall be designated as a joint
                    chairperson and the two persons shall alternate in presiding over meetings. The chair shall prepare
                    the minutes of the meeting.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">In addition to its advisory capacity in matters relating to this
                    agreement, the Labour-Management Committee shall function as a forum in which the Employer shall
                    advise the APTPUO of anticipated trends or policy changes which may have a major impact on the
                    bargaining unit or respond to APTPUO questions.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en" prefixMark="y">The Committee will meet every six (6) weeks with the
                    first meeting of the year being held in September and the last in June. No later than five (5)
                    working days before the meeting, each party will advise the other of the proposed items for the
                    agenda for the meeting in order to allow for sufficient preparation time. Any additional items would
                    be subject to the approval of both parties.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">Of these meetings mentioned above, a meeting in each of the Fall, Winter and the
                    Spring sessions will be set aside for a meeting with the Vice-President, Academic, in order to
                    discuss issues of common interest. Each party will advise the other of the proposed items for the
                    agenda for the meeting at least five (5) working days in advance.</paragraph>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">HEALTH AND SAFETY</title>
            <section>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The Employer acknowledges its responsibility to provide a safe and
                    healthy working environment, and to provide any facilities, supplies and services, and to follow any
                    procedures required by the Occupational Health and Safety Act to protect the health, safety, and
                    security of employees as they carry out their responsibilities of employment on the Employer's
                    premises. The parties agree that the Employer shall provide, and the member shall make use of,
                    protective equipment whenever such equipment is required by the Act or the regulations pertaining to
                    the Act for the safe performance of the members' responsibilities of
                    employment.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">No employee shall be required to act, nor shall she/he act in a manner
                    which constitutes a health and safety hazard.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The Employer will distribute to APTPUO members all Health and Safety
                    notices and information distributed to full-time staff. The Labour-Management Committee will develop
                    a fact sheet dealing with Health and Safety measures and information on responses to emergency
                    situations for distribution to APTPUO members.</paragraph-numbered>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">TRANSLATION AND DISPERSAL OF THE AGREEMENT</title>
            <section>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The Employer agrees to translate each clause of this agreement from the
                    language in which the clause was negotiated at the bargaining table into the other official language
                    of Canada at the time of their ratification at the negotiation table. Within three months of the
                    ratification of the new agreement, the Employer shall provide a complete translation to the APTPUO
                    for approval to ensure that the translation is satisfactory to both parties.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">The back cover (outside) of the Collective Agreement shall be an information
                    page, printed on coloured paper. Its contents shall be prepared by APTPUO on matters related to the
                    Collective Agreement it wishes to bring to the membership’s attention.</paragraph>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Within thirty (30) days of the approval of the translation of this
                    Agreement by the parties, the Employer shall make available on line on its website an electronic
                    copy of the collective agreement that has been signed and ratified by the parties. The Employer
                    shall also inform all APTPUO members of the availability of an electronic copy of the collective
                    agreement found on the Human Resources website. The Employer shall provide at no charge 100 copies
                    of this Agreement to the Association; the Association will bear the cost of any additional copies it
                    requests.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">As well, the Employer will add a hyperlink from the Human Resources website to
                    the APTPUO website, so that members can read the back page of the agreement, which contains
                    information provided by the Association.</paragraph>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">APTPUO MEMBERSHIP</title>
            <section>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Except as provided for in 3.7.2 and 3.7.3, every employee in the
                    bargaining unit shall be a member of the APTPUO.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Any member of the bargaining unit who objects to membership in the
                    APTPUO, in its role as a trade union, on clearly expressed conscientious or religious grounds may
                    withdraw from the APTPUO after having delivered in writing her/his reason(s) to the President of the
                    APTPUO. The APTPUO shall inform the Employer of all membership withdrawals. For the purpose of
                    clarity, it is understood that the employees shall enjoy the rights and the benefits as provided for
                    under this Agreement.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Any employee excluded under section 2.1 who performs part-time teaching
                    for additional remuneration shall make payments in accordance with section 3.8.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Every employee described in 3.7.2 shall be subject to section
                    3.8.</paragraph-numbered>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">DUES CHECK-OFF</title>
            <section>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Each month, the Employer shall deduct from the salary (if any) of each
                    member of the bargaining unit a sum equal to the monthly dues and/or assessments as certified in
                    writing to the Employer by the Treasurer of the APTPUO.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">In addition, the Employer agrees to deduct equivalent monthly dues
                    and/or assessments from the salary of any employee as described in 3.7.2 and 3.7.3. Except in the
                    case of withdrawal on conscientious grounds, the employee may direct the APTPUO to contribute
                    his/her deductions to the APTPUO Student Awards Fund, which shall be administered in trust by the
                    Employer. The APTPUO and the Employer will be jointly responsible for the disbursement of the Fund
                    to University of Ottawa students.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The Employer shall remit the amount so deducted to the Treasurer of the
                    APTPUO at the APTPUO's address by the end of the month in which deductions are
                    made.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The APTPUO shall indemnify and save the Employer harmless from any and
                    all claims which may be made against it by an employee or employees for wrongful amounts deducted
                    resulting from the APTPUO's incorrect instructions or lack of instructions.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The Employer shall allow the APTPUO to audit the contracts of any
                    employees where the APTPUO has reason to believe that the dues have not been adequately
                    deducted.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Subject to paragraph 3.8.2, the Employer shall pay to the APTPUO the
                    equivalent amount which was not deducted from the employee's salary as a result of the Employer's
                    mistake, if such mistake persists for more than fifteen (15) days following notification by the
                    APTPUO.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">If the Employer remits to the APTPUO dues and/or assessments from the
                    salary of any employee who is not required to pay the dues, the Employer shall inform the APTPUO of
                    this error and the APTPUO shall reimburse the amount so received.</paragraph-numbered>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">HOLIDAYS</title>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">No employee shall be required to work on any of the following holidays: New Year's
                Day, Family Day, Good Friday, Easter Monday, Victoria Day, Canada Day, Civic Holiday, Labour Day,
                Thanksgiving Day, Christmas Day, Boxing Day, any other statutory holiday, and any holiday declared by
                the President of the University.</paragraph>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">BULLETIN BOARDS</title>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">The Employer agrees that the APTPUO is entitled to a reasonable amount of space on
                existing bulletin boards for official APTPUO notices in all academic units.</paragraph>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">MAIL SERVICE</title>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">It is acknowledged that the APTPUO may make use of the University's internal post
                services for the purpose of communication with its members and the Employer. Circular letters,
                memoranda, and general correspondence from the APTPUO to its members will be delivered to the members
                through the member's department. Where individual mailboxes for APTPUO members do not exist,
                chairpersons will make appropriate arrangements for such mail to be delivered. APTPUO shall cover the
                costs of all its correspondence to members residing outside the Ottawa area and teaching in off-campus
                centres. The APTPUO may use the University’s external postal services, and the Association agrees to
                reimburse to the University the postal fees for such service.</paragraph>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">SERVICES AND FACILITIES</title>
            <section>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The parties acknowledge that the APTPUO is presently occupying premises
                    located at 85 University Private, Room 124, and the Employer undertakes to continue to rent such
                    space, or similar centrally located space in the event that the present location is unavailable, to
                    the APTPUO up to a maximum of 600 sq. ft. at the maintenance rate determined annually by the
                    Employer in accordance with working practices.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">On request, the Employer agrees to provide two parking spaces close to
                    the APTPUO office on a yearly basis. The APTPUO will pay the appropriate parking
                    fee.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The Employer shall provide the APTPUO with suitable meeting rooms as
                    required for Union business, free of charge, provided reasonable notice is given and space is
                    available.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The APTPUO shall have access to the following services of the University
                    of Ottawa at standard rates for internal users, subject to cost recovery: telephones, mail services,
                    audiovisual and reprographic services, computing and communication services, translation services,
                    material management services, archives and library services.</paragraph-numbered>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en" prefixLineOnly="y">SERVICE ON THE EXECUTIVE OR OTHER COMMITTEES</title>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">From September 1, 2010, to September 1, 2012, the Employer will pay to the APTPUO a
                sum equal to the basic rate for seven (7) 3-credit courses to be used to compensate members for
                executive, bargaining committee, and other committees or the expenses thereof.</paragraph>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <paragraph-numbered langue="en" prefixMark="y">Once a month, the Employer shall provide the APTPUO with an
                electronic report which includes information regarding their members such as: names, employee numbers,
                departments, faculties, positions, home mailing address, telephone numbers, uOttawa email address,
                monthly dues deducted and summary of same. The parties will agree within a period of ninety (90) days
                following the ratification by both parties to the exact information and data to be contained in the
                report. The bargaining agent shall save the Employer harmless in the event any bargaining unit member
                files a complaint or grievance or asserts a cause of action against the Employer for either the
                implementation or administration of this report.</paragraph-numbered>
        </section>
    </article>
    <article>
        
        <title langue="en">COMPLAINTS, GRIEVANCE AND ARBITRATION PROCEDURE</title>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">DEFINITION OF A GRIEVANCE</title>
            <section>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">A grievance shall be defined as any difference between the parties to
                    this Agreement arising out of the interpretation, application, administration, or alleged violation
                    of this Agreement.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <title langue="en">GROUP GRIEVANCE</title>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">A group grievance, resulting from a consolidation of similar individual
                    grievances seeking a common redress, may be initiated by the APTPUO at step two (4.3.2).</paragraph>
                
                <title langue="en">POLICY GRIEVANCE</title>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">A policy grievance involves a question of general application or interpretation
                    of this Agreement and is initiated by the APTPUO at step three (4.4).</paragraph>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">APTPUO AND MEMBERS’ RIGHTS</title>
            <section>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The Employer acknowledges the rights and duties of the APTPUO Officers
                    and/or designates to assist employees in preparing and presenting a grievance and to accompany a
                    member if she/he wishes at any meeting in step one of the grievance procedure. </paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The Employer agrees to cooperate with the APTPUO Officers and/or the
                    APTPUO in providing relevant information concerning a grievance or a potential
                    grievance.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The parties agree that every grievance shall be treated in a
                    confidential manner up to arbitration.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">It is understood that no member can conclude with the Employer or its
                    representative(s), and vice-versa, any agreement which may contravene this Agreement without the
                    consent in writing of the APTPUO.</paragraph-numbered>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">GRIEVANCE PROCEDURE</title>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">It is understood that the management of Academic Labour Relations or designate must
                receive a copy of any letter, document or grievance forwarded by the Association to a supervisor,
                chairperson of an academic unit or dean and faculty.</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">The parties agree to make reasonable efforts to encourage the informal, amicable, and
                prompt resolution of complaints or grievances arising from the administration, interpretation or
                application of this Agreement. Except when otherwise specified by an arbitrator, compensation required
                by an arbitration ruling must be awarded to the member in question without undue delay, unless the
                Employer notifies the APTPUO that it intends to apply for a judicial review. The parties agree that the
                arbitrator is to be kept aware of any issue linked to the operative part of the grievance and/or to its
                application.</paragraph>
            <section>
                
                <title langue="en">STEP ONE: INFORMATION </title>
                <section>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">If the member has a complaint that may lead to a grievance, the
                        member shall advise the chairperson in writing of the subject matter of the complaint no later
                        than ten (10) working days after the member became aware, or reasonably ought to have been
                        aware, of the occurrence of the circumstance giving rise to the complaint, if the matter
                        concerns any of the provisions of article 5; in all other cases, the member must advise the
                        chairperson in writing within fifteen (15) working days. A copy of such notice shall be
                        forwarded to the dean and the Association.</paragraph-numbered>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The chairperson shall arrange an information meeting with the member
                        within five (5) working days of receipt of the notice as specified in 4.3.1.1 and shall advise
                        the member of the right to be accompanied and/or represented by an APTPUO Officer or his/her
                        delegate. The chairperson may also be accompanied by a representative from the management of
                        Academic Labour Relations. In any event, the chairperson shall forward her/his response in
                        writing to the member, to the APTPUO, and to the dean within five (5) working days of the
                        meeting.</paragraph-numbered>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">No complaint can proceed beyond Step 1 unless assumed as a grievance
                        by the APTPUO.</paragraph-numbered>
                </section>
                <section/>
                
                <title langue="en">STEP TWO: GRIEVANCE</title>
                <section>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">If the complaint is not resolved at step one or if step 1 does not
                        apply, the Association shall forward to the dean a formal notice of grievance setting out the
                        details of the grievance, a statement of the matter in dispute, the provisions of this Agreement
                        that allegedly have been violated and the relief sought. Such notice shall be signed by the
                        Association and shall be delivered within fifteen (15) working days of receipt of the
                        chairperson's response. In the case of a group grievance which is initiated at step 2, the
                        Association's notice shall be delivered within fifteen (15) working days after the Association
                        became aware or reasonably ought to have been aware of the occurrence of the circumstance giving
                        rise to the grievance.</paragraph-numbered>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The dean or her/his designate shall convene a meeting within ten
                        (10) working days of receipt of the formal notice of grievance and shall forward her/his
                        decision in writing to the APTPUO within five (5) working days of the
                        meeting.</paragraph-numbered>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">At this stage, the APTPUO can file a formal request for arbitration,
                        according to the terms of 4.4.1. In such cases, the APTPUO must cover all arbitration
                        cancellation fees if ever the grievance is withdrawn or resolved.</paragraph-numbered>
                </section>
            </section>
            <section>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">APTPUO shall be informed of the representative’s name from Academic
                    Labour Relations, so that the President or his or her delegate may also attend.</paragraph-numbered>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">STEP 3: REFERRAL TO ARBITRATION</title>
            <section>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">If the grievance is not settled at step two, the APTPUO may forward to
                    the management of Academic Labour Relations, a written request for arbitration signed by the
                    Grievance Officer and/or her/his designate within ten (10) working days after receipt of the
                    Employer's written reply as required by step two.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">In the case of a policy grievance, the APTPUO shall file a notice to the
                    management of Academic Labour Relations within fifteen (15) working days after the APTPUO became
                    aware or reasonably ought to have been aware of the occurrence of the circumstance giving rise to
                    the grievance.</paragraph>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">The request for arbitration shall contain details of the grievance, the specific
                    provision(s) or interpretation of the Agreement that allegedly has been violated, and the relief
                    sought from the Arbitrator or Arbitration Board.</paragraph>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Upon receipt of the notice or in any event within ten (10) working days,
                    the management from Academic Labour Relations shall convene a meeting with the aggrieved member, a
                    representative of APTPUO and the dean (or with the APTPUO representative alone in the case of a
                    policy grievance) to explore the possibility of settlement. If no settlement is reached, the
                    management from Academic Labour Relations shall inform the APTPUO in writing within five (5) working
                    days of the meeting and confirm that the matter will proceed to arbitration.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">Both parties agree to retain one or more arbitrators within thirty days following
                    the referral to arbitration. After the arbitrator or chair of the Arbitration Board has been
                    selected, the Employer and the APTPUO shall arrange with the designated arbitrator or Arbitration
                    Board for the hearing of the grievance.</paragraph>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Unless otherwise indicated by the parties, if the parties mutually agree
                    on a settlement according to 4.4.2, the parties shall take all reasonable steps to implement the
                    terms of settlement before the end of the academic session in which the settlement is
                    reached.</paragraph-numbered>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">TIME LIMITS</title>
            <section>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The parties agree to follow the Grievance Procedure in accordance with
                    the steps, time limits and conditions contained herein. If, in any step, the Employer's
                    representative fails to give her/his written answer within the required time limit(s), the grievance
                    is deemed to have been refused at that level and the APTPUO may appeal the grievance to the next
                    step at the expiration of such time limit(s).</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">If the employee or the APTPUO fails to follow the Grievance Procedure in
                    accordance with the required steps, time limits and conditions, the grievance shall be deemed
                    settled on the basis of the Employer's last answer.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Any of the time limits set out in this article may be extended if
                    mutually agreed to in writing.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">In the case of a complaint or grievance involving the allotment of a
                    course or courses, the parties agree that it is preferable to arrive at a solution before the
                    beginning of the academic session in which such a course or courses are to be
                    taught.</paragraph-numbered>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">DECISION NOT TO GRIEVE OR TO WITHDRAW A GRIEVANCE</title>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">If the Association notifies the Employer in writing of a complaint or of an alleged
                violation of the Agreement, but indicates a decision not to grieve, this decision will be without
                prejudice to grievances in similar matters. Such notification shall include a detailed statement of the
                matter in dispute and the specific provision(s) or interpretation(s) of the Agreement that allegedly
                have been violated. Further, the withdrawal of a grievance at any age shall be without prejudice to
                grievances in similar matters if the Employer receives written notification of this decision by the
                Association.</paragraph>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">ARBITRATION</title>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">Grievances shall be heard by a single Arbitrator or by a three (3) person Arbitration
                Board.</paragraph>
            <section>
                
                <title langue="en">SINGLE ARBITRATOR</title>
                <section>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">If a hearing before a single Arbitrator is requested by either
                        party, such request shall be included in the notice provided for in paragraph 4.4.1. The other
                        party shall indicate within ten (10) working days whether or not a single Arbitrator is
                        acceptable.</paragraph-numbered>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">If both parties agree to arbitration before a single Arbitrator, the
                        Arbitrator shall be selected from among the panel set out in paragraph 4.7.3 below. The
                        Arbitrators on the list will be used in their order on it, unless the Arbitrator is unable to
                        provide three hearing days within two months of being contacted by the parties. In such case,
                        the next Arbitrator on the list will be contacted until an available Arbitrator is found. An
                        Arbitrator who has been contacted but is unavailable will be deemed to have been used for the
                        purpose of proceeding in order through the list. If an agreement cannot be reached on an outside
                        arbitrator within five (5) working days, either party may request the appointment of an
                        arbitrator by the Minister of Labour for the Province of Ontario.</paragraph-numbered>
                </section>
                
                <title langue="en">ARBITRATION BOARD </title>
                <section>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">If both parties do not agree to arbitration before a single
                        arbitrator or if either party so requests, the arbitration shall be before a three (3) person
                        Arbitration Board. The parties shall immediately proceed to the selection of a chairperson in
                        accordance with the provisions of 4.7.1.2.</paragraph-numbered>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Each party shall advise the other, within five (5) working days of
                        the selection of the chairperson, of their appointee to the Arbitration
                        Board.</paragraph-numbered>
                </section>
                <section/>
                
                <title langue="en">ARBITRATION PANEL </title>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">The parties agree that for the duration of the present Agreement, the persons
                    listed herein may be chosen to sit as a single Arbitrator pursuant to paragraph 4.7.1.2 or
                    chairperson of a three (3) member Arbitration Board pursuant to paragraph 4.7.2.</paragraph>
                <list Type="Numeric">
                    
                    <item langue="en">Ross Dumoulin</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">Claude H. Foisy</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">Brian Keller</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">Bram Herlich</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">William Neville</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">Michel Picher</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">Mary Ellen Cummings</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">Christine Schmidt</item>
                </list>
                <section/>
                
                <title langue="en">COSTS</title>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">Each party shall bear the expenses of its representatives, participants, and
                    witnesses and of the preparation and presentation of its own case. The fees and expenses of the
                    chairperson or single Arbitrator, the hearing room, and any other expenses incidental to the
                    arbitration hearing shall be borne equally by the parties. The parties agree to use University
                    facilities whenever possible.</paragraph>
                <section/>
                
                <title langue="en">AUTHORITY</title>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">The Board of Arbitration or single Arbitrator shall have no authority to add to,
                    subtract from, modify, change, alter or ignore in any way the provisions of this Agreement or any
                    expressly written amendment or supplement thereto or to extend its duration, unless the parties have
                    expressly agreed, in writing, to give it or her/him specific authority to do so or to make an award
                    which has such effect.</paragraph>
            </section>
        </section>
    </article>
    <article>
        
        <title langue="en">POSITIONS AND APPOINTMENTS</title>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">GENERAL PROVISIONS</title>
            <section>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The parties recognize that various criteria including teaching expertise
                    are involved in the process of identifying and defining requirements for preparing and teaching a
                    course.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en" prefixMark="y">Teaching includes the following
                    activities:</paragraph-numbered>
                <list Type="Alpha">
                    
                    <item langue="en">giving courses, conducting seminars, guiding tutorials and laboratories, and
                        supervising individual study projects;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">preparing and correcting assignments, tests and examinations;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">guiding the work of teaching assistants, markers and laboratory
                        instructors;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">supervising, guiding and evaluating students' individual work, such as theses and
                        papers;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">granting individual consultations outside of class or laboratory time;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">participating in the development of teaching methods, programs or course
                        content;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">preparing instructional material, laboratory exercises and course notes for the
                        member's own students.</item>
                </list>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">All other activities in which the member engages for the purpose of preparing
                    courses and seminars, including those undertaken to ensure that her teaching is in keeping with the
                    current state of the subject taught, are considered teaching activities.</paragraph>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">DURATION OF APPOINTMENT</title>
            <section>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">An appointment terminates on the date set out in the
                    contract.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Notwithstanding 5.2.1, it is understood that an appointment terminates
                    on the date on which the member has submitted all of the final marks to the department as confirmed
                    in writing by the chairperson. Final marks are due no later than ten (10) working days after the
                    final examination, whether scheduled or take-home. A member who, more than once, without valid
                    reason, fails to provide the final marks as required above (except for differed marks) may be denied
                    an appointment for a period of eight (8) months,</paragraph-numbered>
                <section>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">When a member recommends a DFR pursuant to deferral policies of a
                        given faculty or recommends that a student be permitted to take a deferred examination or a
                        supplemental examination, or submit additional course work directly related to the assignment of
                        the final grade for the course in conformity with faculty rules and when such DFR, deferred or
                        supplemental, examination, or additional course work directly related to the assignment of a
                        final grade for the course is authorized by the appropriate authority, the member is
                        responsible</paragraph-numbered>
                    <list Type="Numeric">
                        
                        <item langue="en">for determining the nature of any work or examination to be completed by the
                            student to satisfy the DFR or for preparing the supplemental examination or any other course
                            work directly related to the assignment of the final grade for the course;</item>
                        
                        <item langue="en">for setting the date in accordance with faculty regulations by which the work
                            must be completed or the examination taken;</item>
                        
                        <item langue="en">for grading the work or examination, and </item>
                        
                        <item langue="en">for submitting the final grade.</item>
                    </list>
                    
                    <paragraph langue="en">The member will be paid an amount of $150 for each deferred examination,
                        supplemental examination or any additional course work directly related to the assignment of the
                        final grade for the course, prepared under faculty regulations.</paragraph>
                    
                    <paragraph langue="en">The Employer is responsible for the proctoring of any examination taken in
                        connection with a DFR or in accordance with regulations governing supplementals and for the
                        transmission to the member for grading of any work or examination completed in this
                        connection.</paragraph>
                    
                    <paragraph langue="en">In addition, a member will be paid an amount of $150 every time he/she must
                        prepare and grade a new examination, in addition to the one taken by the group or class, with
                        the prior approval of the appropriate authority.</paragraph>
                </section>
                
                <title langue="en">RECORD OF EMPLOYMENT</title>
                <section>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Upon termination of employment, the Employer, on request, shall
                        issue to the employee a record of employment within five (5) days of receipt of the letter of
                        confirmation described in paragraph 5.2.2 above or within five (5) days of the termination date
                        set out in the contract.</paragraph-numbered>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The total insurable hours set out in the record of employment shall
                        be for the last 25 pay periods or the duration of the contract if the period of employment is
                        less, and shall be in accordance with the agreed upon hours in the letter of agreement with the
                        APTPUO. The total insurable earnings shown will be those of the total amount on the contract,
                        shown in total if there are insurable earnings in each of the last 13 pay periods or shown in a
                        breakdown by pay period if there are pay periods with no insurable earnings. In the latter case,
                        the salary per pay period set out in the record of employment shall be determined in accordance
                        with the actual duration of the contract, i.e. the actual period between the commencement of the
                        contract and the termination date, and shall be in accordance with the agreed upon hours in the
                        letter of agreement with the APTPUO.</paragraph-numbered>
                </section>
            </section>
            <section>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en"/>
                <list Type="Alpha">
                    
                    <item langue="en">When an APTPUO member attends a committee meeting to which he/she has been
                        convened by the Faculty or Department to review a case of academic fraud relating to a course
                        he/she has taught and that the Department has set up to deal with the issue and requiring the
                        attendance of the APTPUO member, he/she shall be paid $175 for such attendance as of May 1,
                        2009.</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">When an APTPUO member participates in an official appeal of a student’s grade in a
                        course he/she has taught and that the department requests that the member undertake a further
                        review of the marks after the end of the contract, he/she will be paid an amount of $175 for
                        such a review.</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">When an APTPUO member is requested to assist with accommodation measures for
                        students during in-class examination and that such accommodation is arranged through the Student
                        Access ServiceCentre and involves additional e-mail, telephone or in-person support on the part
                        of the APTPUO member, he/she shall be paid an amount of $200 for such accommodation
                        assistance.</item>
                </list>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">POSITION TITLES</title>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">The Bargaining Unit as defined in Article 1 is made up of regular part-time academic
                staff and student part-time academic staff.</paragraph>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">APPORTIONMENT OF BUDGETARY ALLOCATIONS</title>
            <section>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">At the beginning of April of each year or as soon as the University
                    budget has been set, the Employer shall advise the APTPUO of the projected amounts set aside for
                    teaching by student part-time academic staff and by regular part-time academic staff in each
                    academic unit for the current fiscal year. Unless the academic unit is unable to hire part-time
                    academic staff, the Employer guarantees that in each faculty these minimum amounts shall be used for
                    teaching by part-time academic staff.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The number of courses allotted to student part-time academic staff will
                    be closely monitored.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The University will make all reasonable efforts not to reduce the total
                    amount spent on bargaining unit work by either regular or student part-time academic staff each year
                    below $6,400,000. In the event that enrolment, funding, program approval or other relevant factors
                    result in such a reduction, the University will give reasons to the APTPUO, and allow thirty (30)
                    days for comment before the following cycle of budgets is finalized. Such comment may include
                    proposals to correct the situation through other mechanisms.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Every year, the Employer will provide the APTPUO with a statement of
                    actual amounts allocated to academic units for part-time teaching.</paragraph-numbered>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">POSTINGS</title>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">Descriptions of courses will be posted as early as is reasonably possible, it being
                understood that where enrolment is predictable, such postings should normally be made at least four (4)
                months prior to commencement of the course.</paragraph>
            <section>
                
                <title langue="en">REGULAR POSTINGS</title>
                <section>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">All courses and work offered to part-time academic staff shall be
                        posted. Where these courses and work are known in advance, they shall be posted in accordance
                        with the procedures set out below.</paragraph-numbered>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The chairperson shall post the offer of employment in the department
                        or faculty on the electronic bulletin board set aside for these purposes for a period of at
                        least thirty (30) days, it being understood that no posting may terminate prior to April 1st for
                        courses commencing after the first of September of the same year. Posting of courses on physical
                        bulletin boards will cease beginning with postings for courses starting in January
                        2012.</paragraph-numbered>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The posting shall be electronic and must
                        indicate:</paragraph-numbered>
                    <list Type="Alpha">
                        
                        <item langue="en">the name of the faculty, department or academic unit; the course code, the
                            number, the section, when necessary, as well as the title and description of the course or
                            work, the number of credits attached to the course, the number of hours of work, the type of
                            course as set out in article 9.3, and the course schedule (session(s), day(s) and
                            hour(s));</item>
                        
                        <item langue="en">whether the course or work is being offered to student part-time academic
                            staff or to regular part-time academic staff;</item>
                        
                        <item langue="en">the minimum required qualifications shall be clearly indicated, it being
                            understood that the classification of applicants under 5.7.2 and Appendix "B" and the
                            provisions of 5.7.3, 5.7.5, and 5.7.6 and not the posted level of qualifications determine
                            the awarding of the position;</item>
                        
                        <item langue="en">start and termination dates of the posting as well as the type of
                            posting;</item>
                        
                        <item langue="en">the procedure for submitting an application to the department or
                            faculty;</item>
                        
                        <item langue="en">the language of instruction, and the level of knowledge (active or passive) of
                            the other official language required, if any.</item>
                    </list>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">A copy of the posting shall be forwarded to the Union office no
                        later than the day on which posting begins.</paragraph-numbered>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">All postings shall be deemed to comply with all of the posting
                        requirements set out in this Agreement unless an objection is received by the Employer within
                        twenty-one (21) days following delivery of a copy of the posting in accordance with subparagraph
                        5.5.1.4. It is understood however that the Employer undertakes to identify and inform APTPUO of
                        any of the following changes in current postings of previously posted courses or work: number of
                        credits, number of hours of work, regular or student posting, minimum requirements, course
                        description, or level of competence in the second language.</paragraph-numbered>
                </section>
                
                <title langue="en">IRREGULAR POSTING</title>
                <section>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">For all courses or work that become available less than thirty (30)
                        days prior to the commencement of the course or work, the period of posting may be reduced to
                        terminate seven (7) days prior to the commencement of the course. A copy of the posting shall be
                        sent to the APTPUO by the academic unit no later than the day on which the posting
                        begins.</paragraph-numbered>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">If an appointment is necessary less than one week before the course
                        or work is to start, the Employer shall so notify the APTPUO in writing, as soon as possible but
                        not later than the day on which the posting begins, and the course shall be posted for at least
                        forty-eight (48) hours. It is understood that all qualified members who have applied for all
                        courses in a given year pursuant to 5.6.5 shall be considered to have applied for all such short
                        postings occurring during that academic year.</paragraph-numbered>
                </section>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">If after having posted a course, the Employer decides to modify the
                    contents of the posting or to cancel the posting, the Employer shall inform the APTPUO of its
                    decision to do so and the reasons thereof at the time the modified posting is posted or at the time
                    the cancelled posting is removed from the appropriate bulletin board, in keeping with the time lines
                    set out in 5.5.1.4.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Appointments occurring after commencement of a course need not be
                    posted, but the APTPUO shall be advised of the said appointment and the reasons why it was made. It
                    is understood that such an appointment must be in accordance with the requirements of this Agreement
                    as per Articles 5.6, 5.7, 5.8 and 5.9 of the collective agreement.</paragraph-numbered>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">APPLICATIONS</title>
            <section>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">All applicants must file their applications electronically. Applications
                    are sent directly to the academic unit. Applicants must specify in order of preference the
                    course(s)/work which interest them most. They may indicate the number of courses they would like to
                    teach during the next session in accordance with paragraph 5.9.3.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">All applications shall be accompanied by a complete C.V. It is
                    understood, however, that the Employer shall not refuse to consider an application filed without a
                    C.V. if the applicant had in fact filed one during the three (3) previous
                    sessions.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">A history of the applicant's teaching experience as part-time academic
                    staff at the University of Ottawa, with the appropriate dates, must be included in any application
                    in order to permit the calculation of seniority (refer to items 10(a) and 12 of Appendix
                    A).</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <title langue="en"/>
                <section>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Any person with seniority as set out in section 5.8 and who, prior
                        to April 1st,</paragraph-numbered>
                    <list Type="Alpha">
                        
                        <item langue="en">had submitted an updated record of employment,</item>
                        
                        <item langue="en">had indicated in writing to the departmental chair, to the program director
                            or, in faculties without departments, to the appropriate section head as indicated in APTPUO
                            postings his/her interest in being employed in the academic unit for the following academic
                            year, and</item>
                        
                        <item langue="en">at the same time had provided in writing details concerning the days and times
                            of his/her availability to teach in the coming year shall be deemed to have applied for all
                            the positions for which he/she is qualified in that academic unit.</item>
                    </list>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">When a member applies for an APTPUO posting, she shall receive a
                        confirmation from the electronic posting system.</paragraph-numbered>
                </section>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Student part-time academic staff may apply for a position posted for
                    regular part-time academic staff, but such an application will be considered only when the posting
                    cannot be filled by regular part-time academic staff.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Regular part-time academic staff may apply for positions posted for
                    student part-time academic staff, but such applications shall be considered only when the posting
                    cannot be filled by student part-time academic staff.</paragraph-numbered>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">APPOINTMENT PROCEDURES</title>
            <section>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en"/>
                <list Type="Alpha">
                    
                    <item langue="en">Applicants shall be rated according to their qualifications and the requirements
                        and other criteria set out in the posting.</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">Subject to 5.7.2(a), an applicant who has previously taught the course in question
                        as regular part-time academic staff will be classified at least in category A of paragraph 5.7.2
                        even if the applicant does not possess some of the required qualifications set out in the
                        posting, unless the department specifies otherwise in the posting.</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">Subject to 5.7.2(a), applicants lacking one or more of the required qualifications
                        shall not be considered; applicants who have lost the seniority point(s) for a given course
                        pursuant to 5.8.1(h) on two consecutive occasions shall be considered unqualified for this
                        course in future.</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">In establishing the ratings, the Employer may consider, among other factors,
                        demonstrated competence as a scholar or teacher, whether or not this is specified in the
                        posting.</item>
                </list>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">For each posted position, applicants who are considered qualified shall
                    be classified into one of the three categories set out below in accordance with the guidelines set
                    out in Appendix "B", it being understood that an individual's classification is for a given position
                    and may vary from position to position.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">a) Category A:</paragraph>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">Applicants possessing all of the required qualifications and experience and
                    fulfilling the language requirements</paragraph>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">or</paragraph>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">where the posted course is a first or second-year undergraduate course,
                    applicants possessing some of the required qualifications and experience, fulfilling the language
                    requirements, and having taught the posted course as a regular part-time professor at least three
                    times with a cumulative average of at least 4 in the answers to the following questions of the
                    Senate "Student response questionnaire for use in the evaluation of teaching and
                    courses":</paragraph>
                <list Type="Roman">
                    
                    <item langue="en">the professor is well prepared for class. . . almost always, often, sometimes,
                        rarely, almost never;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">I think the professor conveys the subject matter effectively . . . almost always,
                        often, sometimes, seldom, almost never;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">I find that the professor, as a teacher, is . . . excellent, good, acceptable,
                        poor, very poor;</item>
                </list>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">it being understood that the cumulative average will be for all the most recent A
                    reports for this course to a maximum of 5.</paragraph>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">b) Category B:</paragraph>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">Where the posted course is a first or second-year undergraduate course,
                    applicants who possess the minimum requirements and some additional qualifications, who fulfill the
                    language requirements, and who have taught the posted course as a regular part-time professor at
                    least three times with a cumulative average of at least 4 in the answers to the questions stated in
                    a) i - iii above; it being understood that the cumulative average will be for all the most recent A
                    reports for this course to a maximum of 5.</paragraph>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">c) Category C:</paragraph>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">A sole applicant who fulfills the language requirements and who clearly possesses
                    uniquely superior qualifications to those of any other applicant and is consequently recognized as
                    an expert in the field.</paragraph>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Where the response averages referred to in 5.7.2 for the last three
                    courses a member has taught in a given faculty are at or above the 8th decile of the current 3-year
                    report by deciles for that faculty, the member will be classified one category above the category in
                    which he or she was originally classified in a given competition, it being understood that the above
                    provision does not apply where the special teaching qualifications for Category A and B in 5.7.2
                    were already given in the original classification with the member having already been moved up one
                    category.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Where an applicant is classified C pursuant to 5.7.3 above but another
                    candidate is classified C pursuant to 5.7.2c), this other candidate shall take precedence over the
                    candidate classified C pursuant to 5.7.3. Where two or more candidates are classified C pursuant to
                    5.7.3 above, seniority shall be the determining factor.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en"/>
                <list Type="Alpha">
                    
                    <item langue="en">In order to assign courses/work at the end of the posting period, the chairperson
                        shall establish a list of qualified applicants who have been classified in accordance with
                        paragraphs 5.7.1 and 5.7.2 in the highest category; such a list shall be in decreasing order of
                        seniority and shall contain the full names as well as the seniority points of the applicants, it
                        being understood that where there is a candidate considered to be in category C, no ranking by
                        seniority of category B and A applicants is necessary, and where there are only B and A
                        applicants, only B applicants need be so ranked. All applicants who by accepting the posting
                        will exceed the limits prescribed in paragraph 5.9.3 shall be removed from the list. The
                        chairperson shall then proceed to offer the posting to applicants in the order in which they
                        appear on the list.</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">The chairperson shall deliver to the dean a copy of the list prepared in
                        accordance with paragraph 5.7.5 a) once the posted courses have been finalized with accepted
                        offers. This list shall be included with the report on hirings sent under paragraph
                        5.10.1.</item>
                </list>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The assignment of courses to the applicants should normally be completed
                    within thirty (30) days following the end of the regular posting. For all other postings, assignment
                    confirmations are given no more than forty-eight (48) hours after the end of the
                    posting.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <title langue="en">TIE BREAKER</title>
                <section>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">If a tie in seniority points results and either or both applicants
                        have been part-time teachers before September 1, 1981, experience acquired before that date may
                        be considered as follows: seniority shall be calculated retroactively, one year at a time, until
                        the tie is broken. If the tie is not broken, the applicant with the most seniority points in the
                        course in question shall be assigned the course.</paragraph-numbered>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The Employer undertakes whenever possible, in the assignment of
                        work, to consider the course selections made by the applicant.</paragraph-numbered>
                </section>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en"/>
                <list Type="Alpha">
                    
                    <item langue="en">Among the courses offered to student part-time academic staff, the Employer may
                        assign not more than one (1) three (3) credit course or equivalent per academic year to a member
                        of the student part-time academic staff on a basis which considers economic need and/or the need
                        to give students teaching experience, rather than rating or seniority.</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">Paragraph 5.7.8 a) cannot be used more than once by the same academic unit in a
                        single academic year as a motive for a course assignment.</item>
                </list>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">It is understood that any contract offered verbally or in writing to a
                    student part-time academic staff member may not be cancelled simply because he/she has lost his/her
                    status as a full-time registered graduate student at the start of the teaching
                    contract.</paragraph-numbered>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">SENIORITY</title>
            <section>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Bargaining unit members shall accumulate seniority as
                    follows:</paragraph-numbered>
                <list Type="Alpha">
                    
                    <item langue="en">one point for each three credit course or equivalent of teaching experience at the
                        University of Ottawa. Where the number of hours of teaching eligible for a point is less, the
                        member will receive a fraction of the seniority point;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">two points for the year during which the member gets at least one course or the
                        equivalent thereof;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">two points for each complete year during which the member has filled any of the
                        following positions on the Association Executive Committee:</item>
                    <list Type="Roman">
                        
                        <item langue="en">President,</item>
                        
                        <item langue="en">Vice-President and Secretary</item>
                        
                        <item langue="en">Treasurer</item>
                        
                        <item langue="en">Grievance Officer(s) (anglophone and francophone)</item>
                    </list>
                    
                    <item langue="en">two points for each member of the negotiating committee, to a limit of five
                        members, in a negotiating year;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">up to a total of eight (8) seniority points per year for members participating on
                        various University or joint employer-employee committees;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">a member awarded a University-administered research grant by the SSHRC, the
                        Canadian Institutes of Health Research, the Heart and Stroke Foundation of Canada or a granting
                        agency allocating funds through a peer-review process, which is recognized by the Research
                        Grants and Ethics Service, will get two (2) seniority points at the end of the year following
                        the awarding of the grant and two (2) points for each subsequent year in which the member holds
                        the grant, as well as two (2) points in recognition per year for the duration of the grant; </item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">it being understood that normally no one member shall receive more than a total of
                        eight (8) seniority points from those allocated under c), d) and e) above in any academic year.
                        Additional points may be awarded upon recommendation of the Labour-Management Committee.
                        Seniority points are not awarded until the beginning of the term following the period in which
                        the points were earned; however, a member may add such points to his or her total in an
                        application for a position in the term immediately following the end of the period for which the
                        points are earned.</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">Notwithstanding 5.8.1 a) and b), no seniority points shall be awarded for any
                        course where the cumulative average for the responses to the three questions referred to in
                        5.7.2 is 2.9 or below, unless the chair considers that there are mitigating circumstances.
                        Similarly, no seniority points will be awarded for the academic year in which for each course
                        taught by the member the cumulative average for the responses to the three questions referred to
                        in 5.7.2 is 2.9 or below, unless the chair considers that there are mitigating
                        circumstances.</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">Where a dean is considering withholding seniority points pursuant to 5.8.1(h), the
                        dean shall inform the member in writing and advise the member that he or she must write to the
                        chair, program director, or appropriate section head within ten (10) working days from receipt
                        of the dean's letter, pursuant to 4.3.1.1, to describe any mitigating circumstances that the
                        member believes should be taken into consideration. All correspondence in this matter will be
                        kept in the member’s file. The member will be advised of the dean’s decision in writing within
                        ten (10) working days. All other sections of article 4 then apply.</item>
                </list>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">At the end of each year, the APTPUO shall forward to the Employer
                    written confirmation of the participation of its members in various activities as set out in
                    paragraph 5.8.1 c) and the allocation of seniority points in accordance with paragraphs 5.8.1 d) and
                    5.8.1 e).</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">By June 30 each year, the University shall post the APTPUO member list
                    on its website, including their seniority points, faculty and home department. It shall remain
                    available on the website until the new list is available the following year. Members must report
                    errors or omissions to Academic Affairs and Labour Relations between June 30 and August 31 of every
                    year. It is understood by the parties that service notices to the Association (under 5.8.1 c), d),
                    e), f) and g)), if any, and Employment contracts are used to determine seniority points, as are the
                    terms of the collective agreement governing the accumulation and withdrawal of these
                    points.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">A student part-time academic staff member may not accumulate more than
                    fifteen (15) seniority points for courses reserved for student part-time academic staff.
                    Notwithstanding the foregoing and 5.8.1, seniority points over and above the fifteen-point limit
                    will be credited to the member for past teaching at the end of the term in which the student
                    part-time academic staff is awarded his or her degree by the Senate of the University of Ottawa or
                    at the end of the term during which the student academic staff member has formally withdrawn from
                    his or her program of studies at the University.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <title langue="en">PERIOD OF INTERRUPTED SERVICE </title>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">An individual who is not in the bargaining unit for a period of twenty-four (24)
                    months or longer shall lose all seniority points previously accumulated. There shall be four
                    exceptions:</paragraph>
                <list Type="Alpha">
                    
                    <item langue="en">an individual holding the position of President, Vice-President and Secretary,
                        Treasurer or Grievance Officer of the APTPUO during such a period;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">members on maternity leave and on childcare leave as specified by this
                        agreement;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">members who have formally applied for work in each of the successive winter and
                        fall terms after the twenty-four (24) month period referred to in 5.8.5 above but who have had
                        insufficient seniority to qualify for positions, or individuals who have not been offered a
                        contract in the twenty-four (24) months referred to in 5.8.5 above because of irregular
                        scheduling of those courses for which they are specially qualified, provided such exceptions are
                        agreed to by the Labour-Management Committee;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">members who, for reasons beyond their control and for a limited time, have taken
                        up residence where regular back-and-forth trips are not possible, on the condition that they
                        present a valid supporting document and a favorable recommendation from the Labour-Management
                        Committee.</item>
                </list>
                
                <title langue="en">RETROACTIVE CALCULATION OF SENIORITY</title>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">Subject to paragraph 5.8.5, members may accumulate seniority points in accordance
                    with paragraph 5.8.1 for bargaining unit work carried out since September 1, 1981.</paragraph>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">HIRING</title>
            <section>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Each employee shall receive from the Employer:</paragraph-numbered>
                <list Type="Numeric">
                    
                    <item langue="en">the Internet link to find and view the collective agreement;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">a copy of the academic regulations of the relevant department or faculty, where
                        such regulations exist;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">an identification card.</item>
                </list>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Applicants who have not been successful in their application are
                    entitled to know, upon request to the dean, the reasons therefore and, where seniority was a factor
                    in the decision, they are entitled to know their seniority point total as well as that of the
                    successful applicant.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <title langue="en">LIMITS IN COURSE ASSIGNMENTS</title>
                <section>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">No member of the bargaining unit may teach courses worth more than
                        fifteen (15) credits in two consecutive sessions. When a member teaches a number of hours that
                        is different from the credit value posted and recognized in the faculty calendar, the credit
                        value will be adjusted in proportion to the number of hours of teaching. It is understood that
                        members teaching at the Official Languages and Bilingualism Institute shall not be given a
                        teaching assignment equivalent to more than 340 hours of teaching in any one academic
                        year.</paragraph-numbered>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The parties recognize that the Faculty of Graduate and Postdoctoral
                        Studies limits employment of full-time graduate students to ten (10) hours per week. In
                        addition, the Faculty of Graduate and Postdoctoral Studies normally considers such work to
                        include at least two (2) hours of preparation time per hour of formal lecture teaching. The
                        parties agree that the Faculty of Graduate and Postdoctoral Studies shall not alter these limits
                        without the consent of the parties. When the member has previously taught the same or similar
                        courses, it is recognized that the Faculty of Graduate and Postdoctoral Studies may consider
                        preparation time to be reduced.</paragraph-numbered>
                </section>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">REPORTS</title>
            <section>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">If an administrative exclusion performs duties that would normally be
                    considered bargaining unit work, the chairperson must so advise the APTPUO in writing and specify
                    the exclusion's full name, his/her position, the course code and all other information that would
                    have normally appeared on a posting pursuant to subparagraph 5.5.1.3.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en" prefixMark="y">No later than the last week of the first month in a given
                    session, an electronic list of all hirings in the academic units shall be posted on a Human
                    Resources website and sent to the APTPUO. This list shall contain the full names of the persons
                    hired, the course code, the number of credits, the number of teaching hours, the persons' category
                    (A, B, or C) and the number of their seniority points.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Should changes occur in the hiring report posted and sent pursuant to
                    5.10.2, the academic unit will advise APTPUO in writing.</paragraph-numbered>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">CANCELLATION OF CONTRACT OR POSTING</title>
            <section>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en" prefixMark="n">The Employer reserves the right to cancel or combine
                    courses where the enrolment is 17 students or less when it comes to credit courses and 25 students
                    for non-credit courses.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en" prefixMark="y">A member who has accepted an appointment which was
                    offered to her/him in writing, shall receive the following indemnifications:</paragraph-numbered>
                <list Type="Alpha">
                    
                    <item langue="en">one seniority point and</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">if the cancellation occurs later than twenty-one (21) days after written
                        acceptance of the appointment ten (10) percent of the contract;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">if the cancellation occurs within twenty-one (21) days of the contract’s start
                        date, fifteen (15) percent of the value of the contract shall be paid should the member never
                        have taught the course. If the member has taught the course before, ten (10) percent of the
                        value of the contract shall be paid;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">if the cancellation occurs after the start date of the contract but before fifty
                        (50) percent of the teaching has been performed, fifty (50) percent of the value of the contract
                        shall be paid. If cancellation occurs after fifty (50) percent of the teaching has been
                        performed, the full value of the contract shall be paid;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">for language courses only, if the cancellation occurs within five (5) days of the
                        contract’s start date, fifteen (15) percent of the value of the contract shall be paid should
                        the member never have taught the course before. If the member has taught the course previously,
                        ten (10) percent of the value of the contract shall be paid.</item>
                </list>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Barring extraordinary circumstances, for example moving to another city,
                    obtaining a full-time position, an illness that prevents the member from completing the required
                    duties or another valid reason, a member wishing to cancel a contract for a course or other work
                    must so advise the chairperson in writing twenty-one (21) days before the beginning of the course or
                    work in the summer and fall sessions and twenty-eight (28) days before the winter session. A member
                    failing to comply with these provisions loses three points from his or her seniority point total
                    accumulated prior to the cancellation and the Labour-Management Committee will be informed. It is
                    understood that accepting a part-time position in another institution in the region does not
                    constitute an extraordinary circumstance with respect to this provision.</paragraph-numbered>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">SALARY</title>
            <section>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The minimum salary and hourly rates are set out in Appendix
                    "D".</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Portions of courses or courses with different credit value shall be paid
                    on a pro rata basis.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <title langue="en">INSTALMENTS</title>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">Salaries shall be paid in equal semi-monthly instalments over the period of the
                    appointment and a statement of earnings and deductions will be provided on a semi-monthly basis. If
                    the pay of the employee cannot be processed for payment on the first regular payday following one
                    (1) month after the commencement of work, then the employee may request a special cheque and the
                    Employer shall issue such a cheque before the subsequent regular payday.</paragraph>
                
                <title langue="en">TRANSITIONAL PROVISIONS</title>
                <section>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The rates set out in Appendix "D" shall apply to all members
                        appointed to perform bargaining unit work to commence on or after September 1,
                        2010.</paragraph-numbered>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Retroactive payments to those members earning less than the
                        above-noted rates shall be made to those members performing bargaining unit work since September
                        1, 2010 within no more than three (3) pay periods of ratification of this Agreement. After that
                        period, the members shall be paid in accordance with the new rates set out in Appendix
                        "D".</paragraph-numbered>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Entitlement with respect to all fringe benefits except sick leave
                        shall be assumed to have commenced on the 1st day of September, 1986. For the purposes of the
                        accumulation of unused sick leave, employees who have acquired seniority since September 1, 1984
                        may accumulate sick leave as provided for in section 7.3.</paragraph-numbered>
                </section>
            </section>
        </section>
    </article>
    <article>
        
        <title langue="en">DISCIPLINE AND DISCHARGE</title>
        <section>
            
            <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The Employer accepts the concept of progressive discipline. In this context,
                the Employer shall warn an employee in writing that discipline may follow the repetition of the act or
                omission complained of or the failure of the employee to bring her/his work up to a reasonable standard
                by a given date. Such date shall allow the employee reasonable opportunity to correct the problem(s)
                referred to in the letter of warning.</paragraph-numbered>
            
            <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Notwithstanding 6.1, in exceptional circumstances, the Employer retains the
                right to discipline an employee for just cause without having first issued such a written warning. In
                such cases, the University undertakes to take reasonable steps to consult with the APTPUO prior to the
                imposition of such discipline. It is further understood that the Employer is not precluded by this
                Article from relying on and introducing as evidence at any stage of the grievance and arbitration
                process the employee's previous disciplinary record.</paragraph-numbered>
            
            <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Prior to imposing discipline, the dean or her/his designate, where
                appropriate</paragraph-numbered>
            <list Type="Roman">
                
                <item langue="en">shall notify the employee in writing of the time and place of a meeting to discuss the
                    matter and shall advise the employee of her/his right to APTPUO representation at that
                    meeting;</item>
                
                <item langue="en">shall, where the discharge or the suspension without pay of the employee is being
                    considered, delay the imposition of discipline for seven (7) calendar days (pro-rated for sessions
                    other than Autumn/Winter but not less than three (3) working days), on request of the
                    employee.</item>
            </list>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">It is agreed that the Employer has the right in exceptional circumstances to suspend
                an employee with pay during the period of its consideration of the matter, including the delay in
                6.3(ii), and prior to the imposition of any other discipline.</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Where a dean receives an unsolicited signed complaint by a student against a
                member and determines that further action is required, the dean shall forward a copy of the complaint to
                the member after having removed, if possible under the circumstances, the sections of the complaint
                which could lead to an identification of the author of the complaint.</paragraph-numbered>
            
            <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Where the dean forwards a complaint to the member, he shall invite the
                member to comment on the complaint either orally or in writing within five (5) working days. He shall
                also write to the member to contact his APTPUO representative. No action may be taken by the dean until
                a copy of the complaint has been sent to the concerned member and the five-day period has
                expired.</paragraph-numbered>
            
            <paragraph-numbered langue="en">If the dean determines, after the expiry of the five day period, that
                further action may be required, and if the complaint concerns teaching practices, he shall appoint two
                independent tenured professors from the same field to audit the member's course and to report on whether
                any action is required in light of the complaint.</paragraph-numbered>
            
            <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The member shall not be removed from his teaching responsibilities unless
                the professors auditing the member's course recommend and the dean agrees that an immediate replacement
                is required to avoid irreparable harm to the students. In all other cases concerning teaching practices,
                the member shall be allowed to continue teaching until the end of the term and shall be advised of
                resources available at the University to improve teaching skills.</paragraph-numbered>
            
            <paragraph-numbered langue="en">All disciplinary investigations shall be treated as confidential by the
                Union and the Employer.</paragraph-numbered>
            
            <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The Employer agrees that an employee shall not be disciplined solely for
                failure to perform her/his duties because she/he is arrested and/or incarcerated provided that the
                employee notifies her/his Supervisor of the arrest and/or incarceration and the expected duration
                thereof as soon as possible. The Employer, however, reserves the right to discipline an employee for
                just cause for failure to perform her/his duties for reasons other than arrest and/or incarceration or
                for activities which may have been related to or coincident with the arrest and/or incarceration.
                Further, it is understood that loss of salary for failure to perform scheduled duties shall not
                constitute discipline in the context of this article. It is also understood that no disciplinary steps
                will be undertaken during the time a member is seriously ill or hospitalized, provided the member has
                informed the chair of the illness and provided the Manager, Occupational Health, Disability and Leave,
                Human Resources, has received a medical certificate confirming the illness and indicating an appropriate
                date by which the treating physician believes the member should be able to resume her/his duties. It is
                understood that in the case of a grave illness, the member is not required to submit the medical
                certificate until this becomes possible; it is also understood that any delay in the disciplinary
                process due to the condition of the member’s health shall not prejudice the Employer’s right to begin or
                to proceed with the disciplinary process when the member is judged to be capable of returning to
                work.</paragraph-numbered>
            
            <paragraph-numbered langue="en">An employee who is disciplined shall be advised in writing of the nature of
                the discipline, of the reasons for the disciplinary action and of her/his right to initiate a grievance
                and to be represented by the Union.</paragraph-numbered>
            
            <paragraph-numbered langue="en">If an employee wishes to grieve his/her discipline, Steps one and two as set
                out in 4.3 shall be modified in the following manner:</paragraph-numbered>
            <list Type="Alpha">
                
                <item langue="en">at Step one, the dean shall replace the chairperson;</item>
                
                <item langue="en">at Step two, an APTPUO Union officer shall meet with the management of Academic Labour
                    Relations. </item>
            </list>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">Subject to 4.5, time limits for these steps remain as set out in 4.3.</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The identity of a student complainant is privileged information and will not
                be disclosed under any circumstances, but where a dean has taken disciplinary action based on a written
                complaint and the matter is referred to arbitration, the arbitrator at the request of the APTPUO may
                order that the identity of the student be disclosed to him or her.</paragraph-numbered>
            
            <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Notwithstanding 6.1, any warning or discipline shall not be used against an
                employee after a period of twenty-four (24) months from the date of the warning or discipline except
                where it can be shown that the previous warning or discipline was for conduct similar to that giving
                rise to the current warning or discipline.</paragraph-numbered>
            
            <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Unless there are recognized mitigating circumstances identified in writing,
                when a member obtains a third consecutive evaluation with an average of 3.1 or below 3.1 for a given
                course, the dean may withdraw the member’s right to teach that course for one year. In such a case, the
                dean shall communicate this decision to the member in writing.</paragraph-numbered>
        </section>
    </article>
    <article>
        
        <title langue="en">ABSENCES AND LEAVES</title>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">ABSENCES – GENERAL</title>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">An employee shall, as soon as possible, advise the chairperson of her/his inability
                to perform her/his scheduled duties and the reasons thereof. Except in the case of sick leave pursuant
                to 7.3, the employee shall also make all reasonable efforts to reschedule those duties to another
                appropriate time when the employee is able to attend, or to make such other arrangements with respect to
                substitution of personnel, by trading work assignments or amendment of the work as may be agreed to by
                the dean or her/his designate. Such an agreement shall not be unrea sonably withheld.</paragraph>
            
            <title langue="en">TERMINATION OF CONTRACT – COURSE CANCELLATION OR INSTRUCTIONAL CONTINUITY</title>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">The Employer reserves the right to cancel a contract in order to cancel a course or
                to hire a replacement if the Employer has a reasonable expectation that the employee will not be able,
                by reason of absence, to carry out at least 10/13 of the assigned work in any course. Such termination
                shall not affect the employee's entitlement to paid sick leave or maternity leave, as provided for
                below.</paragraph>
            
            <title langue="en">SICK LEAVE</title>
            <section>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Provided that the employee has, as soon as possible, advised the
                    chairperson of her/his inability to perform her/his scheduled duties because of illness, an employee
                    may claim sick leave with full pay and benefits for up to 2/13 of her/his total assigned work in
                    each course.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Periods of sick leave lasting thee (3) working days or more must be
                    supported by a doctor's certificate.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Employees are not eligible for sick leave if they are already on any
                    other form of leave. Unused sick leave from the two previous academic years may be accumulated but
                    no more than 4/13 of any assigned course can be taken as sick leave on presentation of an
                    appropriate medical certificate. The two-year period may be extended by the Employer at its
                    discretion where on the basis of exceptional circumstances the Labour-Management Committee so
                    recommends. Unused sick leave has no monetary value.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">An employee who provides medical certification that she/he is unable to
                    return to work following a period for which sick leave with pay was granted, shall not lose
                    seniority previously acquired, and shall gain seniority as if she/he had completed the work
                    assignment in which she/he was engaged when she/he became ill, provided that the person is available
                    for work at the conclusion of the period covered by medical certification, and in any event, not
                    later than one (1) year from the initial granting of sick leave with pay.</paragraph-numbered>
            </section>
            
            <title langue="en">BEREAVEMENT LEAVE</title>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">Provided that the provisions of 7.1 have been complied with, an employee shall be
                granted up to four (4) consecutive days leave, the first two (2) of which are with salary and benefits
                and the last two (2) of which are without salary or benefits, in the case of the death of a parent,
                spouse, sibling, child, mother-in-law, father-in-law, or grandparent. In exceptional circum stances,
                additional leave may be granted by the Employer; the Employer may also consider cases of bereavement
                other than those listed above and may grant leave at its discretion.</paragraph>
            
            <title langue="en">PARENTAL LEAVE</title>
            <section>
                
                <title langue="en">MATERNITY LEAVE</title>
                <section>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Pregnant part-time academic staff shall be entitled to a maternity
                        leave for a conse cutive duration of twenty (20) weeks to commence at any time between seventeen
                        (17) weeks prior to anticipated delivery and the date of delivery. Unless exceptional
                        circumstances exist, one month's notice shall be given to the Employer. In normal circumstances,
                        a month's notice will be given to the Employer, but no later than two weeks prior to the
                        expected date of delivery, unless the member has to stop work due to complications caused by her
                        pregnancy in which case the member will provide to the Employer a medical certificate attesting
                        to such complications and the date of the expected delivery.</paragraph-numbered>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Where the employee is performing bargaining unit work at the time
                        notice referred to in 7.5.1.1 above is given and that work is not scheduled to be completed
                        prior to the commencement of the proposed leave, the member shall receive the lesser of the
                        balance of remuneration owing under her contract or 95% of full pay and benefits for two (2)
                        weeks.</paragraph-numbered>
                    
                    <paragraph langue="en">Notwithstanding the foregoing, a member who has completed 60% of her contract
                        at the time her maternity leave commences shall receive the greater of 50% of the balance of the
                        remuneration owing under the contract or 95% of full pay and benefits for two (2) weeks. Where
                        the member has taught 60% of a three-credit course prior to taking maternity leave, the
                        seniority point for that course will be awarded; where the member is teaching a six-credit
                        course, she will be awarded one seniority point for the completion of one term of teaching and
                        another seniority point if she has taught 60% or more of the other term prior to taking
                        maternity leave. It is understood that for the purposes of article 5.8.1 b), the member is
                        entitled to two (2) seniority points for the year in which she taught.</paragraph>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">A pregnant member who wishes to continue working during the period
                        of pregnancy shall not be denied that right. When accommodations are required for her to
                        continue working, the Employer may require a medical certificate confirming the required
                        accommodations.</paragraph-numbered>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Absence for up to eighteen months (18) occurring between six (6)
                        months before and eighteen (18) months after the birth of a child shall not cause a loss of
                        seniority.</paragraph-numbered>
                </section>
            </section>
            <section>
                
                <title langue="en">PATERNITY LEAVE</title>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">The employer agrees to grant paid paternity leave for 1/13 of the contract
                    immediately after the birth or adoption of a child under the father's responsibility, on the
                    condition that the member inform his director as soon as possible of his inability to carry out his
                    assigned duties.</paragraph>
            </section>
            <section>
                
                <title langue="en">CHILD CARE LEAVE</title>
                <section>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Any member may take a child care leave
                        following:</paragraph-numbered>
                    <list Type="Alpha">
                        
                        <item langue="en">the birth of a child, or</item>
                        
                        <item langue="en">the coming of the child into the custody and care of the parent for the first
                            time.</item>
                    </list>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Child care leave is open to both parents. For the purposes of this
                        section, "parent" includes a person with whom a child is placed for adoption and a person who is
                        in a relationship of some permanence with a parent of a child and who intends to treat the child
                        as his or her own.</paragraph-numbered>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Child care leave may begin no more than 52 weeks after the day the
                        child is born or comes into the custody and care of the parent for the first time. Child care
                        leave ends no later than 35 weeks after it began if it is taken following maternity leave and 37
                        weeks in all other cases and is without pay, unless paternity leave has been granted pursuant to
                        7.5.2 above, in which case the week of paternity leave is a week of paid leave and constitutes
                        the first week of the 37 weeks of child care leave. Child care leave may be taken following
                        maternity leave and must begin immediately after maternity leave. During child care leave and
                        maternity leave, seniority points pursuant to 5.8.5(c) are maintained.</paragraph-numbered>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The member must notify his or her chairperson, in writing, of the
                        date of commencement of the child care leave as soon as possible after the member becomes aware
                        of the date.</paragraph-numbered>
                </section>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">During a member's maternity leave or child care leave, the Employer
                    shall continue to make the Employer's contributions for any plan to which the member was subscribing
                    at the time of the leave unless the member gives the Employer a written notice that he or she does
                    not intend to pay his or her contributions.</paragraph-numbered>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">JURY LEAVE</title>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">Subject to the provisions of section 7.1 the Employer shall grant leave of absence
                with pay and benefits to an employee who serves as a juror or witness in any court or who must attend
                citizenship court.</paragraph>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">ACADEMIC DEVELOPMENT</title>
            <section>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">In the event that an employee wishes to under take a project of academic
                    development, inclu ding but not limited to advanced study, research and other scholarly activity,
                    the member may apply for academic development leave of no more than one (1) year’s
                    duration.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Application shall be made to the Academic and Professional Development
                    Fund Committee at least three (3) months before the proposed commencement date of the leave. The
                    applica tion shall include all pertinent details of the project and an up to date C.V. of the
                    applicant.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The Academic and Professional Development Fund Committee shall decide to
                    grant academic development leave if, in the Committee's judgment, the project is likely to enhance
                    the ability of the member to contribute to the academic program of the University. The granting of
                    this leave shall not be unreasonably withheld and the decision shall be given no later than two (2)
                    months prior to the proposed date of commencement of the said leave.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The employee shall accrue seniority for the period of academic
                    development leave, where there exists a reasonable expectation that the employee would have been
                    assigned to duties during the period of the leave. Such seniority accrued shall be equivalent to the
                    average rate of accrual of seniority during the better of (a) the preceding period of three (3)
                    years or (b) the preceding number of conti nuous academic years in which the employee performed
                    bargaining unit work.</paragraph-numbered>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">GENERAL LEAVE</title>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">A member may apply for, and the Employer may grant leaves of absence with or without
                pay in circumstances not covered explicitly by this Agreement. APTPUO will be informed in writing of
                such a request and its result.</paragraph>
        </section>
    </article>
    <article>
        
        <title langue="en">PARTICIPATION</title>
        <section>
            
            <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The Parties acknowledge that the resolution set out below was passed by the
                Senate of the University of Ottawa on April 3, 1989 and it is agreed that such resolution shall not be
                altered without the express written consent of the Parties.</paragraph-numbered>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">PART-TIME TEACHERS AND UNIVERSITY GOVERNANCE</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">Resolution 1: a resolution amending the membership of the departmental assembly in
                faculties with departments (or schools which function as departments).</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">It is proposed that when the departmental assembly is dealing with matters relating
                to the APUO Collective Agreement, it shall not include members of the part-time academic staff but shall
                include members of the full-time academic staff. In all other cases, members of the part-time academic
                staff shall be included in the departmental assembly with both voice and vote. Part-time academic staff
                shall mean sessional lecturers, part-time language teachers, and students registered at the University
                of Ottawa who have full or joint full responsibility for a course. Full-time academic staff shall mean
                regular professors, replacement professors, research fellows, and professors with cross-appointments,
                but shall exclude visiting professors and adjunct professors.</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">Part-time academic staff members are to be elected in accordance with the following
                provisions:</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">1) Any member of the part-time academic staff who has a full or joint full
                responsibility for a course is eligible.</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">2) Part-time academic staff shall elect members from amongst their
                numbers.</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">3) For the purpose of this resolution, the academic year begins September 1 and ends
                next August 31.</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">4) Part-time academic staff shall elect a maximum of two members. The following scale
                will apply:</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">- less than 36 credits or the equivalent taught during the academic year by part-time
                academic staff: no member;</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">- between 36 and 53 credits or the equivalent taught during the academic year by
                part-time academic staff: one member;</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">- more than 53 credits or the equivalent taught during the academic year by part-time
                academic staff: two members.</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">5) The number of elected members shall be kept constant for a three-year period at
                the end of which the number of members to be elected shall be determined in accordance with paragraph 4
                above, the number of credits to be calculated according to the average number of credits taught by
                part-time academic staff during that period.</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">For the first election, the number of members shall be determined in accordance with
                paragraph 4 above, the number of credits to be calculated according to the average number of credits
                taught by part-time academic staff between September 1st, 1986 to August 31st, 1989.</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">6) The chairperson of the department or the chairperson's appointee shall be
                responsible for the election.</paragraph>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <paragraph-numbered langue="en">In the event that Senate modifies its general regulation on the composition
                of faculty councils, the management from Academic Labour Relations for the University shall meet with
                the deans to explore fully the possibilities of such representation.</paragraph-numbered>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">If the APTPUO wishes to express concerns and/or proposals to the Senate or to the
                Board of Governors, it may transmit the appropriate number of copies of its submission to the Secretary
                of the University, who shall ensure that copies are distributed to the members of Senate, without
                prejudice.</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Representatives of part-time teaching staff members are elected at the start
                of the fall term during the first three weeks of September. Alternates are also elected to replace
                representatives who are unable to attend the Departmental Assembly. When no candidate is elected in
                September, elections will be held during the first three weeks of the following
                January.</paragraph-numbered>
            
            <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Departments will be strongly encouraged to pay legitimate expenses (i.e.,
                parking, photocopies) incurred by part-time academic staff representatives attending meetings of
                Departmental Assembly (or Faculty Council if appropriate).</paragraph-numbered>
        </section>
    </article>
    <article>
        
        <title langue="en">CLASS SIZE</title>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">PEDAGOGICAL RESPONSIBILITY</title>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">The Employer and the Union agree upon the objective of maintaining class sizes and
                formats conducive to pedagogical soundness.</paragraph>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">PROJECTED ENROLMENT</title>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">Projected course enrolments established by the Employer shall be set out in position
                postings and contracts for all part-time academic staff, except where not relevant.</paragraph>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <paragraph-numbered langue="en">TYPES OF COURSES: The parties recognize four (4) types of
                courses:</paragraph-numbered>
            <list Type="Alpha">
                
                <item langue="en">Type "A" Courses: courses with no written assignments and without examinations that
                    cannot be computer marked.</item>
                
                <item langue="en">Type "B" Courses: courses with either written assignments or examinations which are
                    not computer marked.</item>
                
                <item langue="en">Type "C" Courses: courses with written assignments and with examinations which are not
                    computer marked.</item>
                
                <item langue="en">Type "D" Courses: courses which, by their nature, consist primarily of individual
                    attention teaching or of small group interactions, e.g. second language teaching, problem solving
                    sessions, and the like.</item>
            </list>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">MARKING AND GRADING ASSISTANCE AND/OR COMPENSATION</title>
            <section>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The member or members teaching a Type "A" course shall be assigned
                    assistance and/or equivalent additional compensation which shall be at least at the rate of 2 1/2
                    hours of marker/grader assistance for each credit value of the course for each block of 10 students
                    or portion thereof exceeding the critical number.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The member or members teaching a Type "B", "C" or "D" course shall be
                    assigned assistance and/or equivalent additional compensation which shall be at least at the rate of
                    2 1/2 hours of marker/grader assistance for each credit value of the course for each block of 5
                    students or portion thereof exceeding the critical enrolment number set out in section
                    9.5.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Assistance shall be provided from the commencement of the course where
                    the initial enrolment exceeds the critical number, but the assistance may be modified so as to
                    reflect the actual enrolment as of the first official enrolment reporting date after the
                    commencement of the course.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Where the initial enrolment is equal to or less than the critical number
                    but actual enrolment as of the first official enrolment reporting date exceeds the critical number,
                    assistance shall be provided as set out in 9.4.1.</paragraph-numbered>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">CRITICAL ENROLMENT NUMBERS</title>
            <section>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">For the types of courses set out in 9.3, the critical numbers shall be
                    as follows:</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">Type "A" – 90 Type "B" – 60 Type "C" – 45 Type "D" - 35 (25 in the case of
                    courses, related to the bilingual mandate of the University including courses given at the Centre
                    for Second Language Learning).</paragraph>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">It is understood that the above figures are not intended to represent
                    norms in class size.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Departments shall employ the same set of rules or criteria in
                    determining the point at which enrolment requires the creation of a new section of a course, whether
                    or not the course is taught by a full-time professor or a member of APTPUO.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en"> </paragraph-numbered>
                <list Type="Alpha">
                    
                    <item langue="en">The number of students registered in a given course is the official number of
                        registered students as established by the Office of the Registrar immediately after the date
                        indicated in the University calendar as the last day for changes in course selection for a given
                        term.</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">From September 1, 2007 to August 31, 2008, a member shall receive an amount of
                        $9.75 for each student for a given type of course over and above the original critical number of
                        registrations for the course in question, as established in 9.5.1. </item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">From September 1, 2008 to August 31, 2009, a member shall receive an amount of
                        $9.75 for each student for a given type of course over and above the original critical number of
                        registrations for the course in question, as established in 9.5.1. </item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">From September 1, 2009 to August 31, 2010, a member shall receive an amount of
                        $9.75 for each student for a given type of course over and above the original critical number of
                        registrations for the course in question, as established in 9.5.1. </item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">Notwithstanding the allocations set out in 9.5.4 a), b) and c), for the period
                        extending from September 1, 2007 to August 31, 2009, a member shall receive the larger of these
                        two amounts: either the allocations set out in 9.5.4 a) and b), or $400 for each multiple of the
                        critical number of registrations specified in 9.5.1.</item>
                </list>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">PAYMENT IN LIEU OF ASSISTANCE</title>
            <section>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Funds for marker/grader assistance is intended first for the
                    University's students. Nevertheless, the Employer shall give reasonable consideration to any
                    reasoned request by a member to receive compensation in lieu of marking assistance. Where such
                    request is granted, payment shall be the greater of the minimum rate established by the University
                    for marker/correctors or the current rate paid by the department offering the
                    course.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Where a member can make a reasonable case to the Employer that the
                    assigned grader/marker is not performing or has not performed satisfactorily, the Employer will
                    offer the member a prorated compensation in lieu of assistance for the marking to be done or for the
                    remainder of the marking not done by the grader/marker. The request for compensation must be made no
                    later than 15 working days after the end of the session.</paragraph-numbered>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The Employer shall endeavour to ensure that the number of seats and
                work/writing surfaces/spaces available in the assigned classroom, laboratory or studio is sufficient for
                the number of students in a class.</paragraph-numbered>
        </section>
    </article>
    <article>
        
        <title langue="en">WORKING CONDITIONS</title>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">FACILITIES</title>
            <section>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">To the extent that University resources permit it, the Employer shall
                    provide employees with facilities and services which are reasonably necessary for the effective
                    discharge of their responsibilities of employment, such as reasonable library and computing services
                    and facilities, and reasonable secretarial and technical services and other support facilities,
                    including the Teaching Resource Centre. An e-mail account must be set up for the member by the time
                    of his or her first pay under a teaching contract and kept open both during active contracts and as
                    long as the part-time professor's name appears on the seniority lists posted in compliance with
                    5.8.3. Access to library services, to Montpetit Hall sports facilities and to special Bookstore
                    benefits for APTPUO members is maintained as long as the member appears on the seniority
                    list.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">The University shall provide a voice messaging system for all members of APTPUO
                    to communicate with their students by telephone during the term in which they hold a contract with
                    the University, including the period ending with the final date for returning their final marks to
                    the appropriate authority, provided members complete the appropriate form and return it to the
                    appropriate authority, it being understood that the University is not responsible for any long
                    distance charges related to this voice messaging system.</paragraph>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">It is understood that a department shall provide a copy of the required
                    textbook and, in units where special methods are specified, access to a reasonable number of manuals
                    setting out the required teaching methods.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The parties agree that part-time academic staff normally require office
                    space to perform part of their workload duties.The parties further agree that the Employer is not
                    required to provide such an office but where an office is not provided, part-time academic staff may
                    request that the Employer acknowledge in writing the need for part-time academic staff to maintain
                    an office at their own expense.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">When a member teaches in an academic unit, the academic unit will, on
                    request and for the duration of the session, assign the member a locker or space in a lockable
                    filing cabinet, provided such space is available.The member will return the key at the end of the
                    session.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">When members teach online courses, they receive a maximum of $15 per
                    month reimbursement for Internet fees upon presentation of a receipt confirming such expenses during
                    the session in which the course is given. In this situation, if the member requests an
                    acknowledgment under 10.1.3, the form must show that the reimbursement in question has been
                    given.</paragraph-numbered>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">PARKING</title>
            <section>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The APTPUO shall be entitled to appoint one (1) member to the University
                    of Ottawa Parking Committee.Rules for members' use of parking facilities and fees for members'
                    parking permits shall be established by the Employer upon consultation with the Parking
                    Committee.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">When an employee is appointed or assigned duties at a place of work
                    within the City of Ottawa but not on either campus of the University, the Employer will reimburse
                    reasonable parking costs incurred upon submission of receipts.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The Employer shall make its best effort to ensure the availability of
                    adequate parking facilities at reasonable cost it being understood that the allocation is subject to
                    rules and regulations of the Parking Committee.Every member may receive, free of charge, a parking
                    permit which will entitle her/him to park in any University of Ottawa parking lot at any time on
                    Saturdays, Sundays and holidays.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Members required to teach evening courses will be entitled to receive a
                    parking permit for evenings (after 4:00 p.m.) at the regular cost of such
                    permits.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Subject to availability of parking permits, APTPUO members may obtain a
                    parking permit for a given session at the same rates as those for regular staff members on condition
                    that the permit be for at least 3 months and that the member hold a teaching contract during the
                    period or have a letter from the department or faculty to the effect that a teaching contract has
                    been offered the member for the given period.If parking spaces are available, the permit may be
                    issued at the time the member applies.It is understood that all regulations of the Parking Service
                    apply to these permits.</paragraph-numbered>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">OFF-CAMPUS TEACHING</title>
            <section>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">When an employee is appointed or assigned duties at a place of work
                    outside the City of Ottawa, the employee shall be reimbursed for those reasonable costs of travel to
                    and from the place of work.These costs shall be based upon current University rates for travel by
                    private automobile and shall reflect the minimum number of trips necessary for the completion of
                    assigned instruction from the main campus of the Employer to the place of work.Such costs shall not
                    be paid to employees who reside near the place of work outside the City of
                    Ottawa.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The Employer shall reimburse costs incurred for lodging where part-time
                    academic staff, required to be outside of the City of Ottawa on assigned duties, is unable to return
                    to his/her residence on the same day because of unforeseen events beyond his/her
                    control.</paragraph-numbered>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">STATUTORY CONTRIBUTIONS</title>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">The Employer agrees to make required statutory contributions to C.P.P. and E.I.C. on
                account of each employee.</paragraph>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">BENEFITS</title>
            <section>
                
                <title langue="en">MAJOR MEDICAL</title>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">Members holding appointments may opt into the Employer's major medical plan, at
                    the time of appointment for a period of twelve months unless they have reached the age of 65, in
                    which case they are not eligible for this coverage.This plan covers prescription drugs, home
                    nursing, ambulance service, wheelchairs, dental work arising from accidents and the removal of
                    wisdom teeth to a lifetime maximum of $25,000 per person.Members shall accumulate credits applicable
                    towards the insurance premiums otherwise payable, up to a maximum of 100% of the premium, at the
                    rate of 8.3% of the premium per credit or equivalent taught during the preceding academic
                    year.</paragraph>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">UNIVERSITY HEALTH SERVICES</title>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">All members of the bargaining unit shall be entitled to make use of the University
                Health Services, free of charge on the same terms and conditions as the other employees of the
                Employer.</paragraph>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">COUNSELLING AND PERSONAL DEVELOPMENT SERVICE</title>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">All members of the bargaining unit shall be entitled to make use of the University's
                Counselling and Personal Development Service, with the exception of personal therapy, free of charge
                during summer months.</paragraph>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">PHOTOCOPYING</title>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">The APTPUO shall have access to a photocopying machine, at cost price, for the final
                copy of Master's theses or their equivalent and Doctoral dissertations for student members of the
                bargaining unit.The APTPUO will provide the Employer with a detailed account of the photocopying costs
                involved, including the names of the student members and the number of pages copied for each student
                member's thesis.The Employer will remit to the APTPUO the costs of this photocopying to a maximum of
                $7,000.</paragraph>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">SPORTS COMPLEX</title>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">Any member of the bargaining unit and any person who continues to maintain seniority
                has basic access to the Montpetit Hall sports facilities.The member must present a valid employee
                identification card issued by Human Resources Service at the Client Services Desk of Montpetit Hall
                according to the procedures of Client Services.</paragraph>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">GUIDANCE FOR STUDENT MEMBERS</title>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">Where possible, guidance in the form of orientation, access to past course outlines,
                course objectives, bibliographies, recommended readings and teaching strategies shall be provided for
                student members who have limited or unrelated teaching experience.The APTPUO recognizes that the
                availability of some materials may be beyond the control of the Employer and therefore not
                available.</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">Before offering a student a course posted for a student-professor member, it is
                strongly recommended that the department ensure that the member has taught previously or has held a
                position as a teaching assistant or has completed some form of pedagogical training.</paragraph>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">ACADEMIC AND PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT FUND</title>
            <section>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The Employer agrees to maintain a fund to be administered by the
                    management of Academic Labour Relations to support research and advanced study (including travel
                    grants) for bargaining unit members.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Grants are awarded through competition based on academic merit of the
                    proposal by a selection committee consisting of one member of the bargaining unit to be selected by
                    the APTPUO, one full-time faculty member selected by the Employer and the management of Academic
                    Labour Relations. The selection committee evaluates the grant applications and decides on any amount
                    to be awarded.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en" prefixMark="y">At the beginning of September 2010, the Employer will
                    provide an annual fund of $100,000 for the purposes set out in 10.11.1. At the beginning of
                    September of each year, the Employer will add a sufficient amount to bring the balance up to
                    $100,000 and supplement the said fund with an additional amount equal to the percentage increase of
                    the basic rate as indicated in Appendix "D". These increases are cumulative from year to year to the
                    fund established in September 2010.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">It is understood that the Employer reserves the right to approve
                    additional amounts where the quality and number of applications are such that the fund is clearly
                    shown to be insufficient.Such decision shall only be considered on recommendation of the selection
                    committee that a particular proposal is of high quality and that there are insufficient funds at the
                    disposal of the selection committee to permit approval and that a delay in the acceptance of the
                    proposal is not practical.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The Labour-Management Committee is authorized to develop guidelines for
                    the administration and distribution of funds from the Academic and Professional Development Fund in
                    accordance with the regulations set out in Appendix "E" and "F".</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en" prefixMark="y">On the first day of October, February and June, the
                    University shall report to the APTPUO in writing and send electronically with respect to the status
                    of the Fund, including the names, departments, confirmation of their status (regular or student),
                    amount received, amount remaining in the Fund and date of award.</paragraph-numbered>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">WAYS AND MEANS FUND</title>
            <section>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The APTPUO and the Employer agree to establish a Ways and Means Fund to
                    be administered by the Employer, subject to recommendations from the Labour-Management
                    Committee.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Expenditures from this fund may be made on the instructions of a
                    committee established by the APTPUO, according to guidelines established by the Labour-Management
                    Committee. Expenditures may include awards for humanitarian considerations and for non-compensated
                    contributions in a university setting.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">In 1994-1995, and again in 1995-1996, the Employer agrees to contribute
                    to the Fund $2.00 for every $1.00 contributed to the Fund by the APTPUO, to a maximum contribution
                    by the Employer of $10,000. Interest gained by the Fund shall be paid into the Fund annually at the
                    rate of interest earned by the University on its short term investments.</paragraph-numbered>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en" prefixLineOnly="y">TUITION FEE CREDITS</title>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">Members of the bargaining unit are eligible for tuition fee waivers for MTCU-funded
                programs and courses as follows:</paragraph>
            <list Type="Alpha">
                
                <item langue="en">Tuition fees credits are earned on the basis of 7.5% of the remuneration paid for
                    bargaining unit work.</item>
                
                <item langue="en">All members of the bargaining unit who will be commencing their fourth consecutive
                    year of teaching at the University of Ottawa shall be entitled to receive tuition fee credits at the
                    rate of 15% of the salary received for part-time teaching.</item>
                
                <item langue="en">These credits may be used as long as she/he is a member of the APTPUO and obtains and
                    teaches at least one (1) course per twenty-four (24) month period.</item>
                
                <item langue="en">These credits may be applied to tuition in credit courses (but not incidental fees)
                    for the member's spouse, dependent children under 26 years of age, and, in the case of members who
                    are not full-time students, the member herself/himself.</item>
                
                <item langue="en">Part-time regular professors may take courses at the University, free of charge, if
                    these courses are recommended in writing by the department as being necessary to improve or increase
                    his/her teaching competence within the department and such recommendation is forwarded to the
                    management of Academic Labour Relations. Such a recommendation is not required for courses taken by
                    a professor to improve his/her competence in one of the official languages.</item>
            </list>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">TUITION FEE CREDIT PLAN</title>
            <section>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The refunds described in this article apply to government funded courses
                    that earn university credits in full time programs of study funded by the
                    government.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The member’s child or dependent must pay incidental
                    fees.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The spouse, child or dependent who wishes to apply for a refund of
                    tuition fees must complete the appropriate form available from Human Resources. The duly completed
                    form must be returned to Human Resources before May 30 for the spring session, before July 30 for
                    the summer session, before September 30 for the fall session, and before January 30 for the winter
                    session. Payments will be made only upon receipt of an application within the established time
                    limits. Applications not received within the prescribed time limits will not be considered initially
                    for payment of the benefit. Late applications submitted for each session will be considered only
                    after all timely applications have been processed, and by December 15 at the latest. No applications
                    will be accepted for a semester other than the current term. </paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en" prefixMark="y">The annual cost for the University of the Tuition Fee
                    Credit Plan shall never exceed $60,000 per academic year divided in three (3) sessions with a
                    partial credit at the beginning of the session and a further credit when it has been established
                    that the fund has not been oversubscribed until such time as all the monies have been allocated as
                    credits. Application will be made on the basis of one session at a time on the form provided by
                    Human Resources.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">In the case of part time students, payment will be calculated
                    proportionally based on the number of courses required for the full time
                    program.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en" prefixMark="y">The maximum amount per member, spouse, or dependent will
                    be $2,000 per academic session.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The tuition fee assistance is a taxable benefit. This assistance is
                    taxable as income to the member, unless it can be used as a scholarship by the spouse, children or
                    dependents, in which case it becomes taxable as income to the recipient. In this case, and if the
                    rules of the Canada Revenue Agency (CRA) allow the allocation of a scholarship, the value represents
                    85% of the amount normally awarded. “Tuition fees” are costs defined by the CRA for the purpose of
                    tax deductions.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">If the value of eligible applications under this plan is less than the
                    total amount available, the surplus will be carried over and added to the amount available the
                    following year beginning May 1, to a maximum of twice the annual amount set out in 10.14.4. If there
                    is a deficit in any given year due to unforeseen circumstances, the deficit will be carried over to
                    the following year beginning May 1. This deficit will be examined to determine its source and to
                    evaluate, in consultation with the APTPUO, the changes to be made to administrative processes to
                    avoid it happening again. If amounts are returned after their distribution, they will be deposited
                    in the fund.</paragraph-numbered>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">PENSION PLAN</title>
            <section>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The Employer agrees to maintain a defined contribution Pension Plan for
                    the benefit of members of the bargaining unit at the earliest opportunity.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The Plan became effective January 1, 1991. The defined contribution is
                    set at 7% for both the Employer and the member, as of April 1, 2009.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The Plan is open to all members of the bargaining unit who have worked
                    during the previous calendar year and who elect to participate in the Plan.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The Plan contains a two (2) year vesting provision whereby a member who
                    withdraws from the Plan prior to vesting will be entitled to withdraw only her/his own contributions
                    plus interest and if a member withdraws from the Plan after vesting, she/he will be entitled to
                    withdraw both her/his contributions and the Employer's contributions plus interest on condition that
                    they are transferred into a locked-in fund.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">There shall be a Pension Plan Committee to administer the Plan and the
                    Committee shall have equal Employer-member representation.</paragraph-numbered>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">COPYRIGHT</title>
            <section>
                
                <title langue="en">INTELLECTUAL PROPERTY RIGHTS</title>
                <section>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Except as provided for in 10.16.1.3, the parties agree that the
                        member holds the copyright with respect to any original work produced even where such work was
                        produced with the use of Employer facilities, support personnel or services where such use does
                        not result in additional cost to the Employer.</paragraph-numbered>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Where the original work was produced with the use of Employer
                        facilities, support personnel, or services and such use results in additional cost to the
                        Employer, the member retains the copyright with respect thereto subject to the
                        following.</paragraph-numbered>
                    <list Type="Alpha">
                        
                        <item langue="en">The member shall advise the Employer of the additional cost incurred,
                            and</item>
                        
                        <item langue="en">the member shall enter into an agreement to reimburse the Employer for any
                            additional costs, it being understood that the Employer may waive such payment in exchange
                            for a share of the proceeds of exploitation as agreed to by the member.</item>
                    </list>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Where the original work was produced as a result of a specific
                        written request of the Employer, agreed to by the member, the Employer shall hold the
                        copyright.The Employer will send a copy of the request to the APTPUO and any agreement given by
                        the member will be valid only for 20 days after receipt of the request by the APTPUO and can be
                        withdrawn by the member during those 20 days.</paragraph-numbered>
                </section>
            </section>
            <section>
                
                <title langue="en">COMMERCIAL EXPLOITATION AND USE</title>
                <section>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">a) The parties agree that no commercial exploitation of an original
                        work described in 10.16.1.3 shall be undertaken without the consent of the
                        member.</paragraph-numbered>
                    
                    <paragraph langue="en">b) Subject to 10.16.3.1, the employer may enter into an agreement with the
                        member regarding the commercial exploitation of an original work for which the member holds the
                        copyright.</paragraph>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">It is understood that the member shall grant to the Employer a
                        non-exclusive, royalty-free, irrevocable and non-transferable right to use any work developed
                        pursuant to 10.16.1 for a minimum of 2 years for University purposes.After such time, the member
                        may withdraw this right.</paragraph-numbered>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The permission given under 10.16.2.2 does not include the right to
                        use course notes, that is, material prepared by the member for his use in interpreting or
                        presenting the content of his course material or as a tool to assist in delivering the course,
                        either in handwritten or other notes. Without limiting the interpretation of the preceding
                        sentence, the expression “course notes” does not include laboratory manuals distributed to
                        students.</paragraph-numbered>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The permission given under 10.16.2.2 does not include the right to
                        use the original work on line, or for purposes other than those for which it was originally
                        produced, or to alter the work in any way, including its content, format or medium, without the
                        member’s consent. When the work is translated, the member will approve the translation and may
                        request that his name not be used with the translated work.</paragraph-numbered>
                </section>
            </section>
            <section>
                
                <title langue="en">DISTRIBUTION OF REVENUE</title>
                <section>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The Employer shall remit to the member 50% of the net revenue the
                        Employer receives from the commercial exploitation of any of the original works referred to in
                        10.16.1.3.When the Employer and member have entered into an agreement for the commercial
                        exploitation by the Employer of an original work for which the member holds the copyright, as
                        described in 10.16.2.1 b), the agreement must specify that the Employer must remit to the member
                        75% of the net revenue that the Employer receives from this commercial
                        exploitation.</paragraph-numbered>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Where the work is authored by more than one person, the Employer
                        shall determine the amount payable to each, based upon the relative contribution of each to the
                        work.</paragraph-numbered>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">"Net revenue" in 10.16.3.1 means any money received as a result of
                        the development or commercial exploitation of the works described in 10.15.1, less any expenses
                        incurred by the Employer or by any agent or agency retained by the Employer to exploit the work
                        commercially.</paragraph-numbered>
                    
                    <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The Employer shall, on an annual basis, provide the author with an
                        internally audited accounting of the proceeds and expenses related to the exploitation of the
                        work.Further, the author shall have open access to all financial documentation, agreements,
                        contracts, statements and other information required to verify compliance with this
                        subsection.</paragraph-numbered>
                </section>
            </section>
        </section>
    </article>
    <article>
        
        <title langue="en">EVALUATION</title>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">EVALUATIONS AVAILABLE TO THE CHAIRPERSON</title>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">Employees will receive in a timely fashion any copies of the A-report of the
                evaluation of their teaching by students which become available. Should any employee wish to comment on
                this report or to have associated with it any other material which might bear on the interpretation of
                that report, the employee shall send a letter to the chairperson including (a) a copy of the A-report
                concerned, (b) any comments the employee wishes to make, and (c) any other relevant material. This
                submission by the employee shall be retained by the department or academic unit and shall be considered
                whenever A-reports of the employee are reviewed.</paragraph>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">EVALUATIONS FOR THE PURPOSES OF DEVELOPMENT OF TEACHING SKILLS</title>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">Part-time academic staff shall have access to the evaluation and advisory services of
                the Teaching and Learning Support Service on the same basis as full-time academic staff.</paragraph>
        </section>
    </article>
    <article>
        
        <title langue="en">DURATION AND MODIFICATION OF AGREEMENT</title>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">DURATION OF AGREEMENT</title>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">This Agreement shall continue in force and effect from September 1, 2007 to August
                31, 2010 and shall be renewed automatically thereafter for a period of one (1) year unless either party
                notifies the other in writing prior to April 1, 2010, that it desires to amend and terminate this
                Agreement. Where notice to amend the Agreement is given, the provisions of this Agreement shall continue
                in force until a new Agreement is signed or the right to strike or lockout accrues, whichever first
                occurs.</paragraph>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <paragraph-numbered langue="en">This agreement may be amended by mutual written
                consent.</paragraph-numbered>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">NO STRIKE/NO LOCKOUT</title>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">For the duration of this Agreement, the Employer and the Union agree as
                follows:</paragraph>
            <list Type="Alpha">
                
                <item langue="en">The Employer shall not call a lockout and the members of the APTPUO shall not take any
                    form of strike action, work stoppage or work slowdown.</item>
                
                <item langue="en">The APTPUO shall take all necessary measures to avoid or discourage picketing,
                    information picketing or similar demonstrations that its members might undertake, individually or in
                    groups, in the context of a labour relations dispute, to disrupt the work and services of the
                    University of Ottawa.</item>
            </list>
        </section>
        <section>
            
            <title langue="en">OTHER UNION STRIKES</title>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">In the event that employees of the University of Ottawa, other than those covered by
                this Agreement, engage in a strike and/or maintain picket lines, employees covered by this Agreement
                shall continue to report to work and carry out their regular duties but shall not be required to perform
                work normally done by those employees.</paragraph>
        </section>
    </article>
    <signature>
        
        <paragraph langue="en">IN WITNESS WHEREOF, the Parties have hereunto affixed their hands at the City of Ottawa,
            on the 12th day of December 2011.</paragraph>
        
        <paragraph langue="en">Association des professeur(e)s à temps partiel de l’Université d’Ottawa Association of
            Part-time Professors of the University of Ottawa </paragraph>
        
        <person langue="en">Greer Knox</person>
    </signature>
    <appendix>
        
        <title langue="en"/>
        <leaveBlank/>
    </appendix>
    <appendix>
        
        <title langue="en">GUIDELINES FOR ESTABLISHING THE RATING OF APPLICANTS FOR PART-TIME TEACHING POSITIONS
            ACCORDING TO PARAGRAPH 5.7.2</title>
        <sub-appendix>
            <list Type="Numeric">
                
                <item langue="en">Required and desired qualifications should be clearly set out in postings and should
                    accurately reflect the level and degree of specialization of the course, as well as the difficulty,
                    extent of research orientation, and the rapidity of change of the material to be covered. Aspects of
                    points 3, 4 and 5 below, which relate to ratings, also have bearing on what constitutes required or
                    desired qualifications. If the doctorate is a required qualification, the posting must so specify.
                    If the doctorate is not required, then, in disciplines in which regular university faculty normally
                    hold a doctorate, a doctorate may be considered a desirable qualification, whether it is explicitly
                    mentioned in the posting or not.</item>
                
                <item langue="en">In evaluating candidates and establishing ratings, the required and desired
                    qualifications shall not differ significantly from those set out in the posting.</item>
                
                <item langue="en"> In distinguishing among rating Categories A, B and C, consideration must be given to
                    the level of the course. Consequently, for basic undergraduate courses of a general nature, a
                    correspondingly greater emphasis must be given to the combination of teaching experience and level
                    of teaching competence first in the area and then in related areas, while for higher level courses,
                    or courses in very specialized areas, a greater emphasis may need to be placed on the level of
                    achievement in various aspects of scholarly activity and research, while recognizing that at least
                    satisfactory performance as a teacher is required. For courses lying in between these two extremes,
                    balance between teaching experience and quality of teaching on one hand, and scholarly activities on
                    the other, shall reflect the level of the course.</item>
                
                <item langue="en">In distinguishing between applicants who fall into Category A and applicants who fall
                    into Category B, there must be the expectation that the course would be significantly improved if
                    given by an applicant in Category B, rather than by an applicant in Category A. The expectation of
                    significant improvement in a course shall be based upon the abilities of the candidate as a teacher
                    and as a scholar. The same is true for the distinction between Category B and C. Differences among
                    applicants which are unlikely to have a noticeable impact on the course to be taught should not
                    normally result in different rating categories.</item>
                
                <item langue="en">In judging an applicant to be in Category C, which implies a distinct superiority over
                    all other applicants, care must be taken to ensure that the areas of superiority bear a clear
                    relationship to the nature and/or content of the course, and/or to the attractiveness of the course
                    to potential students.</item>
                
                <item langue="en">In courses which have a professional component, or which are part of professional
                    programs, activity outside the University, which constitutes a contribution to that profession or to
                    a related profession, should be taken into consideration.</item>
                
                <item langue="en">Deans shall endeavour to ensure that criteria and practices reflect this appendix,
                    and, within a given department, do not experience a notable discontinuity, (e.g. due to a change of
                    director or the like).</item>
            </list>
        </sub-appendix>
    </appendix>
    <appendix>
        
        <title langue="en">REPORT ON HIRING</title>
    </appendix>
    <appendix>
        
        <title langue="en">SALARY AND RATES OF PAY</title>
        <sub-appendix>
            
            <title langue="en">GENERAL</title>
            <sub-appendix>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The minimum salary or hourly rates shall apply to members appointed
                    under Article 5 of this Collective Agreement.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">Portions of courses or courses with different credit value shall be paid
                    on a pro rata basis.</paragraph-numbered>
                
                <paragraph-numbered langue="en">The rates set out below shall apply to all members appointed to perform
                    bargaining unit work to commence on or after September 1, 2010.</paragraph-numbered>
            </sub-appendix>
        </sub-appendix>
        <leaveBlank/>
    </appendix>
    <appendix>
        
        <title langue="en">ACADEMIC AND PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT FUND</title>
        <sub-appendix>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">The Academic and Professional Development Fund is created by the Collective Agreement
                between APTPUO and the University of Ottawa. It is administered by a selection committee which operates
                within guidelines agreed to by the parties.</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">The purpose of the Academic and Professional Development Fund is to promote research
                and participation in scholarly activities on the part of part-time academic staff.</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">Scholarly activities are those which contribute:</paragraph>
            <list Type="Alpha">
                
                <item langue="en">through research, to the advancement of knowledge in a discipline;</item>
                
                <item langue="en">through artistic or literary creation, to the advancement of the arts and the
                    letters;</item>
                
                <item langue="en">through various professional activities, to the advancement of a profession.</item>
            </list>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">The fund provides three types of grants:</paragraph>
            <list Type="Numeric">
                
                <item langue="en">Travel grants for participation in conferences.</item>
                
                <item langue="en">Research grants.</item>
                
                <item langue="en">Publication grants.</item>
            </list>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">Grants under points 1 and 2 above may include stipends with the provision that the
                guidelines for payment of stipends have been adhered to (Appendix "F").</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">Presented below is information on each type of grant: it covers the elements to be
                contained in the application, the guidelines used by the Academic and Professional Development Fund
                Committee in the attribution of grants, and the types of expenses funded.</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">Members of the APTPUO bargaining unit, and those persons still maintaining seniority
                under the collective agreement are eligible to apply to the Academic and Professional Development
                Fund.</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">GENERAL:</paragraph>
            <list Type="Numeric">
                
                <item langue="en">All applications shall be treated as confidential by the Committee.</item>
                
                <item langue="en">Applications must be submitted in four (4) copies to the office of the University
                    Chief Negotiator.</item>
                
                <item langue="en">Committee decisions are final. The Committee may respond, on request, to an appeal of
                    a decision rendered and/or provide advice to unsuccessful applicants with a view to improving the
                    quality of their future applications. The Committee may send a decision for review to the
                    Labour/Management Committee in the case of an appeal on which the members do not agree.</item>
                
                <item langue="en">The Selection Committee may meet, but is not required to meet to reach a decision in a
                    particular case. In the event of a decision without a meeting (a) before a decision is finalized,
                    each committee member will be made aware of the views of the other two members, and (b) decision
                    shall be by majority vote. If a meeting takes place, a quorum shall be all three members.</item>
                
                <item langue="en">The fund will not be used to fund thesis research directly but may be used to fund
                    presentation of thesis findings at a conference, publication in scholarly journals, or travel
                    essential to the research (as verified by the thesis supervisor) provided that funds were not
                    obtained from other funding sources leading to a refund greater than the expenses incurred. If a
                    member is writing a thesis and applies for a grant for a research project that he/she believes is
                    not related to the thesis and therefore is not affected by the foregoing, he/she must provide, with
                    the application, a statement from the thesis supervisor stating that the research project is not
                    related to the thesis or has only tenuous links with it.</item>
                
                <item langue="en">Deadlines: For conferences, applications must normally be submitted three months in
                    advance. This deadline will be strictly adhered to in the case of the Learned Societies meeting and
                    other major conferences. Under no circumstances will retroactive funding be approved except under
                    exceptional circumstances.</item>
                
                <item langue="en">In any given year, priority will be given to applicants who did not receive a grant
                    the previous session.</item>
                
                <item langue="en">If, for one of the grant types in the Academic and Professional Development Fund, an
                    amount said to be “reserved for a given academic year” remains unspent four months before the end of
                    that academic year whereas the rest of the Fund has been used, the Selection Committee will assign
                    the unspent amount to other requests complying with Appendix E.</item>
                
                <item langue="en">The University will issue a Canada Customs and Revenue Agency T4A form for each amount
                    granted from the Fund (CRA).</item>
            </list>
            
            <title langue="en">TRAVEL GRANTS</title>
            <sub-appendix>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">TYPE A: Presentation of papers or similar activities</paragraph>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">A member may not receive more than $2,500 for this purpose in one academic
                    year.</paragraph>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">Applications</paragraph>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">Completed applications must include the following items:</paragraph>
                <list Type="Alpha">
                    
                    <item langue="en">a description of the conference which the applicant wishes to attend (dates,
                        place, conference organizers, type of conference and the program if possible);</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">a description of the nature of participation in the conference (presenting a
                        paper, or similar activity);</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">an abstract of the paper or description of the academic activity accompanied, if
                        possible, by confirmation of its acceptance by the conference organizers; if confirmation of
                        acceptance is not immediately available, a conditional award may be granted;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">a letter of support from the applicant's department chairperson or from an
                        established researcher in the field, indicating that participation in the proposed conference is
                        a useful and meaningful contribution. When there is more than one applicant from a given
                        department for a particular conference, the department chairperson must give a priority
                        ranking;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">an itemized budget covering transportation costs, hotel costs, and per diem costs
                        for food as specified in the university travel regulations;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">an up-to-date C.V. of the applicant;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">proof of teaching at the University of Ottawa in the last 24 months (photocopy of
                        TP form preferred).</item>
                </list>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">Factors used in the attribution of travel grants:</paragraph>
                <list Type="Alpha">
                    
                    <item langue="en">availability of funds in the Academic and Professional Development Fund;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">previous scholarly activities of the applicant;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">nature of the conference;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">pertinence of the conference to the applicant's teaching and research;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">nature of the applicant's participation as revealed by the abstract of the paper
                        or the description of the activity to be presented, correspondence from the conference
                        organizers, program, etc.;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">other funding available to or received by applicant for the same conference e.g.
                        GSA, Learned Society.</item>
                </list>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">N.B. Evidence of partial support from another body is considered a positive
                    factor in the evaluation of the application.</paragraph>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">Funding granted</paragraph>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">Applicants who are recommended for funding will normally receive a refund
                    for:</paragraph>
                <list Type="Alpha">
                    
                    <item langue="en">transportation costs - (i) APEX fare or equivalent for a conference abroad, (ii)
                        excursion fare or equivalent for a conference in Canada and</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">registration fees.</item>
                </list>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">The Committee may also grant refunds for hotel costs and/or per diem if these can
                    be granted without unduly restricting the success rate of applications. The Committee may also grant
                    a stipend subject to the rules for payment of stipends (Appendix “F”).</paragraph>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">TYPE B: Attendance at a conference</paragraph>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">A sum not exceeding $17,500 will be set aside from the total Academic and
                    Professional Development Fund budget in the 2010-2011, 2011-2012, and 2012-2013 academic years for
                    special travel grants to attend a conference. A member may not receive more than $2,500 for this
                    purpose in one academic year.</paragraph>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">The candidate must provide a clear statement of how attendance at the conference
                    will enhance his/her teaching.</paragraph>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">The chair and/or dean concerned must recommend the applicant and attest to his or
                    her belief that such attendance will in fact enhance the quality of the applicant's
                    teaching.</paragraph>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">All other procedures and directives for Type A grants as described above apply
                    mutatis mutandis.</paragraph>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">On their return, recipients of Type A and Type B travel grants must forward a
                    copy of their plane, train, or bus ticket to the Office of the Chief Negotiator, together with a
                    brief report concerning the activity for which the grant was awarded, it being understood that
                    future applications for grants from the Fund will not be processed until members have complied with
                    this provision.</paragraph>
            </sub-appendix>
            
            <title langue="en">RESEARCH GRANT</title>
            <sub-appendix>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">An amount not exceeding $15,000 of the Fund will be set aside during the
                    2010-2011, 2011-2012, and 2012-2013 academic years for research grants. A member may not receive
                    more than $2,500 in research grants in one academic year.</paragraph>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">APPLICATIONS</paragraph>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">Applications should include the following items:</paragraph>
                <list Type="Alpha">
                    
                    <item langue="en">a two-page description of the research project (objectives, methodology, research
                        schedule, importance, link with applicant's current teaching and/or research activities or
                        dissertation);</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">a letter of support from the applicant's department chairperson or from an
                        established researcher in the field stating that the research being proposed is a valid and
                        meaningful contribution;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">an itemized budget for funds requested (with justification): the budget may
                        include items such as research supplies, photocopying, postage, and research travel; if a
                        research stipend is requested either for the applicant or for a research assistant, the
                        applicant must follow the rules for payment of stipends (Appendix "F");</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">an up-to-date C.V. of the applicant;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">proof of teaching at the University of Ottawa in the last 24 months (photocopy of
                        TP form preferred);</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">other sources of funding to which application has been made and results of such
                        application.</item>
                </list>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">When a research grant involves an award for travel, the recipient must provide a
                    copy of the plane, train, or bus ticket to the Chief Negotiator. At the completion of the research
                    activity for which a research grant was awarded, the member will provide a brief report concerning
                    that activity. It is understood that future applications for grants from the Fund will not be
                    processed until members have complied with these provisions.</paragraph>
            </sub-appendix>
            
            <title langue="en">PUBLICATION GRANT</title>
            <sub-appendix>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">APPLICATIONS</paragraph>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">A sum not exceeding $10,000 of the total Academic and Professional Development
                    Fund budget will be set aside in the 2010-2011, 2011-2012, and 2012-2013 academic years for
                    publication grants. That portion of the Academic and Professional Development Fund destined for aid
                    to publication is meant only to supplement other grants or assistance. A member may not receive more
                    than $2,500 in publication grants during an academic year.</paragraph>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">Applications for works already published will not be accepted unless the
                    publication date falls within the academic year in which the application is made.</paragraph>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">Applications should include the following items:</paragraph>
                <list Type="Alpha">
                    
                    <item langue="en">a two-page description of the work to be published, importance, link with
                        applicant's current teaching and/or research activities or dissertation;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">information about publication grants requested from other agencies, as well as the
                        reports of expert evaluators requested by such agencies, or where the texts of such expert
                        evaluations are not transmitted to the person requesting the grant, at least the granting
                        agency's decision on the application, together with its reasons for accepting or rejecting the
                        application;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">where the work has been published, independent evaluations of the academic value
                        and usefulness of the work;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">an itemized budget, or where the work has been published, full details of
                        publication costs, amounts paid, and sources of these amounts;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">an updated C.V. of the applicant;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">proof of teaching at the University of Ottawa in the last 24 months (photocopy of
                        TP form preferred);</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">other sources of funding to which application has been made and results of such
                        application.</item>
                </list>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">If a publication grant is awarded, the member will provide to the Chief
                    Negotiator a brief written report containing publication data concerning the work for which the
                    publication grant was awarded.</paragraph>
                
                <paragraph langue="en">Factors used in the attribution of research and publication grants:</paragraph>
                <list Type="Alpha">
                    
                    <item langue="en">availability of funds in the Academic and Professional Development Fund;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">scholarly merit of the research project, or value to scholars of the proposed
                        publication;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">previous scholarly activities of the applicant;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">link between the research project or proposed publication and the applicant's
                        current teaching and/or research activities or dissertation;</item>
                    
                    <item langue="en">availability of other sources of funding.</item>
                </list>
            </sub-appendix>
        </sub-appendix>
    </appendix>
    <appendix>
        
        <title langue="en">RULES FOR PAYMENT OF RESEARCH STIPENDS TO APPLICANTS</title>
        <sub-appendix>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">Academic and Professional Development Fund</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">The Academic and Professional Development Fund (APDF), as administered by the APDF
                Committee, has internal procedures for the determination of grants for expenses incurred by the
                applicants in the completion of approved projects.</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">In certain circumscribed circumstances, the APDF may be used to pay stipends directly
                to applicants as compensation. The Committee may allocate APDF funds to such stipends if one or more of
                the following conditions is met:</paragraph>
            <list Type="Numeric">
                
                <item langue="en">The member holds a teaching contract under this collective agreement, and must
                    interrupt it for one or more classes in order to carry out the approved project. In this event, the
                    Committee may allocate a sum up to the amount which the member would have earned if that(those)
                    class(es) had been given by the member.</item>
                
                <item langue="en">A department, which has previously employed the member as a part-time teacher,
                    supports the project and the payment of a stipend and also contributes economic resources towards
                    the project. In this event, the APDF Committee may allocate some resources for a research stipend.
                    The applicant may not be a graduate student.</item>
                
                <item langue="en">The APDF Committee may allocate resources for a research stipend if (a) the project
                    causes the applicant to give up a teaching contract already offered, (b) the applicant is a member
                    of the APTPUO, and (c) the applicant is not a graduate student. The stipend shall not exceed the
                    value of the foregone contract.</item>
            </list>
        </sub-appendix>
    </appendix>
    <appendix>
        
        <title langue="en">POSTING</title>
    </appendix>
    <appendix>
        
        <title langue="en">PROCEDURES TO ACCESS INFORMATION</title>
        <sub-appendix>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">Article 5.8 of the collective agreement sets out how employee seniority is to be
                calculated. The Union, the University and employees have a shared interest and responsibility to ensure
                the accuracy of employee the seniority list.</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">The University collects, uses and discloses contracts, notices of service to the
                Union, research grant awards (referred to herein as "the employee records") for the purpose of
                calculating employee seniority. The Union and the University agree that this information is personal
                information as defined in FIPPA and as such must be collected, used and disclosed in compliance with
                that Act and the law.</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">Access Process The following shall apply when the Union wishes to have access to the
                employee records for the purpose of determining whether or not employee seniority has been correctly
                calculated by the University:</paragraph>
            <list Type="Numeric">
                
                <item langue="en">The official representative of the Union shall advise the University in writing of the
                    name(s) of the employee(s) whose employee records they require access to. The letter shall reference
                    this Appendix and describe the purpose of the request.</item>
                
                <item langue="en">The official representative shall advise the employee(s) whose employee records they
                    are seeking access to in writing, with a copy to the Employer. The letter shall reference this
                    Appendix and describe the purpose of the request.</item>
                
                <item langue="en">The Employer will review the employee records in question and provide a copy to the
                    official representative.</item>
                
                <item langue="en">The Union agrees to collect, safeguard, use and disclose the employee records in
                    accordance with the Union's privacy policy and the law.</item>
                
                <item langue="en">The Union agrees to use the employee records only for the purpose of determining
                    member seniority.</item>
                
                <item langue="en">The Union will store the employee records in a secure location and limit access to the
                    employee records to Union representatives who are carrying out a review of the contested seniority
                    ranking. The Union will destroy the employee records once the seniority review process is
                    finalized.</item>
                
                <item langue="en">The Union will provide the University with a copy of its privacy policy upon request
                    by the University.</item>
                
                <item langue="en">The Union agrees to indemnify and save harmless the Employer from any complaint or
                    cause of action arising from the Union's collection, use and disclosure of the employee
                    records.</item>
            </list>
        </sub-appendix>
    </appendix>
    <appendix>
        
        <title langue="en">LETTERS OF UNDERSTANDING</title>
        <sub-appendix>
            
            <title langue="en">ANNUAL STUDENT HANDBOOK</title>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">Where a department publishes an annual student handbook that contains the names and
                university degrees of its regular professors, the chair will ensure that the names of all part-time
                professors currently teaching in the department, together with their university degrees, appear also,
                provided that the part-time professor has indicated in writing that he or she wishes his or her name to
                appear.</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">Only the names and degrees of those part-time professors who have responded
                affirmatively in writing to the chair's written request concerning the above will be included in the
                handbook, provided the part-time professor provides the information requested within the deadline stated
                by the chair in the original request.</paragraph>
        </sub-appendix>
        <sub-appendix>
            
            <title langue="en">LANGUAGE COURSES</title>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">Language courses offered to University personnel will be open to members of APTPUO
                beginning in the Fall term 1993.</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">Immediately following the deadline for registration for full-time staff, the
                University Chief Negotiator will advise APTPUO of the number of vacant places remaining.</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">APTPUO members may register on a first-come first-served basis by following the
                procedures employed by the Official Languages and Bilingualism Institute.</paragraph>
        </sub-appendix>
        <sub-appendix>
            
            <title langue="en">PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT FUND</title>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">Notwithstanding article 3.4 of the Agreement, the University and the APTPUO agree to
                form a joint committee made up of three APTPUO representatives and three Employer representatives to
                study and evaluate the operation of the committee responsible for managing the Professional Development
                Fund. Its duties are to review the committee's make-up, rules, operating procedures and decision-making
                process and to then submit recommendations to the Labour-Management Committee.</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">The joint committee must be created no later than thirty (30) days after this
                Agreement is ratified by both parties.</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph langue="en">The joint committee's period of operation and the deadlines involved are to be agreed
                on by the Labour-Management Committee.</paragraph>
        </sub-appendix>
    </appendix>
</agreement>